<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Odos gath operbochēns the more excellent way to edifie the Church of Christ, or, A discourse concerning love : the design of which is to revive that grace (now under such decays) among Protestants of all perswasions / by Nathanael Vincent ...</title>
            <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 242 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12241760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12241760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64966)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 620:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Odos gath operbochēns the more excellent way to edifie the Church of Christ, or, A discourse concerning love : the design of which is to revive that grace (now under such decays) among Protestants of all perswasions / by Nathanael Vincent ...</title>
                  <author>Vincent, Nathanael, 1639?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 152 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.A. for T. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians IV, 16 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Love --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56801:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56801:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;</p>
            <p>THE More Excellent Way TO Edifie the Church of CHRIST OR A DISCOURSE CONCERNING LOVE: The Deſign of which is to Revive that Grace (now under ſuch decays) among <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of ALL perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL VINCENT,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Pet. 4. 8.</bibl> 
               <hi>And above all things have fervent Charity among your ſelves.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Phil. 4. 5.</bibl> 
               <hi>Let your Moderation be known unto all men, the Lord is at hand.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Gal. 5. 15.</bibl> 
               <hi>But if ye bite and devour one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>Chryſoſt. in 1 Cor.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the Bible and three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chappel</hi> and at the Bible on <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> near the Gate. 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56801:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56801:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>ALthough</hi> my Name <hi>be in the mouths of many, and</hi> Tongues <hi>have</hi> ſcourg'd <hi>it moſt ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and</hi> moſt falſe Reports <hi>have been ſpread concerning me both in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; yet I could more patiently have born the</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>of</hi> my Reputation, <hi>if the</hi> Honour <hi>of</hi> God <hi>had not been at all concerned. A regard to</hi> his Name, <hi>and his</hi> Goſpel's Credit, <hi>prevails with me to break ſilence; and</hi> Love to others, <hi>makes me fear their being</hi> ſcandalized <hi>to their prejudice. There is a deſign driven on by Hell and</hi> Rome, <hi>to introduce</hi> Atheiſm <hi>in order unto</hi> Propery; <hi>to make men really of</hi> no <hi>Religion, that they may not ſtick to profeſs themſelves of the</hi> Romiſh, <hi>when they ſhall apprehend 'tis for their</hi> Secular Intereſt. <hi>Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome mens lives by the Grace of God have been unblameable, and tended to convince the World, that there is a</hi> reality <hi>and</hi> power <hi>in Godlineſs; theſe upon this account are ſingled out, and loaded with Calumnies and Reproaches; that being repreſented
<pb facs="tcp:56801:3"/> as</hi> Hypocrites, <hi>all Religion may the more eaſily be ſuſpected, as a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Pet. 1. 16.</note> cunningly deviſed. Fable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let not thoſe who have ſtupified their</hi> own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, think that I have acted of late againſt</hi> Mine. <hi>Though I think I ought not to keep at ſuch a</hi> diſtance <hi>from the</hi> Church of England, <hi>as I did; yet I have</hi> no preferment <hi>in it, neither</hi> can I ſubmit to the terms <hi>of ſuch preferment. Nay, I have</hi> exceedingly hindred <hi>my</hi> own ſecular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, <hi>by my</hi> Moderation, <hi>which is not the way to thrive in ſuch a</hi> Violent Age <hi>as this. A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate man is like one that parts two which are fighting; instead of being</hi> thank'd, <hi>he is</hi> lik'd by neither; <hi>he has</hi> blowes <hi>from</hi> both, <hi>for wiſhing them no</hi> worſe <hi>a thing than</hi> Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From prophane tongues I expect lies and ſlanders: That Maſter whom I ſerve, met with no better uſage. He was called a</hi> Wine-bibber, <hi>a</hi> Friend to Publicans and Sinners; <hi>nay, ſaid to have a</hi> Devil. <hi>But though the</hi> Slander <hi>be never ſo</hi> groſs, <hi>it ſhall not hinder me from</hi> praying <hi>for the</hi> Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer; <hi>and I hope I ſhall be enabled to</hi> live <hi>ſo ſtill, as</hi> that no body ſhall believe him. <hi>If Profeſſors who are</hi> Non-conformiſts, <hi>ſpeak againſt me, and cenſure me as a</hi> Temporizer; <hi>My Anſwer is, That</hi> with me 'tis a ſmall thing to be judged of them, or of mans judgment. <hi>My own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſpeaks other kind of language; and in that one, I have</hi> Mille teſtes, <hi>a thouſand Witneſſes of my Integrity. God is convincing me of the</hi> vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:56801:3"/> 
               <hi>of</hi> popular Applauſe; <hi>and how ſoon that kind of</hi> wind <hi>may</hi> turn <hi>and</hi> change. <hi>And if a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of this makes me</hi> more humble and low in my own eyes, <hi>Diſhonour will do me a</hi> far greater kindneſs <hi>than Praiſe. I will ſay to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> O &amp; praeſidium, &amp; dulce decus meum, <hi>my</hi> ſafety, <hi>and ſweet</hi> Ornament; <hi>and next unto Heaven, expect the greateſt</hi> reſt to my Soul, <hi>in the exerciſe of this lovely Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fury of thoſe who have been most, enraged againſt me, has but heightned my love to them: I have poured out more prayers and tears for them than they are aware of; and they will know what a true Friend I have been to them, when they come into another World. Thoſe whoſe</hi> Heads <hi>are</hi> hotter <hi>than their</hi> Love, <hi>ſhall not move my</hi> anger, <hi>but my</hi> pity <hi>and</hi> ſorrow: <hi>And let them call me what they pleaſe, I ſhall own what is good in them; and requite their</hi> Cenſures <hi>with</hi> Supplications, <hi>that their</hi> Light <hi>and</hi> Faith, <hi>their</hi> Humility <hi>and</hi> Love <hi>may be encreaſed; and that they may do nothing unbecoming the</hi> Children <hi>of the</hi> God of love and peace; <hi>nothing prejudicial to the</hi> Church, <hi>or to</hi> themſelves!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have preached heretofore to multitudes, while I was permitted: For all the Churches in</hi> London <hi>not being able to hold the</hi> tenth part <hi>of</hi> all <hi>the Inhabitants, I thought they had better hear a</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine agreeable to the Articles of the Church of England, <hi>from</hi> my mouth, <hi>than not</hi> hear at all. <hi>But it never was my practice to</hi> preach up
<pb facs="tcp:56801:4"/> a party; <hi>and it troubles me to ſee how much of Religion is placed in</hi> ſmaller things, <hi>as appears by mens eagerneſs about them: As if ſome thought a</hi> Church, <hi>others thought a</hi> Conventicle <hi>like the</hi> Ark <hi>of</hi> Noah, <hi>out of which 'tis impoſſible to eſcape</hi> drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Perdition. <hi>My deſign all along was to</hi> bring men to God by Faith in Jeſus; <hi>and that</hi> their hearts <hi>might be purified, and to perſwade them to be</hi> holy in all manner of Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>I confeſs I am</hi> ſomewhat altered <hi>from what I was; but 'tis in the</hi> extenſiveneſs of my love: <hi>But I am perſwaded that this is an alteration for the</hi> better, <hi>and makes me more to</hi> reſemble Chriſt. <hi>Who can juſtly blame me for imitating the</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Jeſus! <hi>who loves</hi> all ſincere Proteſtants, <hi>of</hi> all <hi>perſwaſions, and has</hi> Communion <hi>with them</hi> all. <hi>I add no more but that of the Apoſtle,</hi> Rom. 15. 7. Wherefore receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo received us to the glory of God.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56801:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EPH. IV. 16. latter part.</bibl>
               <q>—Maketh Increaſe of the Body, unto the Edifying of it ſelf in Love.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I had a voice as loud as Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I would cry <hi>Fire, Fire,</hi> with a wiſh that all <hi>England</hi> might hear. A Flame is kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led much <hi>worſe</hi> than that which <hi>burnt down</hi> London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which threatens both Church and State with ruine: and that is, the Flame of fierce <hi>Contention.</hi> Mens Hearts are as <hi>hot as Hell;</hi> their Tongues do <hi>ſet on fire the courſe of Nature;</hi> ſuch wrath, ſuch bitterneſs, ſuch animoſities every where appear, as plainly ſhew the body Politick and Body Myſtical are in a dangerous fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and Feaver, which I wiſh may not iſſue in diſſolution and deſtruction. That Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of our Lord is fulfilled; <hi>Iniquity ſhall abound, and love ſhall wax cold.</hi> Luſt indeed breaks out into a flame; mens Paſſions are hot unto the higheſt degree, and fury makes them
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56801:5"/> abound in tranſgreſſion; but a deadly damp has ſeiz'd on Love. No wonder that the Churches pulſe does beat diſorderly, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſhe is languiſhing, and ready to dye, for Love is the cauſe of her increaſe and Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            <p>Is there no Balm in <hi>Gilead?</hi> is there not a Phyſitian there? are the ſpots and ſymptoms ſuch as ſhew the diſeaſe is mortal, and that there no remedy? Though the caſe be deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 'tis not deſperate. Were my Text but minded, in it might be found a ſure <hi>Recipe.</hi> Chriſt is the Churches <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Healer;</hi> and were but <hi>Love revived,</hi> it would quickly bring <hi>his Body to a better and more healthy temper.</hi> Light may do much, but Love will do more. <hi>Love covers a multitude of ſins;</hi> Love cures a multitude of Maladies: The Church encreaſes and edifies it ſelf in Love.</p>
            <p>Though the Apoſtle was a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> yet we find his Heart <hi>enlarged</hi> towards the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> Having before diſcourſed concerning the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of <hi>Faith,</hi> in this Chapter he preſſes <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Love</hi> with the greateſt vehemency; and in order hereunto he exhorts to <hi>all lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and meekneſs:</hi> He knew that pride is the cauſe of contention, and that humility and love are the way both to the Souls, and to the Churches Reſt. He uſes great ſtrength and cogency of Argument, that he may prevail. The Saints are <hi>Members of one Body:</hi> They
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56801:5"/> have been regenerated, and are acted by <hi>one Spirit;</hi> who hath effectually called them to a <hi>lively hope of one and the ſame incorruptible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance:</hi> And in that Inheritance, there is not, there cannot be the leaſt diſcord. They ſerve <hi>one Lord,</hi> who is beſt ſerved, when his Servants beſt agree together. They are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in <hi>one Goſpel,</hi> juſtified by <hi>one Faith,</hi> baptized in <hi>one Name.</hi> Finally, that <hi>God is one,</hi> who is a moſt compaſſionate and indulgent Father to them all: And from ſo many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, how ſtrongly and undeniably may we conclude, that all Saints ſhould be of one Heart, and of one Soul!</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in thus preaching Love and Peace, ſhewed he had a very great regard to the <hi>glory of Chriſt</hi> the Head, <hi>who is aſcended far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Heavens, that he might fill all things;</hi> and that he had a great concernedneſs for <hi>his Body,</hi> the Churches edification: For accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Text, it <hi>increaſes and edifies it ſelf in Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Words there are four Propoſitions worthy of our obſervation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Church of Chriſt is compared to a Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>This Body of Chriſt is imperfect in this world, and therefore continually ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56801:6"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The Body of Chriſt ſhould diligently endeavour the edifying of it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The more Love abounds among the Members of the Church, the more the whole Body will be edified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſit.</hi> 1. I begin with the firſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>The Church of Chriſt is compared to a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> The Scripture often uſes this Metaphor of a Body; now a Metaphor is a ſimilitude in a word; and indeed there is a great reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance between an Humane Body, and the Church of Chriſt, as by and by will be made evident. Believers are ſometimes called the <hi>Brethren</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 17. which intimates a very near relation: Sometimes they are call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>his Spouſe,</hi> whom he <hi>has betrothed to himſelf for ever,</hi> Hoſ. 2. 19, 20. and that's a relation much nearer; and ſignifies a more intimate and dear affection and familiarity: Sometimes they are called <hi>Branches,</hi> Joh. 15. 1, 2, 3, 4. and this expreſſes a nearer Union ſtill; and that both the life and fruitfulneſs of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans depends upon their being and abiding in Chriſt the true Vine. But becauſe Branches, though they grow, are without ſenſe and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo that neither themſelves, nor the Vine feel any pain when they are cut or broken: therefore Believers are ſtiled <hi>Members,</hi> the Church a <hi>Body,</hi> and Chriſt is the <hi>Head;</hi> who is very much concerned both in it and for it.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56801:6"/> 
               <hi>Eph. 5. 2, 3. Chriſt is the Head of the Church, and he is the Saviour of the Body. So</hi> Eph. 3. 6. <hi>That the Gentiles ſhould be fellow-heirs, and of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel.</hi> Again, <hi>Col. 1. 18. And he is the head of the body, the Church, who is the beginning and firſt-born from the dead; that in all things he might have the preeminence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchius</hi> upon this Text takes notice of two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That by the Body we are <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Phorius in ſcholiis.</note> to underſtand <hi>Verum Christi Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Mysticum,</hi> the true Church, the <hi>true mystical body</hi> of Chriſt. This Church is made up of them that are really ſanctified; of this Hypocrites are not members; for tho' ſuch are viſibly Saints, yet in truth they are under the dominion of ſin, and ſhall receive for their hypocriſie greater damnation. Tho' hypocrites profeſs themſelves Chriſts members, yet really they are not united to him; Chriſt lives not, rules not, acts not in them, as he does in ſincere Chriſtians: Let them ſeem to be his followers, let them pretend never ſo highly to be his friends, yet really they are ſtrangers, whom Chriſt will profeſs at the great day, he never knew. <hi>Luk. 13. 26, 27. Then ſhall ye begin to ſay, We have eaten and drunk in thy preſence, and thou hast taught in our ſtreets. But he ſhall ſay, I tell you, I know you not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hence you are, depart from me all ye workers of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56801:7"/>2. By the Church we are to underſtand the Church Militant, that part of the <hi>body of Christ which is militant on earth,</hi> not which is triumphant in Heaven. The Church above needs not exhortations to grow and increaſe in Knowledge and Grace; it needs not the means of edification: Sermons of love are not to be preached there. Glorified Saints have not the leaſt ſinful defect; they ſee God face to face, and Chriſt as he is; and their love to their Father and Redeemer is anſwerable to the ſight they have, and as much as they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of. And being refined from all remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of ſin, they are become ſuch lovely Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that they cannot but love one another with a moſt pure and perfect love. 'Tis the Church of Chriſt on earth the Apoſtle ſpeaks of; this is the Body that is to be edified; and alas, in how many reſpects, how certainly in all reſpects does it ſtand in need of edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>In the handling of this Propoſition, I ſhall firſt of all ſhew the <hi>great reſemblance that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> between the Church of Christ and a Body.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>What kind of body the Church of Christ is.</hi> Laſtly, Make Application.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I am to ſhew the great reſemblance between the Church of Chriſt and a Body.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:56801:7"/>1. The life of the Body depends upon its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Head. <hi>Christ is the Churches life,</hi> and the <note place="margin">Nos Chriſto adglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinamur, non ſicut populus Principi; ſed ſicut membra buma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni corporis ſuo Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti.</note> Church could no more live without Chriſt, than a body could remain alive after the head were ſevered from it. Our Lord calls himſelf the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life</hi> alſo, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 6. By his blood he frees his Church from the ſentence of death and condemnation which ſin had brought her under; and makes her ſpiritually alive by his quickning Spirit. So that the Church breaths after God, walks with him, labours in his work and ſervice, all which are evidences of life ſpiritual. We read 1 Joh. 5. 12. <hi>He that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life.</hi> They that by faith receive the Lord Jeſus, are purified, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, and ſhall live for ever, but as many as through unbelief reject him, remain dead in ſin and doom'd to Hell. Union with Chriſt is a moſt neceſſary, a moſt happy union. The Churches life from this has its beginning, and continuance, unto conſummation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Head has a mighty influence upon the Body. There is <hi>a powerful influence from Chriſt upon his Church;</hi> and what good it does, is done by vertue of this influence. He is ſaid to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted far above all Heavens, that he might fill all things, Eph.</hi> 4. 10. Whatever grace and ſtrength, and comfort is communicated to believers, it is really
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56801:8"/> and all from Chriſt. He fills Ordinances with efficacy, mercies with ſweetneſs, afflictions with light and uſefulneſs, and Souls with greater degrees of Grace and Holineſs; out of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all-fulneſs it has pleaſed the Father ſhould dwell in him,</hi> Col. 1. 19. Our Lord tells his Diſciples they muſt abide in him, for ſeparated from him <hi>they can do nothing,</hi> Joh. 15. 5. No wonder the Apoſtle profeſſes, That <hi>Chriſt is all and in all,</hi> Col. 3. 11. Though the Body, the Church, ſhould be never ſo much increaſed, a deficiency in the Head Chriſt need not be feared; neither is it indeed poſſible: for in him there is <hi>all the fulneſs of the Godhead.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently his <hi>Rightouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> muſt needs be <hi>ſufficient</hi> for the <hi>whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Body has many Members, and theſe members have different Offices. The Church likewiſe <hi>has various members,</hi> and their different ſtations, relations, callings, diverſify their work and duties; and yet the doing of theſe duties is both comely and advantageous; and the more every one does his own work, the more all are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefited. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 45. the Apoſtle tells us, That <hi>as we have many members in one body, and all members have not the ſame office, ſo we being many are one body in Chriſt:</hi> And from thence infers, that All ſhould uſe the gifts they have received, which are differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the grace and good pleaſure of God the Giver. It would be unreaſonable for the Ear to attempt to ſpeak like the Tongue, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56801:8"/> the Hand to ſee like the Eye: The ſeveral mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have their uſes and work proper to them. <hi>All are not Apoſtles, all are not Prophets, all are not Teachers, all are not Governours,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 29. There are <hi>many</hi> indeed, <hi>moſt</hi> in the Church, that <hi>have need to be taught and governed;</hi> and thoſe that think themſelves wiſe enough to inſtruct and govern themſelves, and ſo deſpiſe their ſpiritual Guides, uſually are the moſt ignorant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, and hugely need the help and conduct of others. The members muſt abide in their place and calling, Maſters, Servants, Parents, Children, Husbands, Wives, Magiſtrates, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Paſtors, People, doing their duties which the Scripture in their ſeveral ſtations and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations calls for.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Body is fitly joyned; and <hi>thus fitly joyned is the Church of Chriſt.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies that there is a <hi>congruous order</hi> among the members of Chriſt. Without Order an Army would be a Rout and not an Army; a Kingdom would become a confuſed ſelf-deſtroying mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. The Churches God is the <hi>God of Order and not of confuſion.</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 33. There is a rule for Order and Government, and a ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the Church; 'tis not a body of <hi>levellers;</hi> if there were a perfect parity, all would affect to <hi>rule,</hi> none would care to be <hi>ruled.</hi> The <hi>reproof</hi> of <hi>two or three,</hi> is more than the reproof of <hi>one;</hi> the <hi>Churches admonition and cenſure</hi> is ſtill with greater authority. The flock is to <hi>ſubmit themſelves</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56801:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o their Paſtors <hi>who are over them in the Lord. Heb.</hi> 13. 17. and both Paſtors and people are to ſubmit eſpecially unto Chriſtian Magiſtrates, who are prophetically promiſed in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that they ſhould be <hi>Nurſing Fathers</hi> to the Church under <hi>the New.</hi> A right Order in Churches and Families, will have a mighty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to make believers ſtedfaſt againſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations both to Error and Wickedneſs. The Apoſtle rejoyced in the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> chap. 2. 5. when he <hi>beheld their order, and the ſtedfaſtneſs of of their faith in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Body is compact together, <hi>ſo is the Church of Chriſt;</hi> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhews that the Church is firmly knit unto Chriſt the Head, and the members one unto another. The <hi>hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between the Natures of Chriſt ſhall never be diſſolved, neither ſhall the <hi>myſtical union</hi> between him and his members; and if ſo, then his true members muſt needs remain cloſely knit together. There are ligaments, joynts, bands, whereby the Body of Chriſt is held together: The Spirit of Grace, and Love unites the body to Chriſt, and members to members. The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt are ſubſervient unto this union; and ought to be preaching and commending love, which is a grace of an uniting nature. The Apoſtle had a concernedneſs for the <hi>Coloſſians, which he</hi> expreſſes by a <hi>great conflict,</hi> and that which he wiſht ſo vehemently for, was this, that their <hi>hearts might be comforted, beingknit together in love,</hi> Col. 2. 1, 2.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56801:9"/>
            <p>Where is the member of the natural Body that grows weary of its fellowſhip, and is willing to be cut off. The Arms, the Hands, the Leggs, the Feet, are deſirous to keep their places; and and nature makes them abhor to be ſevered. True grace makes the members of the Church to diſlike ſeparation. As they believe ſo, they very well like, and are deſirous of the <hi>communion of Saints.</hi> A very black mark is ſet upon them who are of a contrary inclination. 1 <hi>Joh. 2. 19. They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with us; but they went out that they might be made manifeſt they were not all of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. God hath ſet the Members in the body as it pleaſed him; the <hi>different gifts and graces which are in the Church of Chriſt and the members of it, are according to Gods will and pleaſure.</hi> He beſtowes larger gifts upon ſome, and leſs upon others; and yet thoſe that have leſs, are not unuſeful. Some Saints receive greater meaſures of Grace, others ſmaller; but all have that grace which is true, and which at laſt will end in glory. Some members of the Church are higher, others lower, and yet they ſhould not envy or deſpiſe one another; for God has aſſigned their place unto both: the higher, may direct the lower, the lower may ſerve the higher. <hi>The eye cannot ſay to the hand, I have no need of thee; nor the head to the feet, I Have no need of you; and thoſe members of the body which ſeem to be more feeble are neceſſary.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56801:10"/> 1 Cor. 12. 21, 22. By the <hi>grace</hi> of God the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt <hi>are what they are.</hi> They have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what they have received; and the more any have received, the more humble and diligent they ſhould be; for where much is given, much will alſo be required.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In the Body Nouriſhment is conveyed unto the parts, and the whole is hereby ſuſtained. The <hi>body of Chriſt alſo by joints and bands having nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together, increaſeth with the increaſe of God.</hi> Col. 2. 19. The Church of Chriſt has food to eat which the world knows not of, it has ſpiritual ſenſes, a ſpiritual appetite, and its food is ſpiritual. The word of God is compared to food; here is milk for Babes, and ſtronger meat for more grown Saints. No food ſo profitable and nouriſhing, no food ſo pleaſant, no food ſo neceſſary. Heark to the profeſſion of <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 23. 12. <hi>Neither have I gone back from the commandment of his lips; I have eſteemed the words of his mouth more than my neceſſary food. David</hi> cries out, <hi>How ſweet are thy words unto my taſte! yea ſweeter than hony to my mouth.</hi> Pſal. 119. 103. And the Prophet ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe; Jer. 15. 16. <hi>Thy words were found, and I did eat them, and thy word was unto me the joy and rejoycing of my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body of Chriſt is nouriſhed by his Word, and other Ordinances are appointed for the increaſe of this body. <hi>A famine of this word</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be dreaded as a very ſore judgment.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56801:10"/>
            <p>The better the food, if it be well digeſted, the better the chyle, and the purer the blood; and the body will be more proſperous and healthy; the more purely and ſincerely the word of God is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed, the members of Chriſt will become ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the inward man be the more renewed day by day. As Chriſt gives his word, ſo he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes <hi>himſelf</hi> to be <hi>food</hi> to his members. <hi>His fleſh is meat indeed, his blood is drink indeed,</hi> Joh. 6. 55. And by this they are nouriſhed unto that life which is eternal. It might alſo be added, that Chriſt is the cloathing, as well as the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Body; his Righteouſneſs is the Robe which covers their guilt and nakedneſs, his Grace beautifies and adorns his Saints; therefore they are bid <hi>to put on the Lord Jeſus Christ, and to make no proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the lusts thereof.</hi> Rom. 13. 14.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In the Body, the Members and parts are operative and active for the good of the whole; in the Church <hi>there is an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, effectual working in the meaſure</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Phot.</note> 
               <hi>of every part,</hi> that the whole may be increaſed. The new Nature which is in ſincere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, inclines them unto <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ſuitable to that nature; ſloth is exceedingly oppoſite unto Religion. God is a rewarder of them that <hi>diligently ſeek him:</hi> to ſeek him negligently is indeed to <hi>neglect him.</hi> The mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56801:11"/> of Chriſt are induſtriouſly to do their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards their <hi>Father,</hi> and their <hi>Head,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>towards one another;</hi> hence it is that we read of the <hi>labour of love,</hi> which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle requires and encourages, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 10, 11, 12. <hi>God is not unrighteous, to forget your work and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of love which you have ſhewed towards his Name, in that you have miniſtred to the Saints and do miniſter; and we deſire that every one of you do ſhew the ſame diligence to the full aſſurance of hope unto the end; that ye be not ſlothful, but follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of them who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes.</hi> The members of Chriſts Church are to be active, but in their place, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; for if they act irregularly, that action will be <hi>againſt</hi> the Body, and to its prejudice, not to its edification. Every part has its place, and that place it muſt keep, and not aſpire higher without a call; and that meaſure of grace which it has received, it muſt faithfully exerciſe, with a regard to the Churches good as well as its own.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The whole Body and all its members are animated by one Soul; and <hi>the Church with all its true members are animated by one and the ſame Spirit.</hi> We read <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>There is one body and one Spirit:</hi> and again 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 17. <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit.</hi> The ſame Spirit which is in the Head, is in all the members which are joyned to him: And the Apoſtle ſticks not to ſay, <hi>If any man have not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56801:11"/> of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8. 9. All that <hi>light</hi> which the members of Chriſt have, is from the Spirit; he has cauſed a <hi>marvellous light</hi> to ſhine into their hearts, which before were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>power of darkneſs:</hi> he likewiſe is the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of that <hi>liberty</hi> and ability which they have unto what is good: whereas before they had a freedom, but it was <hi>only to evil continually.</hi> Theſe members of Chriſt are all <hi>changed into his image,</hi> which is their glory: but the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that change, and the progreſs of it unto greater glory, is from and by the Spirit. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 17, 18. <hi>Where the Spirit of the Lord is there is liberty, but we all with open face beholding as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image from Glory to Glory even as by the Spirits of the Lord.</hi> The Spirit dwells in all true believers, and Chriſt has promiſed that he <hi>ſhall abide in them for over,</hi> Joh. 14. 16, 17. Soul and Body indeed may be ſeparated, but the Spirit and the Saint ſhall not.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>bodies</hi> of believers are affirmed to be the <hi>Temples of the Spirit,</hi> where he dwells and abides, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 19. <hi>What know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghoſt, which is in you, which you have of God, and ye are not your own?</hi> And if the body be his Temple, ſurely the Heart and Soul ſhould be as it were the <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſanctorum,</hi> the holyeſt of all; fill'd with light and grace, that it may be alſo fill'd with peace and joy.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56801:12"/>10. The Body is under the Souls conduct and command; <hi>the Church is conducted and ruled by the Spirit of Chriſt.</hi> The eyes do ſee, the ears hear, the hands work, the feet move, according to the Souls will and pleaſure: and as it has <hi>deſpoticum imperium,</hi> the command and government of the members, ſo it acts them, and their operations are from the Souls preſence; for if the Soul were gone, the body would immediately become a clod of Earth, and the members be deprived of all ſtrength and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Spirit of Chriſt commands and acts his Members; he makes them to <hi>ſee</hi> the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, and that world which is inviſible; he makes them <hi>hear</hi> the voice of Chriſt, ſo as to obey his call; he makes the <hi>hands</hi> holy, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt purified the heart, and employes them in working Righteouſneſs: He turns the <hi>feet</hi> into the way of Gods teſtimonies; and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens believers ſo as that they <hi>run,</hi> and are not weary, they <hi>walk</hi> without fainting.</p>
            <p>A Chriſtians converſation is ſtyled a <hi>walking in the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5. 16. <hi>This I ſay then, walk in the Spirit;</hi> in his Light, in his Strength, and according to his will, <hi>and fulfill ye not the luſts of the fleſh.</hi> Without this walking, 'tis a vain thing to pretend to be in Chriſt, or to hope for Juſtification by his Righteouſneſs; for the Son of God was made a Sacrifice for ſin, <hi>that the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the law might be fulfilled in them, who walk not after the fleſh but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8. 4.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56801:12"/> What kind of Saints would there be! What exemplary Members! What illuſtrious Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies! if every one had in a greater meaſure crucified the fleſh with its luſts and affections, and had a more attentive and obedient <hi>ear to hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi> You ſee the Reſemblance between the Church of Chriſt and a Body.</p>
            <p>In the Second place I am to tell you, what <hi>kind of body</hi> the Church of Chriſt is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church is a <hi>Body of Men.</hi> Ezek. 34. 31. <hi>And ye my flock, the flock of my paſture, are men, and I am your God, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> I grant the Elect Angels have Chriſt to be their Head; but all the Apoſtate Ones were left in that miſery into which by ſin they brought themſelves. And though the Son of God be the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Keeper</hi> of the Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, yet he is not <hi>their Redeemer,</hi> as he is of his Church, for whom he died. When this Saviour was born, the Tongues of Angels pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>peace on earth, good will towards men;</hi> Luk. 2. 14. Though the World lye in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet the Church is gathered out of the World. The Saints themſelves were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>dead in ſins and treſpaſſes; and walked ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of this world, according to the Prince of the power of the air; fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind; and were by nature the Children of wrath, even as others.</hi> Eph. 1. 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56801:13"/>
            <p>All the ſtones of Gods ſpiritual Temple are dug out of the common Quarry of Mankind; and to keep them humble; they ſhould often look <hi>to the rock from whence they were hewen.</hi> All the Sons and Daughters of the Lord Almighty, are of <hi>Adams</hi> lapſed race without exception. The Grace of God is admirable, in making a Church of ſuch as theſe: The <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> was formed out of the <hi>duſt,</hi> but the <hi>Myſtical body</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Adam</hi> was form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of that which is a great deal worſe, a meer <hi>maſſe of corruption.</hi> And as there is not a Saint, but was once a Sinner; ſo thoſe Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners who are choſen, and called, and made faithful, they are not of the <hi>wiſe</hi> commonly, or of the <hi>mighty,</hi> or <hi>noble</hi> of the World: <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world, to confound the wiſe; and God hath choſen the weak things of the World, to confound the things that are mighty; and baſe things of the world, and things deſpiſed, yea, and things that are nor, to bring to nought things that are; that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence; but according as it is written, He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 27. 31.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Church is a Body <hi>governed by the beſt Laws:</hi> The Lord himſelf is their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver; and he is holy, and juſt, and good; and his Commands are like himſelf, <hi>holy, juſt, and good alſo,</hi> Rom. 7. 12.</p>
            <p>There is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Law of ſin,</hi> which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56801:13"/> the men of the world obey. This Law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands what the Law of God forbids, forbids what the Law of God commands: Darkneſs and light are not more contrary, than theſe two Laws are. But this Law of Sin is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Law of Death: Obedience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to him that yields it. The Law of the Lord is quite of another nature; there is life and peace in the doing of it; <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 2. <hi>Keep my Commandments, and live, and my Law as the apple of thine eye.</hi> Pſal. 119. 165. <hi>Great peace have they that love thy Law, and nothing ſhall offend them.</hi> The more the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms to the Laws of her Lord and Head, ſhe recovers the more of the Image of God which was loſt by the Fall, and partakes the more of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> eſcaping that corruption that luſt cauſes in the World. This Law is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Heart, which is changed and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the Heart being ſuited to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, delights in obedience: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 8. <hi>I delight to do thy will, O my God, yea, thy law is within my heart.</hi> This Law is of the higheſt authority, therefore the Saints ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to keep it without ſpot; and whatever penalties they ſuffer, they will never have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to repent of their faithfulneſs to their Lord, or their obedience to his Precepts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church is the <hi>wiſeſt Body and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the World.</hi> Indeed all the World beſides are a company of meer Fools and mad-men:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56801:14"/> Are not they fools that hate knowledge? are not they fools that joyn with Satan to undo themſelves? are not they fools who venture for a meer trifle, a little ſinful gain or pleaſure, to loſe their precious Souls, which are of more value than the whole World put together? are not they fools, who have Salvation, Life, and Immortality offered to them, and neglect the offer? who are warned to flee from fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Wrath, and the vengeance of eternal Fire; and yet will needs run thither, and are angry with any that endeavour to ſtop them? Oh how has ſin bereaved men of their Wits and Underſtandings!</p>
            <p>But the Church of Chriſt is ſayingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, all her true members made wiſe unto Salvation: They are ſo wiſe as to make their peace with God, believing in Jeſus, and relying on his blood for Reconciliation; they are ſo wiſe as to follow the Lamb, and that path muſt needs be beſt and ſafeſt, wherein he leads them: They are ſo wiſe as to make timely proviſion for eternity; and to commit the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Souls into a ſtrong hand, which never loſt any that it undertook to keep and to ſecure. Therefore the Apoſtle ſpeaks with ſo much confidence, 2 <hi>Tim. 12. I know whom I have believed, and I am perſwaded he is able to keep that which I have committed to him againſt that day.</hi> What is the wiſdom of this World com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Churches wiſdom, which is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56801:14"/> ſpiritual? the Apoſtle undervalues the policy of Princes, in compariſon of the Goſpel; that <hi>policy</hi> comes to <hi>nothing,</hi> this Goſpel guides to <hi>glory;</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 6, 7. <hi>Howbeit we ſpeak wiſdom among them that are perfect; yet not the wiſdom of this world, nor of the Princes of this world,</hi> (who yet get moſt by their wiſdom) <hi>that come to nothing: but we ſpeak the wiſdom of God in a myſtery, even the hidden wiſdom which God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained before the world unto our glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Church is <hi>a Body of great beauty and excellency,</hi> called therefore in the <hi>Song of Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the <hi>faireſt among women,</hi> Cant. 5. 1. <hi>Sion</hi> is affirmed to be <hi>the perfection of beauty,</hi> Pſal. 50. 2. The Church is excellent in regard of her Original, for ſhe is of Heavenly extraction, and born of God himſelf: All her true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are new Creatures; they are beautified with the image of God, and reſemble him in Knowledge, Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs. As Sin is the greateſt deformity, ſo Holineſs is the trueſt beauty; 'tis this which makes the Angels ſhine; nay, 'tis the glory of God himſelf. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 11. <hi>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gods! who is like thee, glorious in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs!</hi> How certain is it, that the <hi>Righteous man is more excellent than his Neighbour:</hi> Now the Church is called <hi>the Generation of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church is likened to a Woman, becauſe the Woman excells the man in beauty; but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56801:15"/> ſhe is ſuch a Woman, as the like is not to be found: <hi>Rev. 12. 1. She is cloathed with the Sun, the Moon is under her feet, and upon her head a Crown,</hi> not of Gold, and Diamonds, but bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; <hi>a Crown of twelve Stars.</hi> What can equal this Glory of the Church? <hi>All fleſh is graſs, and all the glory of man as the flower of the field,</hi> which ſoon withers, and fades away. She is ſaid to be cloathed with the Sun, becauſe juſtified by Chriſt, the Sun of Righteouſneſs; the Moon is ſaid to be under her feet, becauſe all changeable things are below her ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and raiſed Affections; the twelve Stars, which are her Crown, ſignifie the Doctrine of the twelve Apoſtles of the Lamb, whereby ſhe is inlightned, and brought at length to that light which is everlaſting.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Church is a <hi>Body of great ſtrength;</hi> for this Body is <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might.</hi> Sinners are without ſtrength; they cannot pleaſe God, they cannot profit themſelves; but the Churches members are <hi>ſtrengthened with might by the Spirit in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man;</hi> ſo that they can do things beyond the power of Nature; they can ſee the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, they can believe againſt hope, they can overcome and deny themſelves, they can wreſtle with the Almighty, and as Princes prevail with him; they can foil the Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers of darkneſs, they can fight the good fight of Faith, and lay hold of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56801:15"/> life; and all theſe are mighty acts indeed, too great to be performed by any that are Hypocrites and ungodly. The Church is moſt oppoſed, and yet is moſt victorious; and will ſtill abide in the world, notwithſtanding all the worlds rage; like the <hi>Immortal Regiment</hi> among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> that never was deſtroyed till the Empire was deſtroyed; for if any Souldier was killed, another preſently was liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his room. This buſh of the Church is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſumed in a flame; nay, it has been moſt green and flouriſhing when the flame has been fierceſt. God has ſtrengthened and preſerved her, and her preſervation may be look'd upon as one of the greateſt Arguments and Miracles of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Church is a <hi>Body to whom the whole world is beholding:</hi> It ſhould be the <hi>joy,</hi> for it is the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of the whole earth. How ſoon would the <hi>Tares</hi> be pluck'd up, bound in bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and caſt into the fire, if it were not for the <hi>Wheat</hi> which grows among them? <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 29. The Church is a Friend, and wiſhes well to Mankind; 'tis her Prayer, that Gods <hi>way may be known on earth, and his ſaving health among all Nations;</hi> that <hi>the Kingdoms of the World may become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt:</hi> And like a Mother, ſhe is in travel for the converſion and ſalvation of a greater multitude of Souls. Why ſhould the World be angry, and recompenſe evil for good?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56801:16"/> they ſhould all be wiſe at length, and deſire to be incorporated into the Church, and be reſolved to <hi>go with her;</hi> for they may be well aſſured that <hi>God is with her.</hi> Zech. 8. 23.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Church is a <hi>Body that will at length by many degrees be made more glorious than 'tis at preſent.</hi> Now 'tis truly ſanctified, 'tis high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignified; but it does <hi>not yet appear what it ſhall be;</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 2. But when Chriſt the Head ſhall appear the ſecond time, without ſin, to ſalvation, what a glorious Church will appear with him! <hi>Col. 3. 4. Every member will ſhine as the Sun in the Fathers Kngdom. Mat.</hi> 13. 43. And what a glorious ſpectacle will that be, to behold all the Saints together in a company, and every one of them ſhining forth as the Sun; and the Son of God at the head of them all! How with our cries and groans, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diligence in preparing for it, ſhould we continually be haſtning the coming of that day of God! Chriſts Body, the Church, has its defects and blemiſhes, while it ſojourns here below; but at the laſt day all the ſpots will be off, all the wrinkles ſmoothed, and the end of Chriſts death will be fully attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>He gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for his Church, that he might ſanctify and cleanſe it, and preſent it to himſelf a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh:</hi> Eph. 5. 26, 27. How gorgeouſly apparrel'd, how
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56801:16"/> richly adorned, how amiable and lovely will the <hi>Lamb's Bride</hi> at laſt be, when Satan ſhall be quite vanquiſht, Death ſwallowed up in Victory, and ſin ſhall ceaſe to have a being! when light ſhall be without any darkneſs, joy without ſorrow, purity without the leaſt mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of defilement! When Chriſt does put the Crown of Life upon his Churches Head, then that Scripture will be fully verified, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>Thou art all fair, my Love, there is no ſpot in thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the Application.</p>
            <p>USE. I. Let the Church and all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, <hi>conſider their relation unto Chriſt their Head,</hi> and <hi>doe that duty</hi> which ſuch a relation calls for: They are <hi>Chriſt's,</hi> and not <hi>Mammons;</hi> they are Chriſts, and not <hi>their own;</hi> they are his purchaſe, his Spouſe; nay parts, and pieces, and Members of him, which he has bought, and united to himſelf: 'Tis highly againſt all reaſon, that they ſhould ſeek, or pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a ſinful and ſelf-deſtroying man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Their Duty towards Chriſt, their Lord and Head, is in ſeveral Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Members of Chriſt ſhould <hi>love him in great ſinoerity.</hi> The Apoſtle wiſhes, <hi>that the grace of God may be</hi> with all ſuch ſincere Lovers, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 24. Diſſembled and ſeeming Love is really none at all; and in ſeveral reſpects worſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56801:17"/> than none. Chriſts Love to his Church was moſt real: How exceeding low was his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, that ſhe might be advanced! how great his Sufferings for her eternal Redemption! The Apoſtle ſpeaks as one amazed at the <hi>height, and length, and depth, and breadth of this love of Chriſt which paſſes knowledge,</hi> Eph. 3. 18, 19. And if the Head be ſo full of love to all the Members, certainly the Members will be in the worſt ſence unnatural, if they return not love to their Head and Saviour; they ſhould prize him moſt highly, <hi>counting all things but loſs and dung that they may win him,</hi> Phil. 3. 8. They ſhould mourn when he withdraws, but rejoyce exceedingly when they enjoy his preſence, and ſee his face who is <hi>altogether lovely.</hi> They ſhould value his Word and Ordinances, in which he is to be found, and delight themſelves in the contemplation of his fulneſs, and that great and everlaſting Salvation whereof he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. Their very <hi>Souls ſhould love him,</hi> Cant. 3. 4. which expreſſion intimates both the truth, and the ſtrength and fervency of affection: and truly our Lord is ſo excellent, that there is no danger or poſſibility that Love to him ſhould be exceſſive.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Members of Chriſt ſhould endeavour <hi>to promote his Honour and Glory:</hi> They ſhould be very zealous that their Head may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, and have the preeminence over all things. Their tongues ſhould be ſhewing forth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56801:17"/> his praiſes, commending him to the World as the beſt of Princes, as the only Saviour; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the unreaſonableneſs of the Worlds preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt his <hi>yoak and burthen,</hi> which are ſo <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and ſo light.</hi> Mat. 11. <hi>ult.</hi> They ſhould earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire that Chriſt their Lord, may be the Worlds Univerſal Monarch; and that all Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings and Emperors may caſt down their Crowns before him, and willingly ſubmit to his Scepter and Government.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Members of Chriſt <hi>ſhould obey all his Commands.</hi> Joh. 14. 15. <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments.</hi> And <hi>v. 21. He that hath my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me.</hi> It is a monſtrouſneſs in Nature, if any of the Members ſhould not be placed under the Head: Surely then all the Members of Chriſt ſhould readily be ſubject to him. Thus to be Subject is to Reign. Obedience is the great Sacrifice to be offered under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the Saints are ſtyled <hi>Prieſts; Kings</hi> as well as Prieſts; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Royal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9. So that to obey the Lord Jeſus contains in it no leſs than a Regal Honour. He ſhould be reverenced, all his Commands performed. He that hears Chriſts ſayings, and <hi>doth them,</hi> is the <hi>wiſe Builder,</hi> whoſe Houſe ſhall never fall; is indeed the bleſſed man, and is in the right way to Life and Immortality. <hi>Rev. 22. 14. Bleſſed are they that do his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, that they may have right to the Tree
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56801:18"/> of Life, and may enter in through the gates into the City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Members of Chriſt <hi>ſhould live by faith upon him:</hi> They are to expect the Remiſſion of ſin, and deliverance from wrath to come no other way: when they have done their beſt and moſt, they muſt look unto Jeſus, that they through him may be accepted: For there is no way to be <hi>accepted, but in the Beloved.</hi> Eph. 1. 6. In all their Temptations, Sorrows, Sufferings, they are to depend upon him for ſuccour, joy, and Grace ſufficient. The Body is ſecured, and in the Spiritual Warfare, has both conduct and conqueſt by acting Faith in Chriſt the Head. Every Member therefore ſhould imitate the Apoſtle, who ſaid, <hi>Gal. 2. 20. The life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Members of Chriſt <hi>ſhould do nothing unbecoming his Members.</hi> The Glory and Name of Chriſt, and the Credit of the Goſpel ſhould be very dear to them; and they ought to be <hi>blameleſs and harmleſs, without rebuke, in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Generation; and ſhine as lights in the World.</hi> Phil. 2. 15. They ſhould manifeſt that they <hi>abide</hi> in Chriſt, <hi>by walking as he walked;</hi> they ſhould he patient, meek, and lowly as Chriſt was, contemn the world as he contemn'd it, count it their meat and drink to do the will of God as he did: and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56801:18"/> ſince Chriſt endured the contradiction of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againſt himſelf, ſo ſhould they. Though the Foes of Chriſt are numerous, and oppoſe his intereſt with never ſo great force and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet his members muſt never be aſhamed to own their Head, nor afraid to follow him. It becomes them, and it concerns them to cleave to him <hi>with full purpoſe of heart,</hi> Acts 11. 23. For to leave him is to be loſt for ever, and to bid farewell to bleſſedneſs, and life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
            <p>USE. II. Let the Members of this Body the Church, <hi>conſider the relation they have one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> They are indeed very near, and ſhould look upon themſelves as very near one to another: And this Relation ſhould be of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty efficacy to perſwade them to perform thoſe mutual Duties which are incumbent upon them. In the general, All <hi>particular</hi> Members ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the good of the <hi>whole</hi> Church: They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> and their <hi>Love</hi> ſhould <hi>run parallel</hi> with their <hi>Faith;</hi> and care will be an effect of true Love. A private Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is very prejudicial to the Body of Chriſt, whilſt only one part is minded, and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: 'Tis juſt as if there ſhould be an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make one member of the Body natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral great and ſtrong, with an unconcernedneſs how weak, and feeble, and ſmall ſoever the other Members remain. 'Tis lamentable that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56801:19"/> there are ſo many Parties in the Chriſtian Church; but 'tis more to be lamented, that theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are ſo ſelfiſh, and ſo little mind the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt; which being neglected, their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt cannot be regarded ſo truly as it ſhould be. For if a whole Town be burnt down to the ground, no particular houſe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capes the fury of the flames: No mans Cabin can be ſecured, if the Ship be caſt away, and ſinks to the bottom of the Sea.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral Counſels which I would intreat the Members of the Church to follow, that it may be the better with the Church, and with themſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let not the <hi>higher Members deſpiſe the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> You that are higher, <hi>what have you that you have not received? why then ſhould you glory, as if you had not received it?</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 7. That's a Scripture whoſe ſharp point ſhould prick the bladder, and let out pride and ſelf-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Phil. 2. 3. Let nothing be done through ſtrife or vain glory; but in lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves. Moſes</hi> the holieſt and moſt uſeful man in his time, was the <hi>meekeſt man</hi> upon earth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. 3. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> though he laboured more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than all the Apoſtles to ſpread the Goſpel and Faith of Chriſt, yet in what an humble ſtyle does he write of himſelf, and ſurely his Heart and Pen went together, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 9. I am the leaſt of the Apoſtles, that am not worthy to be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56801:19"/> called an Apoſtle.</hi> Nay, he abaſes himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath all <hi>Saints,</hi> as well as all Apoſtles, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the Critick's ſcoff, in coyning the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſhew how low he was in his own thoughts: <hi>Eph. 3. 8. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto me who am leſs than the leaſt of all Saints, is this Grace given, that I ſhould preach among the Gentiles the unſearchable riches of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let not the <hi>lower Members of the Church be diſcontented.</hi> Every Member is highly favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, highly honoured; every Member is under the Head's care, and ſhall at laſt be fully hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in and with Chriſt Jeſus. To be a <hi>Door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper in the Houſe of God,</hi> was look'd upon as an honour and Priviledg by a King of <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 84. 10. The leaſt degree of true Grace is more worth than all the Gold and Silver that God has made. Saints are to be blamed when diſcontented becauſe they are not of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt rank; for all Saints are Children, all are Heirs, all are firſt-born; therefore the Church is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Church of the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,</hi> Heb. 12. 23. nay, they are all, even the meaneſt of them, advanced to Kingly Dignity. <hi>Rev. 1. 5, 6. To him that hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, and hath made us Kings and Priests unto God, and his Father; to him be glory and dominion for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let the Members of the Church <hi>be ſenſible of the need they ſtand in one of another.</hi> How much are the higher Members of the Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56801:20"/> to the Feet, which are the loweſt of all! the Body could not go without them, but only lame, and a Cripple. God has ordered it ſo in his Church, that as the Members are to have their main and principal dependance upon Chriſt their Head, ſo they are to have ſome kind of dependance upon one another: and the reaſon is, that thoſe two excellent Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> may flouriſh among them. Though the Hand by the Philoſopher be fitly ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt uſeful Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet it cannot do every thing: It cannot ſee like the Eye; nor ſpeak like the Tongue; and if a man ſhould attempt to go upon his Hands, he would walk after a ſorry and odd faſhion. The ſtrongeſt Saints, nay, the ableſt Miniſters are beholding to the meaneſt Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; the ſtronger are encouraged when the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er do their Duty. A word ſometimes from a weak Chriſtian, may be much to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian more grown. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays, <hi>he lived,</hi> if the <hi>Theſſalonians ſtood faſt in the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſ. 3. 1. And a beggar could not beg more heartily for an Alms, than he did for the Prayers of the Saints at <hi>Rome.</hi> Rom. 15. 30. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, for the Lord Jeſus Christs ſake, and the love of the Spirit, that you ſtrive together with me in your Prayers to God for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Let the Members of the Church <hi>have the ſame care one of another that they have of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:56801:20"/> 1 Cor. 12. 25. In the natural body it is thus; if the Face be ſtruck at, the Arm en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to ward off the blow; if the Body be in danger in one place, the feet are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to carry it to a place of greater ſtrength and ſafety. Chriſtians ſhould be concerned for their fellow Chriſtians as for their fellow Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: and mind that of the Apoſtle more, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 24. Let no man ſeek his own;</hi> that is, his own only, <hi>but every man anothers wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Let the members of the Church <hi>ſympathize with ſuffering members.</hi> We are commanded <hi>to weep with thoſe that weep,</hi> Rom. 12. 15. The ſorrows of afflicted Chriſtians ſhould be ours, and we ſhould feel their burthens. 'Tis the glaſs eye that ſheds no tears, 'tis the wooden Arm and Leg that feels nothing: Every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt ſhould be full of Bowels. The Injunction is plain, <hi>Remember them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them which ſuffer adverſity as being your ſelves alſo in the body.</hi> Thoſe were upbraided, and threatned ſeverely for their carnal ſecurity and hardneſs of heart, who were <hi>at eaſe</hi> when <hi>Zion</hi> was in trouble, and were not at all <hi>grieved for the Afflictions of</hi> Joſeph, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 6.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let the members of the Church <hi>be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned about ſuch fellow members that are ſinfully diſtempered.</hi> If any part of the body natural aile any thing, all the other parts are ready to afford the utmoſt relief and aſſiſtance they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56801:21"/> are able. And why ſhould Chriſtians be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of Chriſtians, as if they were of <hi>Cains</hi> temper, who ſaid, <hi>Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> If a beaſt be fallen, we pity him, and are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to help unto the lifting him up again; and ſhould not a member of Chriſt who has fallen into ſin and hurt himſelf ſo much by his fall, move our compaſſions? We are indeed care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to <hi>avoid infection</hi> by thoſe that are lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: yet 'tis our duty to <hi>reſtore them in the Spirit of meekneſs, conſidering our ſelves, leſt we alſo be tempted,</hi> Gal. 6. 1.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If <hi>one member of the Church be honoured all the members ſhould rejoice with it.</hi> Is the hand envious at the eyes quickneſs? or the ear en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious at the hands activity? Envy is as unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable in the body myſtical, as in the body na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural. We ought to rejoice in the gifts of others, and in their graces, and in their uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; elſe the Spirit of God who has given theſe gifts and graces, and has made them thus uſeful, will be grieved, and we ſhall hinder our ſelves of that profit which we our ſelves might reap from them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Let there be no <hi>diſcord among the members of the Church,</hi> but they ſhould perfectly agree together. By that <hi>Apologue</hi> concerning the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of the Members falling out with the Body, <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi> did put an end to a contention that was likely to prove fatal, between the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate and the common
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56801:21"/> people. How unreaſonable would it be that the hand ſhould envy the eyes, and endeavour to put them out? that the feet ſhould take it amiſs that they are lowermoſt, and ſhould fall a kicking all the parts which are within their reach? Diſcord among Saints is ſuch a kind of unnatural and fooliſh contention. If <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithful ſaid unto <hi>Lot; Let there be no ſtrife between Me and Thee, for we be Brethren,</hi> Gen. 13. 8. ſurely Chriſtians <hi>à for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori</hi> may argue with one another, Let there be no ſtrife among us <hi>for we are Members,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Rom. 12. 5.</p>
            <p>USE III. Let the <hi>World take heed how they deal with the Church which is the Body of Chriſt.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Luthers</hi> obſervation, That if any part of the Body be hurt and pained, the ſigns of feeling appear in the <hi>Head,</hi> the Brows are contracted, the Tongue cryes, Oh! the Viſage is altered. Chriſt the Head, knowes all the ſorrows of his Church, nay in all her Afflictions he is afflicted. When <hi>Saul</hi> made havock of the Body on Earth, the Head in Heaven cryes out, as having felt his fury; <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> Act. 9. 4. Let the world be wiſe, and the higheſt and greateſt in it, for whatſoever injuries are done to Chriſtians for Chriſts ſake, he accounts them as done to himſelf: in hurting his Body they ſtrike him there where he is moſt tender, moſt ſenſible, and ſuch blows without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56801:22"/> will be dreadfully revenged. Chriſt who is the Churches Head is to be the <hi>Worlds Judge:</hi> and if when the Lord comes with ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of his Saints, hard ſpeeches ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred; Surely the Worlds hard uſage of his members ſhall not be forgotten, ſhall not paſs unpuniſhed. If at the great day, the <hi>not feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cloathing of hungry and naked Saints,</hi> will be puniſhed with <hi>everlaſting fire;</hi> oh what a ſin will it be found to take away their food and rayment from them? if Chriſt will be ſo angry with thoſe who <hi>viſited not believers in Priſon,</hi> Mat. 25. 42, 43. where ſhall they appear that were the Impriſoners of them? The World ſhould not be cruel to Chriſtians, ſince Chriſt will quickly appear to <hi>judge the World in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> So much for the firſt Propoſition, <hi>That the Church of Chriſt is compared to a Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſit.</hi> II. The ſecond Propoſition is this, <hi>That this Body of Chriſt is imperfect in this World, and therefore continually ſhould be encreaſing.</hi> Hence it is that Chriſtians are exhorted to <hi>grow in Grace, and in the Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2. Pet. 3. 18. and not only to <hi>be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and unmoveable;</hi> but <hi>always to abound in the work of the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 58.</p>
            <p>In the handling of this Propoſition, I ſhall firſt ſhew, in what reſpects <hi>the Church of Chriſt here on earth is imperfect.</hi> Secondly, In what ſenſe the <hi>Church ſhould be continually increaſing.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56801:22"/> I ſhall produce <hi>ſeveral Reaſons for this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Church.</hi> Laſtly, I ſhall give you <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes that may be made of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of theſe; and ſhall ſhew, in what reſpects <hi>the Church of Chriſt here on Earth, is imperfect.</hi> Two things are here to be conſidered. Firſt, <hi>The number of the Churches Members is not yet compleated.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Thoſe Members which actually are of the Church, are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, the very beſt of them, as long as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The number of the Churches Members is not yet compleated.</hi> There are more ſtill to be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the World, and brought home to Jeſus: All are not gathered, which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has deſigned to give him. <hi>Joh. 10. 16. And other ſheep I have, who are not of this Fold; them alſo I muſt bring, and they ſhall hear my voice, and there ſhall he one Fold, and one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Many, 'tis to be hoped, <hi>who have heard the Goſpel, ſhall be converted, though as yet they are not.</hi> Though they have hitherto reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt, yet at laſt they ſhall yield unto his Call and ſtriving. When once the day of power, and the <hi>time of love</hi> is come, they ſhall be <hi>made willing</hi> to receive a Saviour, to be the Lords, and to ſerve the Lord; though now never ſo great an obſtinacy and unwillingneſs is diſcovered. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 3.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:56801:23"/>2. Many who are <hi>in the loyns</hi> both of Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Unbelievers, ſhall in due time be born, and <hi>born again.</hi> The Church ſhall never quite diſcontinue; it may indeed ſometimes be leſs viſible, but it always has a Being. God will have a <hi>Seed to ſerve him</hi> in every future Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. 30.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Natural Branches are to be graffed in again to their own Olive-tree.</hi> Rom. 11. 24. <hi>For if thou wer't cut out of the Olive-tree which is wild by nature, and wer't graffed contrary to nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a good Olive-tree, how much more ſhall theſe, that is, the</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>which be the natural bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, be graffed into their own Olive-tree?</hi> Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in part is happened to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but they are ſtill beloved for their Fathers ſake; and at length the veil which is upon their Hearts, ſhall be taken away, and they ſhall look unto him whom their Fathers crucified, and be ſaved by him: For he is the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the <hi>deliverer that is come out of Sion, and ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from Jacob,</hi> Rom. 11. 26. Now when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be added to the Chriſtian Church, how will this Church be encreaſed! it will be a very glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous augmentation, like a Reſurrection from the dead, <hi>Rom. 11. 15. For if the casting away of them be the reconciling of the World, what ſhall the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of them be but life from the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Kingdoms of the world are to become the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt,</hi> Rev. 11. 15. I grant this is in part already; the <hi>Gentiles</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56801:23"/> have been preached to, and have obeyed the Goſpel; Chriſt, according to the Fathers Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, has <hi>had the Heathen given to him for his Inheritance,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>uttermoſt parts of the earth for his poſſeſſion;</hi> but we may rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, after the deſtruction of Antichriſt, and the utter overthrow of his power and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, that many more Kingdoms of the world will ſubmit unto the Lord Jeſus; and his Church hereby will have a vaſt increaſe. We find <hi>Rev. 18. Babylon deſtroyed,</hi> the Kings of the earth, and the Merchants that committed Fornication with her, crying, Alas! alas! and lamenting her ſudden and utter downfall; <hi>The Heavens, and the holy Apoſtles and Prophets rejoycing over her, becauſe God had avenged them upon her.</hi> And then it follows, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 12. that upon the head of Chriſt were <hi>many Crowns,</hi> which ſhews the ſubjection of many Kings to him: <hi>and v. 6. there is a voice of a great multitude, as the voice of many waters, and as the voice of mighty thundrings,</hi> as if all the World did joyn <hi>together</hi> in <hi>ſaying, Alleluia, for the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth.</hi> From all this it appears that the Church as yet is incompleat: and that greater numbers of Converts are to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and how ſhould the Promiſes of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es enlargement in the latter dayes, be thought upon with joy; and how earneſtly ſhould we pray that thoſe Promiſes may be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Members <hi>which actually are of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56801:24"/> Church, are imperfect the very best of them, as long as they remain in this World.</hi> How plainly does the Wiſe man ſpeak, <hi>Eccl. 7. 20. There is not a just man upon Earth, that doeth good and ſinneth not.</hi> There is many a juſt man upon earth; and every juſt man his practice is to do good: but there is not one that <hi>ſo</hi> does good, as not to be chargeable with the leaſt evil. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> that is ſo much for joyning good works with faith, yet acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges in many things we offend all, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 2. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> that great Saint and Preacher, ſpeaks thus of himſelf; (and ſurely he would not tell a lye through abundance of humility: <hi>Phil. 3. 12, 13. Not as though I had already attained either were already perfect, but forgetting the things which are behind and reaeching forth to thoſe things which are before. I preſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the mark for the prize of the high calling of God.</hi> The imperfection of the Saints and Members of the Church on Earth, will be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in ſeveral reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Knowledge of the Saints is imperfect.</hi> He that knew as much as any, ſayes, <hi>We know in part, and propheſy in part,</hi> and <hi>now we ſee through a glaſs darkly,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 9. 12. <hi>David,</hi> who was <hi>wiſer than his enemies,</hi> who had more underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than <hi>all his Teachers,</hi> than <hi>the Ancients;</hi> yet prays ſtill that God would <hi>teach him,</hi> that God would <hi>open his eyes,</hi> and <hi>give him underſtanding,</hi> Pſal. 119. which expreſſions ſhew a remainder
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56801:24"/> of ignorance in him, a trouble at it, and a deſire after a more perfect inſtruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Holineſs <hi>at preſent is imperfect in the beſt of men,</hi> as well as Knowledg. Other Graces can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perfect, if Knowledge be not. He that does not know the evil of ſin ſo fully as he ought, cannot hate it ſo much as he ſhould. He that is imperfect in his knowledge of God and Chriſt, muſt needs fall ſhort in his Faith and Love, and holy Fear, and Reverence. There is not one ſanctifying Grace in us, but needs further degrees. The Apoſtle makes it the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant work of Believers here below, <hi>to be clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves from all filthineſs both of the fleſh and ſpirit, and to be perfecting holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>victory over ſpiritual enemies is not yet fully obtained by militant Saints.</hi> They are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating but they have not conquered, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt Satan, and force him many times to flee; but he returns again and renews his aſſaults: and the God of peace has not yet done it, though he <hi>has promiſed to tread him under their feet ſhortly,</hi> Rom. 16. 20. They have crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts; but though the fleſh is faſtened to the Croſs of Chriſt, and therefore <hi>the old man is ſaid to be crucified with him;</hi> yet the fleſh ſtruggles upon the Croſs: the Body of Sin is not quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, ſome fleſhly and worldly luſts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are ſtirring which are not totally mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56801:25"/> Militant Saints are not as yet compleat Conquerours, for their enemies ſtill make a head, and continue the war, though at length they ſhall be made <hi>more than Conquerours through him that loved them,</hi> Rom. 8. 37.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Joyes of believers alſo are imperfect.</hi> All tears ſhall at laſt be wiped away from their Eyes, but at preſent their Eyes are full of them. The worlds wickedneſs, and folly in that wickedneſs; profeſſors degeneracy; the Churches diviſions, and diſtreſſes and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the dreadful tokens and ſigns of Gods diſpleaſure, if not of his departing; finally, their own ſpiritual diſtempers, which are ſo far from being perfectly cured; alas! theſe are enough to hinder their joy from being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Their <hi>Happineſs is as yet but an imperfect Happineſs.</hi> All the world are miſerable beſides, and the Saints are the only happy ones; and yet theſe by many degrees are not ſo happy as they ſhall be. This ſad effect ſin has by coming into the world, that not a man, not the beſt man can be fully happy, till got out of the world. The Churches true members are happy indeed, becauſe <hi>God is theirs,</hi> Pſal. 144. <hi>ult.</hi> becauſe <hi>Chriſt is theirs;</hi> but they muſt needs be happy only in part, becauſe God and Chriſt are but in part enjoyed.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place I am to ſhew, <hi>in what
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56801:25"/> ſenſe the Church ſhould be continually increaſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. The Church ſhould endeavour to <hi>increaſe in numbers,</hi> and that <hi>the ſtone cut out without hands may become a great mountain, and fill the whole earth,</hi> Dan. 2. 34, 35. 'Tis the worlds miſery that it hates and keeps at a diſtance from the Church of Chriſt. But if this world were but taken into the Church, and were brought to believe in the ſame <hi>Jehovah,</hi> in the ſame Jeſus, and to yield Subjection to the ſame Goſpel, what a New and Happy world would there be preſently! This increaſe of the Church in numbers, is to be endeavoured ſeveral wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Prayer ſhould be <hi>conſtant and very fervent for this increaſe.</hi> All the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> ſhould be importunate, that the City of God may be enlarged; that the <hi>Church</hi> may not have a <hi>barren womb,</hi> or <hi>dry breaſts;</hi> but that by reaſon of her numerous Offspring ſhe may <hi>enlarge the place of her tent,</hi> and without <hi>ſparing</hi> ſhe may <hi>lengthen her cords and ſtrengthen her ſtakes, and ſtretch forth the curtains of her habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> Iſa. 54. 2. There is mercy enough in God, though the miſerable ſinners that come to him are never ſo great a multitude. The fulneſs of Chriſt is ſo infinitely unmeaſurable, that 'tis ſufficient to ſupply and to enrich the whole empty and beggar'd race of <hi>Adam.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is of capacity to contain millions of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants more. Let us therefore pray that the converſion of Souls may be by thouſands;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56801:26"/> and that they may <hi>flie as a cloud, and as doves to their Windows,</hi> Iſa. 60. 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>promiſes of the Churches increaſe are to be believed, and pleaded.</hi> In what a ſtrain does God ſpeak unto his Church, what Promiſes does he make her! <hi>Iſa. 60. 3, 4, 5. The Gentiles ſhall come to thy light, and Kings to the brightneſs of thy riſing. Lift up thine eyes round about, and ſee; all they gather themſelves together, they come to thee. Thy Sons ſhall come from far, and thy Daughters ſhall be nurſed at thy ſide. Then ſhalt thou ſee, and flow together; and thy heart ſhall fear and be enlarged: Becauſe the abundance of the Sea ſhall be converted unto thee: And the Forces of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhall come to thee.</hi> And <hi>v. 11. Thy Gates ſhall be open continually, they ſhall not be ſhut day nor night;</hi> that ſtill there may be greater confluence. And <hi>v. 16. Thou ſhalt alſo ſuck the Milk of the Gentiles, and ſhalt ſuck the breaſts of Kings; and thou ſhalt know that I the Lord am thy Saviour, and thy Redeemer, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty One of Jacob.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like Promiſes are certain; that God who has made them, is eaſily able to make them good: His Glory and Name, and his Sons Honour, are much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in fulfilling them: And he is delighted to ſee his Saints deſirous with a reſpect to his Name, that theſe Promiſes may be performed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church is to be increaſed <hi>by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful preaching of the Goſpel.</hi> This Preaching by all means is to be encouraged; for <hi>Faith comes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56801:26"/> by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God,</hi> Rom. 10. 17. Thoſe that moſt preach Chriſt, and leaſt themſelves, are likelieſt to enlarge the Church of God. Thoſe that are moſt skilful to convince men of ſin, that are wiſe to win Souls, that know Chriſt themſelves, and how to reveal him to others, and with greateſt zeal do preſs the love and practice of Holineſs; theſe are the Paſtours after the Heart of God, and are likely to do as <hi>Jacob</hi> did to <hi>Laban,</hi> vaſtly to increaſe the Flock of Chriſt. The Apoſtle was ſo far from hindring the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, that he was glad it was preached by thoſe that did not preach ſincerely: Surely the Church may have ſome benefit and enlargement by <hi>ſuch.</hi> Phil. 1. 15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Some preach Chriſt even of envy and ſtrife, and others alſo of good will: the one preach Chriſt of contention, not ſincerely, ſuppoſing to add afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to my bonds; but the other of love; knowing that I am ſet for the defence of the Goſpel. What then I Notwithſtanding every way, whether in pretence, or in truth, Chriſt is preached; and therein I do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, yea and will rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>avoiding of Scandal is much for the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Increaſe.</hi> The Scandalous and looſe lives of Profeſſors, make the World conclude the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel but a <hi>cunningly deviſed Fable;</hi> and harden the men of it in Irreligion, and a profane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent. The evil works of ſuch as are called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56801:27"/> for many of theſe latter Ages, has been a great impediment to the ſpreading of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. Our Lord ſayes, <hi>Woe to the World becauſe of offences,</hi> Mat. 18. 7. for the World hereby is confirmed in prejudice and Wickedneſs, and at laſt more certainly ruined: But when the Members of the Church do work out their own Salvation with fear and trembling, and ſhew a vehement deſire after the Worlds Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation alſo, this is the way to gain the World to Chriſt, and to turn it unto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Church is mightily increaſed <hi>by the exemplary converſation of her Members.</hi> When Believers are zealous of good Works, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebuke and blame. When they are pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of Piety, Juſtice, Mercy, Meekneſs, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Self-denial; when they go about doing good; and by the heavenlineſs of their diſcourſe and carriage, declare plainly that they <hi>ſeek a better countrey</hi> than is to be found in this World; hereby they adorn the Goſpel, and render it more lovely in the Worlds eye, and more likely to be entertained: <hi>the ignorance</hi> of wicked and <hi>fooliſh men is ſilenced by well doing,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 15. nay, they be forced to a confeſſion, that God is in his Church of a truth; and may at length conſent and deſire to be Members of that Church, where there is ſo much of God, and of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence viſible and apparent.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56801:27"/>
            <p>2. As the Church ſhould increaſe in numbers, ſo <hi>all the Members of the Church ſhould ſtrive to increaſe more and more in grace and goodneſs.</hi> They ſhould ſtrongly be induced to this; becauſe of their own imperfection in Grace, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection fills them many times with inward trouble, and tormenting doubts and fears; and makes outward affliction but highly neceſſary. Beſides, Holineſs is of ſuch an excellent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo perfective of the Nature of man, that the ſtrongeſt deſires are to be juſtified, the moſt diligent endeavours after it to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</p>
            <p>Grace is increaſed in the Members of Chriſt ſeveral wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a <hi>Serious and frequent engaging in thoſe Ordinances which he has inſtituted.</hi> He that has inſtituted theſe, has promiſed his bleſſing, and adds the efficacy. Prayer, Faſting, giving of thanks, receiving the Supper of the Lord, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon the Word preached, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, and the like means of Grace, when ſeriouſly uſed, do exceedingly promote the growth of a Chriſtian, making him to become ſtrong in Spirit. The Church is the Garden of God; the Saints are planted there; the Word and Ordinances of Chriſt are like the ſhowers from Heaven, and the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans pains, which makes theſe Plants to thrive and flouriſh. <hi>Pſal. 92. Thoſe that be planted in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56801:28"/> houſe of the Lord ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of our God:</hi> But ſtill it muſt be remembred, though means are to be uſed, yet we muſt look beyond them, unto him that has appointed them, elſe they will never attain their end, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 7. So then neither is he that planteth any thing, nor he that watereth, but God that giveth the increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Grace is increaſed by the <hi>improving of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences.</hi> The Diſpenſations of Providence were various towards <hi>David;</hi> he was exerciſed with great Severity, and likewiſe with great Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; we read <hi>Pſal. 116. 3. That the ſorrows of Death compaſſed him, and the pains of Hell gat hold upon him, he found trouble and ſorrow:</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 10. He was greatly afflicted; in this diſtreſs he calls upon that God who is merciful and gracious, for deliverance, and his calling is heard, and his <hi>Soul is delivered from Death, his Eyes from Tears, and his Feet from Falling:</hi> And now how is his Heart affected! his Graces ſtrengthned! He is filled with Love, he is reſolved to give himſelf to Prayer as long as he lived, his Soul is at reſt in God who had dealt bountifully with him, he offers the Sacrifice of Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and he cryes out, <hi>Oh Lord I am thy Servant, truly I am thy Servant,</hi> v. 16. as if he ſhould ſay, Lord! thou art a Maſter beyond all compariſon; and as it is my firm reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, ſo 'tis my Happineſs and Honour, as well as Duty to be a Servant to thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Covenant of Grace is to be Studied, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56801:28"/> the Promiſes applyed in order to a Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi> God has aſſured his People that he will <hi>perfect that which concerns them,</hi> and that he will not forſake the work of his own hands: He has ſaid, that his Servants ſhall <hi>Spring up as among the Graſs, and as Willows by the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,</hi> Iſa. 44. 4. <hi>That the Righteous ſhall hold on his way, and they that have clean hands ſhall wax ſtronger and ſtronger,</hi> Job 17. 9. That they ſhall <hi>bring forth fruit even in Old Age,</hi> and even then be <hi>flouriſhing,</hi> and this ſhall be <hi>to ſhew that the Lord is upright,</hi> Pſal. 92. 14, 15. Such Promiſes being prized and applyed, will make the New Creature full of vigour, and perſeverance will be certain. Heark to the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> r. 6, 7. <hi>Being confident of this very thing, that he who hath begun a good work in you, will perform it unto the day of Jeſus Chriſt, even as it is meet for me to think this of you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Grace is increaſed by <hi>Having recourſe unto that fulneſs which dwells in Chriſt.</hi> Therefore <hi>growing in Grace</hi> and <hi>growing in the Knowledge of Chriſt</hi> are joyned together; for Chriſt is <hi>full of Grace and Truth,</hi> and <hi>out of his fulneſs</hi> ſayes St. <hi>John, We all have received and Grace for Grace,</hi> Joh. 1. 14, 16. that is, Grace anſwerable to that Grace which is in him. Grace is his purchaſe, he has it in Poſſeſſion, he gives it to all that have it, and every new degree is from the ſame hand; He is the Object, <hi>the Author and</hi> the <hi>Finiſher of Faith,</hi> Heb. 12. 2. They are the moſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56801:29"/> growing and eſtabliſhed Saints, that are leaſt taken with the World, that have leaſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in themſelves, that do beſt underſtand, and moſt <hi>look unto Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. All <hi>impediments of increaſe muſt be carefully ſhunn'd,</hi> as Pride, and ſloth and earthlineſs, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and corrupt affections; if theſe, or things of like nature prevail, they will prove to the Soul, what Diſeaſes are to the Body, and make the Members of Chriſt to be feeble and languiſh, depriving them both of their Strength and Beauty. Theſe are like peccant humours, which muſt be Purged if we would have our <hi>Souls healthy and proſperous:</hi> Theſe are like <hi>weights which muſt be laid aſide,</hi> if we will <hi>run the Race that is ſet before us,</hi> ſo as to obtain the Prize, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 1.</p>
            <p>In the third place I am to produce <hi>ſeveral reaſons</hi> why <hi>the Church ſhould be continually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This increaſe is <hi>for the Fathers glory,</hi> the more Saints there are, God is honoured by the more; and the more any are Saints, he has ſtill the more glory from them. The ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the members of Chriſt grow; their Faith in God is firmer, their fear more filial, they love him more with their heart, and Soul, and ſtrength, they walk more humbly with him: all which ſhews what right apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they have of him, and that they glorifie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56801:29"/> him as God, believing his preſence, power, mercy, truth and righteouſneſs. That our Lord might perſwade unto fruitfulneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, he ſayes <hi>Joh. 15. 8. Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much fruit, ſo ſhall ye be my Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This increaſe of the Church is <hi>for the honour of Chriſt the Churches Head.</hi> The large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Dominion, and the multitude of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, is the honour of a Prince: The more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians there are, the Kingdom of our Lord is the more enlarged, and He himſelf is magnified the more. The Redeemer is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified when the Everlaſting Goſpel <hi>runs;</hi> when his word which is the Scepter of his Kingdom is believed and obeyed: when Souls by whole multitudes come flocking to him, to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by his blood, ſanctified and healed by his grace, and ſaved to the uttermoſt. How was Chriſt honoured, when after the ten firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire ſubmitted to the Faith, the <hi>Eagle</hi> gave way to the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great threw down his Crown at the feet of the Lamb of God: Then was that Scripture ſignally fulfilled, though a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accompliſhment is ſtill to be expected, <hi>Iſa. 55. 5. Behold thou ſhalt call a Nation that thou knoweſt not, and Nations that knew not thee ſhall run unto thee, becauſe of the Lord thy God, and for the Holy One of Iſrael, for he hath glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56801:30"/>3. In this increaſe of the Church the <hi>operae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit is very illuſtrious.</hi> He wrought the miracles for the confirmation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and made it at firſt to be entertained in the world. Wherever there is true Faith, it is of his beſtowing. Thoſe that are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated are ſaid to be <hi>born of the Spirit,</hi> Joh. 3. 6. The <hi>renewing</hi> of a Soul is <hi>of the Holy Ghost,</hi> Tit. 3. 5. All ſpiritual gifts, all true grace, all ſolid comforts are from the Spirit. The more therefore Light is ſpread, the more largely gifts are diſtributed, the more plentiful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication there is of grace, the more peace and joy abounds; the greater is the Spirits glory. The <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> calls the Spirit <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord and Giver of life. <hi>Quot Membrae, tot Miracula;</hi> So many members as Chriſt has, ſo many miracles there are of the Spirits working; for he has raiſed them all to life, who were once dead in ſins and treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as well as others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Increaſe is <hi>for the Churches advantage,</hi> therefore it ſhould be endeavoured. 'Tis mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of joy and praiſe to Saints, to behold ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners converted and ſanctified, to ſee Prodigals coming to themſelves, and coming home to their Fathers Houſe; to ſee <hi>ſtrangers and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners made fellow-Citizens with the Saints, and of the Houſhold of God,</hi> Eph. 2. 19. And when theſe Saints perceive, that more of light is imparted to themſelves, and that they are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56801:30"/> fuller with the <hi>fruits of righteouſneſs which are by Jeſus Chriſt, to the Glory and praiſe of God;</hi> they muſt needs apprehend this to be for their profit, if the trueſt riches may be called gains, and Pearls of the greateſt price be of any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>World is benefited by the Churches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi> Not a Soul gathered out of the World, but ſomething is ſecured of greater value than the World. If a City were on fire, and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apace to the ground, the more perſons are ſaved, the more Goods are ſecured, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er kindneſs is done to that City; becauſe theſe Perſons, theſe Goods eſcape the fury of the flames. Sin is ruining the World apace; but all that in time come out from the World, and touch not the unclean thing, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into the Church of Chriſt; are ſafe as in a Sanctuary, ſhall be delivered from the common deſtruction, and ſcape the vengeance of eternal fire, in which all the wicked muſt burn for ever.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The <hi>Angels themſelves are concerned at the increaſe of the Church.</hi> The Apoſtate Ones are confounded, when by all their ſubtilty and ſtrength they are not able to hinder <hi>the increaſe of Chriſts Government;</hi> nay, that they are ſo over-ruled, that they are made to promote his Kingdom by thoſe very means which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to overthrow it. And the Elect Angels are affirmed to <hi>rejoyce</hi> at the Repentance and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56801:31"/> of a Sinner: <hi>Luk. 15. 10. Likewiſe I ſay unto you, there is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one ſinner that repenteth.</hi> And if they are ſo glad at the Converſion of one, what an acceſſion would it be to their joy, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thouſands and millions, added to the Church of Chriſt! 'Tis pleaſing to the Angels to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>peace on Earth,</hi> and <hi>Gods good-will</hi> expreſſing it ſelf in the Salvation of <hi>Men,</hi> Luk. 2. 14. and upon this account they cry, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Glory be to God in the higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Application follows.</p>
            <p>USE 1. Of Reproof to them that hinder the Churches increaſe. The furtherers of it I am ſure are few, the hinderers many; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more are concerned in the Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Enemies without</hi> endeavour with might and main to hinder the increaſe of the Body of Chriſt. They hate the light, and would fain hinder it from ſhining; they are grieved that Jeſus is preached, are angry as well as grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; for they are unwilling his Subjects ſhould become numerous. The World upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count raiſes Perſecution; and how many at ſuch a time <hi>do fall away!</hi> Mat. 13. 21. <hi>Cyprian</hi> laments the preſſure of that Perſecution which had ſo wofully waſted the Flock he was over; and ſayes that <hi>poſiti erant inter plangentium ruinas, &amp; timen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium reliqutas; inter numeroſam languentium ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56801:31"/> &amp; exiguam ſtantium paucitatem.</hi> L. 4. Ep. 4. Many were ruined, the reſt feared, the Church languiſhed; and few did ſtand againſt ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous an aſſault. We have <hi>large Martyrologies;</hi> but if <hi>all Apoſtates</hi> were regiſtred, how <hi>vaſt</hi> would be the <hi>Catalogues</hi> of them! 'Tis well <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation</hi> laſts but <hi>ten dayes,</hi> a ſhort time; elſe the World might tread the Church under. But the Worlds rage is without reaſon, againſt the Church of Chriſt, which will do no harm, and deſires to do the World the greateſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Hypocrites within</hi> are to be reproved, for they hinder the Churches increaſe; fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>Vipers,</hi> which are ſaid to eat the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els in which they were bred. Our Lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is very hot, and his words ſharp againſt Hypocrites, <hi>Mat. 23. 13. For they ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven againſt men; they refuſe to go in themſelves, neither ſuffer they them that are entring to go in.</hi> They profeſs high, but when they fall, and notoriouſly diſcover their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſs, they wound the reputation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, unto the Churches grief and diſadvantage, and the hardning of the Ungodly in their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; their Convictions hereby being quite and clean extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Churches increaſe is likewiſe hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by <hi>imprudent Members.</hi> Such are not ſo careful to avoid appearances of evil themſelves; and they blaze abroad the Infirmities of others,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56801:32"/> which love ſhould find a Mantle to cover; nay many times they hear and report the moſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant lies and ſlanders, whereby not only the Perſon ſlandered, but likewiſe Religion and the Church ſuffers. Theſe fools deſerve to be laſh'd ſeverely for their inconſiderate talkativeneſs, and uncircumſpect walking: And they ſhould remember, that the Diſciples of Chriſt are to be <hi>wiſe as Serpents, and harmleſs as Doves,</hi> Mat. 10. 16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Erroneous Members and Church-dividers</hi> are deeply guilty of hindring the increaſe of the Church. Errour has a natural tendency to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion; for they that ſpeak <hi>perverſe things,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to <hi>draw away Diſciples after them,</hi> Act. 20. 30. And Diviſion is a grand Impediment to edification. The Church of Chriſt after the giving of the Spirit on the day of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> did grow exceedingly; and one reaſon was, becauſe the <hi>Multitude of them that believed, were of one heart, and of one ſoul;</hi> Act. 4. 32. But di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion weakens the Churches ſtrength, and turns her own Members againſt her, by turning them one againſt another. The Apoſtle ſeverely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes the <hi>Corinthians</hi> upon this ſcore, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>For ye are yet carnal; for whereas there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men? q. d.</hi> This unpeace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and dividing temper makes you act not not like Members of Chriſt, but like <hi>Men</hi> of the World, whom Chriſt bids his Diſciples to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56801:32"/> of, as Enemies to his Intereſt and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Indeed the Corruptions of others are not to be approved; yet what is good and ſound is to be own'd; and we are to be taken with the Image of Chriſt in whomſoever we ſee it ſhining.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Slothful, unfaithful, proud and ſelfiſh Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tours</hi> deſerve as ſharp a rebuke as any, becauſe the Churches increaſe is hindred by theſe with a witneſs. Such <hi>ſeek their own things, not the things of Chriſt; their own profit, not the profit of many that they may be ſaved.</hi> 'Tis ordinary with them, to <hi>make the heart of the righteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſad, whom God has not made ſad, and to strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hands of the wicked, that he ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from his wicked way, by promiſing him life</hi> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ezek. 13. 22. The Prophet propheſies ſharply againſt the Shepherds of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 34. 2, 3. 4. <hi>Woe to the Shepherds of Iſrael who feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, not the flock. The diſeaſed have ye no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> strengthened; neither have ye healed that which was ſick; neither have ye bound up that which was broken, neither have ye brought again that which was driven away; neither have ye ſought that which was lost: but with force and with cruelty have ye ruled them.</hi> Now if the flock be thus neglected, 'tis likely to be leſſen'd, and the Church to be brought very low. Oh dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful account that ſuch Paſtours have to give both of themſelves and of the flock, unto the Great Shepherd, at the laſt day!</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:56801:33"/>
            <p>USE II. Of <hi>encouragement unto the Church of Christ notwithstanding her Imperfection.</hi> Her Spirit ſhould not ſink into deſpondency becauſe perfection is not yet attained to; but ſeveral truths may be offer'd as grounds of ſupport.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Righteouſneſs which is imputed to the Church of Chriſt is perfect.</hi> Though their Faith, though their evangelical obedience be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, yet the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which their faith layes hold on is every way com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. <hi>The obedience of one,</hi> that is the Son of God, is ſufficient to <hi>make many righteous</hi> though never ſo many do believe, <hi>Rom. 5. 19. By one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified,</hi> Heb. 10. 14. The Apoſtle indeed is aſhamed of his own Righteouſneſs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to be found in it, and deſires <hi>to be found in Chriſt,</hi> and that he might have on <hi>that Righteouſneſs which is of God by faith.</hi> The obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ſufferings of Chriſt are the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs imputed to them that believe; and 'tis called the Righteouſneſs of God, becauſe God contrived it, and accepts it; and Chriſt who obeyed and ſuffered, is not only man but <hi>over all God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Chriſt has done and ſuffered enough to ſatisfie divine juſtice, to ranſom and ſave ſouls; and to obtain eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Redemption for us: and here is a firm ground for the Churches conſolation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Sins of the Churches Members are all
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56801:33"/> pardon'd;</hi> not ſo much as <hi>one</hi> is unforgiven; <hi>Col. 2. 13. Having forgiven you all treſpaſſes.</hi> Pſal. 103. 12. <hi>As far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt ſo far hath he removed all our tranſgreſſions from us. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xori lis non intenditur.</hi> The Church is eſpouſed to Chriſt, and he has ſatisfied the Law and Juſtice for all her offences: it may joyfully be ſaid therefore, <hi>There is no condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 8. 1. Her Head and Husband having paid the Churches debts; payment from her is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, ſhall not be demanded.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Churches members are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, yet the <hi>leaſt degree of true grace ſhall be owned.</hi> The ſmalleſt Stars are Stars, and are fixt in Heaven as well as the greateſt. The weakeſt Saints are Saints, and as ſuch ſhall be regarded. 'Tis ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>He ſhall feed his flock like a Shepherd, he ſhall gather the Lambs with his Arm, and carry them in his boſom,</hi> Iſa. 40. 11. The feebleſt of Chriſtians ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in need of cheriſhing, and they ſhall have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they need. Our Lord <hi>will not break the bruiſed reed; nor quench the ſmoaking flax; untill he ſends forth judgment unto victory,</hi> Mat. 12. 20.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Church of Chriſt notwithſtanding her imperfection, is in a <hi>ſafer ſtate than</hi> Adam <hi>was in Innocency.</hi> The Union between his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Him, was not ſo indiſſoluble as the Union between Chriſt and true Believers. Life was promiſed to him upon condition of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56801:34"/> in obedience, but he had not a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Grace to make him perſevere: But the Saints have ſuch a Promiſe; God has ſaid. He will <hi>put his fear in their Hearts, that they ſhall not depart from him,</hi> Jer. 32. 40. That he will <hi>ſtrengthen and uphold them with the right hand of his righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 41. 10. That <hi>none ſhall pluck them out of the hand of Chriſt,</hi> nor <hi>out of the Fathers hand, who is greater than all,</hi> Joh. 10. 28, 29. That <hi>nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate them from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus their Lord,</hi> Rom. 8. <hi>ult. Adam</hi> was intruſted with a Treaſure in his own keeping; but he loſt it, and beggar'd himſelf and his whole Progeny: Believers therefore are not thus truſted; both themſelves and their Treaſure are in the hands of him that is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, and ſo both are ſecured: <hi>Their life is hid with Christ in God,</hi> Col. 3. 3.</p>
            <p>USE. III. Of Advice unto the Church of Chriſt, and all her true Members.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let their <hi>imperfection keep them humble.</hi> There is not a Soul without a ſtain, nor a Grace without a mixture, nor a Duty without a failing, nor a Saint without ſome ſin remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. All therefore, nay, the very beſt of all, have reaſon to be low in their own eyes. The more humble we are, the more our hearts are ſuited to our preſent imperfect ſtate; and the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56801:34"/> more of Gods reviving Preſence, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our imperfection, will be vouchſafed. <hi>For, thus ſaith the High and Lofty One, who inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Eternity, whoſe Name is holy; I dwell in the high and holy place; with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble Spirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones,</hi> Iſa. 57. 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the Churches Members <hi>hunger and thirst after a greater meaſure of righteouſneſs.</hi> Thoſe that to do ſo, are <hi>bleſſed, for they ſhall be filled,</hi> ſayes he in whom all Fulneſs dwells, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 6. This is an hunger truly <hi>ſacred,</hi> that never ends in ſtarving, but in ſatisfaction. We ſhould long more for the Waters of Life; the Soul ſhould thirſt more vehemently for the living God, deſiring to behold his glory, and to be changed more fully into his glorious Image. Such kind of deſires widen the Souls capacity, and make it meet for a larger participation both of Grace and comfort.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let the Church believe and long for that <hi>enlargement and glory</hi> that is promiſed in the <hi>latter dayes;</hi> but eſpecially to be <hi>tranſlated unto thoſe Manſions above,</hi> which her <hi>Head</hi> is gone <hi>to prepare for her.</hi> Let her long that her War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare may be well accompliſhed, her courſe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully finiſhed, and the Crown of Life and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs received: And to this end, let all her Members tear the Air, and pierce the Heavens with their cryes; <hi>Come Lord Jeſus, come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:56801:35"/> Rev. 22. 20. Thus, of the Second Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>That the Body of Chriſt is imperfect in this World, and therefore continually ſhould be encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſit.</hi> III. The Third Propoſition follows; <hi>That the Body of Chriſt ſhould diligently endeavour the edifying of it ſelf.</hi> Before the Apoſtle had uſed the Metaphor of <hi>a Body;</hi> now he uſes another Metaphor of <hi>an Edifice</hi> or Building. The Church is to <hi>edify it ſelf,</hi> but the Power to do this is from God; and her Lord, who acts and ſtrengthens her in this action, lays a juſt claim to all the glory. The Church is an Edifice, or an Houſe, but a <hi>Spiritual one;</hi> therefore called a <hi>Temple.</hi> Eph. 2. 21, 22. <hi>In whom,</hi> that is, Chriſt, <hi>all the building fitly framed together, groweth unto an holy Temple in the Lord: In whom you alſo are builded together for an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarion of God through the Spirit.</hi> This <hi>Temple</hi> is <hi>holy,</hi> for God hath <hi>ſet apart ſuch as are godly for himſelf:</hi> The Stones are <hi>lively,</hi> for all Saints are quickened, to live to God, and act for him. In this Temple <hi>Sacrifices are offered,</hi> but they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſpiritual; <hi>Prayers, Praiſes,</hi> other <hi>Duties,</hi> and the <hi>Heart</hi> of him that performs them. And though theſe Sacrifices are never ſo ſpiritual, yet they are not accepted upon their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, but they are <hi>acceptable unto God throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 5.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:56801:35"/>
            <p>In the further handling of this Propoſition, I ſhall Firſt, Shew <hi>upon what foundation the Church is to Edify it ſelf.</hi> Secondly, <hi>To what end this Edification muſt be.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Make Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place I am to ſhew, <hi>upon what foundation the Church is to edify it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Knowledge of God</hi> is ſtyled <hi>a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 19. <hi>Nevertheleſs the foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, having this Seal, The Lord knoweth them that are his.</hi> God has from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity foreknown and <hi>choſen his Church in Chriſt, that ſhe ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love,</hi> Eph. 1. 4. This is a Foundation laid before the Foundation of the World; and will endure infinitely longer than the World ſhall. The Churches Members ſhould <hi>give all diligence to make their calling and Election ſure; for if they do theſe things, they ſhall never fall, but an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant entrance ſhall be adminiſtred to them into the everlasting Kingdom,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 10, 11. Now Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made ſure by hearkening to, and <hi>obeying the call</hi> of the Goſpel, and <hi>departing from Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Christ</hi> the Rock, is called a <hi>Foundation,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 11. <hi>Other Foundation can no man lay, than that is laid, which is Jeſus Christ.</hi> Though he <hi>was ſet at nought</hi> by the <hi>Jewiſh builders, yet he is the head Stone of the Corner; neither is there Salvation in any other.</hi> The Churches Faith muſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56801:36"/> be firmer in Chriſt; her hope in him more and more abundant; and ſhe may build with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear; for the Foundation will never fail the Superſtructure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Doctrine of the Apostles and Prophets</hi> is alſo ſtyled a <hi>Foundation,</hi> Eph. 2. 20. Both were inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt; and the harmony and agreement between Apoſtles and Prophets, between the Old Teſtament and the New, makes the Foundation more ſure. The Church, that ſhe may edifie her ſelf, is to eye the Scripture; then ſhe will build according to the right rule. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten Traditions</hi> that would impoſe upon her Faith what the Scripture has not revealed, are to be rejected; and that <hi>light within</hi> that would lead her away from the written Word, is no more to be followed than a fooliſh Night-fire. If ſhe has Scripture for her Faith and Practice, ſhe has good ground for both; and both may be juſtified before the Judge of all the World.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>good Works</hi> are called <hi>a Foundation.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 19. <hi>Laying up in ſtore for themſelves a good Foundation against the time to come, that they may lay hold on Eternal life.</hi> This is done by <hi>doing good,</hi> by being <hi>rich in good works.</hi> Though good works are not meritorious, for Eternal Life is the <hi>Gift</hi> of God; yet they are neceſſary to evidence out Faith, and that the Promiſes may be fulfilled <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Glory and Immortality</hi> is promiſed to them who
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56801:36"/> by <hi>patient continuance in well-doing ſeek for it,</hi> Rom. 2. 7. He builds firm, that builds his houſe <hi>upon a Rock;</hi> and he builds thus, who <hi>hears the Words of Christ, and does them:</hi> But he that hears, and <hi>does them not,</hi> is a <hi>fooliſh man,</hi> and <hi>builds his houſe upon the ſand; and when the rain deſcends, and the winds blow, and the floods come, and beat upon his houſe, it will fall, and great will be the fall of it,</hi> Mat. 7. 24, 25, 26, 27.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place I am to tell you, <hi>to what end this Edification of the Church muſt be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church muſt Edifie it ſelf, that it may grow <hi>Stronger.</hi> The ſtronger her Faith is, the more will ſhe <hi>Glorifie</hi> that God in whom ſhe believes: <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 20. 'tis ſaid of <hi>Abraham; He ſtaggered not at the Promiſe of God through <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, but was ſtrong in Faith, giving glory to God.</hi> The ſtronger her Love, the more it will conſtrain her to labour in her Lords work, and caſt out the fear of ſuffering for his ſake; for a ſtrong love is <hi>ſtronger than Death,</hi> and has <hi>a moſt vehement flame; many waters cannot quench it, neither can the floods drown it,</hi> Cant. 8. 6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Church muſt Edifie it ſelf, that it may become <hi>Larger.</hi> Prayer ſhould be inſtant and conſtant, and pains ſhould be taken both by Paſtors and People, and Godlineſs ſhould be both in Form and Power, that ſo the <hi>Mountain of the Houſe of the Lord, may be eſtabliſhed in the top
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56801:37"/> of the Mountains, and exalted above the Hills, and all Nations may flow unto it,</hi> Iſa. 2. 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church muſt Edifie it ſelf, that it may become more <hi>Beautiful and Glorious.</hi> The great day of the Churches <hi>publick Marriage to the Lamb,</hi> is approaching; how careful ſhould ſhe be to cleanſe and adorn her ſelf, that ſhe may be <hi>found of him, in Peace without ſpot and blameleſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 14. This Beauty and Glory which the Church is to endeavour after, and to long and hope for, you have deſcribed <hi>Rev. 21. 9, 10. Come hither, and I will ſhew thee the Bride, the Lambs Wife: And he carried me away in the Spirit to a great and high Mountain, and ſhewed me that great City the holy Jeruſalem, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending out of Heaven from God, having the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God; and her light was like unto a ſtone moſt precious, even like a Jaſpar-ſtone, clear as Chryſtal, the walls were high, the twelve Gates were all Pearls, the Street of the City was pure Gold, as it were tranſparent glaſs: and I ſaw no Temple therein, for the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb are the Temple of it: And the City had no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it, for the glory of God did lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof.</hi> What is the glory of <hi>Solomons</hi> Kingdom or Temple, or of the whole World, if compared with the Beauty of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which the moſt valuable things in nature, as Gold and Jewels, are uſed to ſet forth, but fall exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhort of what they ſignifie?</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:56801:37"/>
            <p>I ſhall now make a brief Application.</p>
            <p>USE I. It is matter of great Lamentation, that the Church at preſent is ſo far from <hi>Edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſelf, that 'tis doing quite the contrary;</hi> 'tis about to be <hi>Felo de ſe,</hi> to deſtroy and to pull it ſelf down to the ground, if the God of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Love and Peace, do not hinder. The Poet lookt upon it as truly lamentable, that the Roman State was engaged in a Civil War where there could be no Triumph after Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; that <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> both brave, both <hi>Roman</hi> Generals, ſhould fight ſo eagerly, ſo bloodily one againſt the other: but ſurely 'tis one of the ſaddeſt ſights in the World, to ſee the Members of the Body of Chriſt at variance, and biting and devouring, and doing that to one another, which the ſierceſt Perſecution was never able to effect. Alas for Wo! that the Church of Chriſt ſhould be militant, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe of her <hi>fighting</hi> with <hi>Enemies,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Diſcord among her own <hi>Members.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Suis &amp; ipſa Eccleſia viribus ruit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> The Church employes her own force to her own ruine. Paſtours are ſet againſt Paſtours, Saints againſt Saints, Sermons againſt Sermons, nay, Prayers againſt Prayers, and <hi>Sion</hi> is become like a <hi>Babel</hi> of Confuſion!
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>—Quis talia fando</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Temperet à lachrymis?—</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Well may the Prophets words be here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56801:38"/> 
               <hi>Ezek. 19. 14. This is a lamentation, and ſhall be for a lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE II. Of Advice. Let the Churches <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication be minded:</hi> Let all ſtudy and <hi>follow the things that make for Peace, and things wherewith one may Edifie another,</hi> Rom. 14. 19. 'Tis not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the greateſt of men to put their hands to this work, of Building. the Houſe of God; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it ſhould ſtrenuouſly be ſet about by All, <hi>Magiſtrates, Miniſters, People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Churches Edification is to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Magiſtrates.</hi> Their Authority ſhould be ſubſervient to the Authority of Him <hi>by whom they Reign,</hi> Prov. 8. 15. <hi>By me Kings Reign, and Princes decree Juſtice.</hi> The Laws of Kingdoms and States ſhould alwayes promote and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Progreſs of the Goſpel. Truth and Holineſs do ever deſerve the countenance of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but ſin is worthy of a frown. Thoſe Princes who are moſt for the Churches wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, do moſt conſult their own; <hi>If Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs exalts a Nation, and ſin be the reproach and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ine of any People,</hi> Prov. 14. 34; then the more the Church is Edified, the more firmly both Throne and Kingdom are eſtabliſhed. <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> his Zeal for Religion was attended with a bleſſed Proſperity, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. 21. <hi>In every work that he began in the Service of the houſe of God, and in the Law, and in the Commandments, to ſeek his God, he did it with all his Heart, and he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:56801:38"/>2. The Churches Edification is to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Miniſters:</hi> 'tis their office more peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be <hi>Labourers together with God,</hi> in his <hi>Husbandry</hi> and <hi>Building, 1 Cor. 3. 9.</hi> They ſhould Pray, Preach, Live ſo as to Edifie. Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and worldly advantage are poor things; <hi>Edification! Edification</hi> is moſt truly conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſhould ſound in their Ears, ſhould be upon their Hearts, and endeavoured with their utmoſt abilities. They muſt <hi>be blameleſs as the Stewards of God,</hi> and faithfully diſpenſe food to Souls; <hi>They muſt not be Self-willed, not ſoon Angry, not given to Wine, no Strikers, not given to filthy L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cre; but lovers of Hoſpitality, lovers of good Men, Sober, Juſt, Holy, Temperate,</hi> Tit. 1. 7, 8. Then they are like to Build the Houſe of God indeed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>People</hi> alſo ſhould endeavour the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Church: They ſhould by a good example <hi>provoke one another to love and good works; No corrupt Communication ſhould proceed out of their Mouths, but that which is good to the uſe of Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, and which may adminiſter Grace to the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs,</hi> Eph. 4 29. They are to <hi>pleaſe</hi> one another for <hi>Edification:</hi> Rom. 15. 2. And in all <hi>Reproofs</hi> let <hi>Love</hi> and a <hi>deſire to Edifie</hi> be apparent in the <hi>Reprover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude with a few Arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all to Edifie the Church.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church of Chriſt is hugely <hi>out of repair,</hi> the breaches are great, and there is much
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56801:39"/> rubbiſh to be removed: and where there is ſo much work to be done, the Labourers ſhould be the greater number, and the more diligent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. While you are building his Church the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf <hi>will be with you,</hi> and then no matter for oppoſition. Greater is he that is in you, than he that is in the World. When <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was building <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he was derided, he was oppoſed, but he was not diſcouraged, neither did the work ceaſe; and the Enemies were forced to an acknowledgment that <hi>God was with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Your labour ſhall <hi>not be in vain,</hi> either as to <hi>ſucceſs</hi> or as to <hi>reward.</hi> Some good you <hi>ſhall do,</hi> who do deſire it, and God takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice how much more you <hi>would do,</hi> and will reward you accordingly. The Lord is too good a Maſter to ſuffer any of his faithful la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers and ſervants to want encouragement. <hi>David</hi> had it in his <hi>heart</hi> to build him an houſe; and God <hi>eſtabliſhes the houſe of David,</hi> 1 Chron. 17. 23. and his family was upheld, till Chriſt the Son of <hi>David</hi> came. I have done with the third Propoſition; <hi>That the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt ſhould diligently endeavour the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſit.</hi> IIII. The fourth and laſt Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this. <hi>The more Love abounds among the members of the Church, the more the whole Body will be edified;</hi> or more briefly thus: <hi>Love is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56801:39"/> exceedingly for the Churches edification.</hi> I might be large in diſcourſing of <hi>Love to Chriſt,</hi> and manifeſt how this will conſtrain all in whom it is, to endeavour the edification of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and to ſeek the welfare of thoſe for whom he died. One who loves the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity, how can he chuſe but love all Saints though of different perſwaſions, ſince notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that difference they are all ſo dear to him, that he gave his life a ranſom for them all; and the <hi>blood of God</hi> was ſhed for every one of them, that there might be a price paid ſufficient for their Redemption.</p>
            <p>But the Apoſtle is to be underſtood in my Text of Chriſtians <hi>love one to another.</hi> This is that Charity which the Scripture calls ſo loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for: <hi>Joh. 13. 34. A new Commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye alſo love one another;</hi> the command is <hi>doubled,</hi> and called a <hi>new</hi> commandment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though delivered long before, yet here 'tis delivered with a <hi>new example,</hi> that of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>(as I have loved you)</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a new and ſtrongly enforcing motive. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> gives this charge, <hi>1 Pet. 4. 8. Above all things have fervent charity among your ſelves. Gifts</hi> though excellent, may be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and perverſely employed, to inſtill Errour, and rend the Church of God. <hi>Knowledge</hi> if it be alone, will not profit but <hi>puſſ up</hi> him that has it: But <hi>Charity edifieth,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 1. Love
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56801:40"/> is greatly beneficial; its acts are pure, and peaceable, and gentle, full of mercy and good fruits; and 'tis againſt the very nature of it to work ill to any.</p>
            <p>In the handling of the Propoſition, I ſhall Firſt, <hi>Diſcourſe concerning the Nature of Love.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Diſcover the Properties which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture attributes to it.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Demonſtrate how it is for the Churches Edification.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Shew the vanity of thoſe excuſes that are made for the want of love.</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Apply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt place I am to diſcourſe <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nature of love.</hi> There is a fourfold Love, <hi>Carnal, Natural, Civil, Spiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Carnal, and impure:</hi> Thus <hi>Amnon loved his fair Siſter Tamar,</hi> 2 Sam. 13. 1. and <hi>Sampſon</hi> fell in love with <hi>Delilah;</hi> but this impure af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection coſt both theſe their lives, and brought the one and the other to an untimely end. This may more properly be called <hi>Luſt</hi> than Love; and in whatever heart 'tis harbour'd, how does it defile and harden! If but a ſpark of luſt be let alone, what a flame may quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, which may conſume the Eſtate, the Reputation, the Body and the Soul: it may indeed be extenuated; but 'tis threatned with the wrath of God. Not only for <hi>fornication</hi> but for <hi>evil concupiſcence,</hi> cometh <hi>the wrath of God upon the Children of diſobedience,</hi> Col. 3. 5, 6. When Luſt is ſuffer'd to conceive and bring
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56801:40"/> forth actual Adultery, how do the Adulterer and his Strumpet ſhew their hatred one to the other! The miſchief they do themſelves is inconceiveable: and how do they defile each the others Body, wound each the others Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and delight in that whereby they damn each the others Soul!</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a Love which is <hi>Natural.</hi> I mean <hi>Natural affection.</hi> To have this natural affection is a duty, for 'tis planted in the heart by the wiſe and gracious God, as that which has a mighty tendency to the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Mankind: therefore to be <hi>without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural affection,</hi> the Apoſtle makes one of the crimes of them who were given up to <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind,</hi> to do <hi>thoſe things which were not convenient,</hi> Rom. 1. 28, 31. Natural affection we owe unto Relations; which debt if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to pay, we ſhut our ears to the dictates of Nature, as well as the word of Chriſt, and become worſe than Infidels, nay worſe than the beaſts that periſh. Parents muſt love their Children, Children their Parents, Husbands and Wives be full of affection to one another: But Grace ſhould <hi>ſpiritualize</hi> this Natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Not only the perſons of our Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be loved, but their Souls; and their eternal Salvation moſt earneſtly deſired and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured; and if we cannot bear the thoughts of a Parents, Husbands, Wives, or Childs pain, poverty, ſlavery, ſtarving; the thoughts
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56801:41"/> of their being eternally damn'd, ſhould be much more intolerable! and all means ſhould be uſed to prevent it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a Love which may be ſtyled <hi>Civil.</hi> This is one of the great bonds of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Societies, whereby they are kept toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; whereas hatred and diſcord, do firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and then deſtroy them. This <hi>Amor patriae,</hi> love to our Countrey, the more it prevails, the more will our Countrey flouriſh. In a Kingdom, the whole ſhould be concerned for every indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual; and every individual for the whole; and all the parts for one another. No mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhould haſtily be concluded a gangren'd one; that is</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enſe recidendum, ne pars ſincera trahatur;</hi> Preſently to be cut off, leſt the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity be endanger'd. <hi>Draco</hi> is not lookt upon as one of the wiſeſt Legiſlators, who made al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Offence capital, and therefore is ſaid to have <hi>writ his Laws in blood.</hi> A mild Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſuch as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> is, does beſt ſuit with Chriſtianity, and is likelieſt to attain the end of Magiſtracy, the <hi>Higheſt Sovereigns glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the <hi>King and Kingdoms ſafety.</hi> Love ſhould make all the Subjects of a Kingdom to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Relation they have to, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in one another; and no Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies ſhould be allowed; but onely deſigns and endeavours of one anothers wealth and welfare; eſpecially the trueſt wealth, and the welfare that is eternal.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:56801:41"/>
            <p>I cannot but here bewail the <hi>want</hi> of this <hi>Civil love,</hi> and the variance that is in my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country. <hi>New Names</hi> of diſcrimination are invented, which our forefathers knew not. Breaches grow <hi>wide as the Sea;</hi> who but the God of Love and Peace can heal them? A <hi>perverſe Spirit</hi> mingles it ſelf among different Parties; and differences are kept up, and ſtill increaſed with an unuſual animoſity. When <hi>Phaeton</hi> had ſet the World on fire, the Poet by an elegant <hi>Proſopopoeia</hi> brings in the Earth it ſelf thus pleading,
<q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoſne mihi fructus? hunc fertilitatis honorem, Officiique refers? &amp;c.</hi>—</p>
               </q> And may not <hi>England,</hi> which at this day is in a flame of Contention, be introduced thus <hi>ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to her Inhabitants?</p>
            <p>O <hi>Engliſh-men, what means this more than</hi> civil Diſcord and Fury <hi>among you? In Me you have been</hi> born <hi>and</hi> bred: <hi>And conſidering the temperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Climate, the fruitfulneſs of the Soil, the variety of Delights; where can you find a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Land, that might</hi> reaſonably be wiſht to have been the Land of your Nativity? <hi>Be not I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you ſo unnatural, as to fill and</hi> load me with ſin, <hi>and to make me</hi> deſolate, a Land not inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited. <hi>The Corn I bear, the abundance of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Fruit I produce, the Beaſts I nouriſh for your food, the wholeſome Air you breath in;</hi> for all
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56801:42"/> theſe, <hi>it would be an</hi> unworthy requital <hi>to turn me into an</hi> Aceldama, <hi>a Field of Blood. I have been a Land of</hi> Light <hi>to you, as well as fruitful: The</hi> Sun of Righteouſneſs <hi>has ſhined as</hi> clearly and gloriouſly <hi>in</hi> Me, <hi>as in any Nation under Heaven. Oh</hi> ſin <hi>not,</hi> quarrel <hi>not</hi> away <hi>that which is</hi> my trueſt glory, <hi>that which is</hi> your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Priviledge. <hi>Study and mind the things which</hi> concern your peace: <hi>Make your peace with God by faith in his Son, and that faith accompanied with Repentance and Reformation; and</hi> be at peace among your ſelves; <hi>and then you need not fear your forreign foes: And I ſhould again become a</hi> Land of Renown; <hi>and be both</hi> feared <hi>and</hi> court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>all</hi> Europe <hi>over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. There is a Love which is <hi>Spiritual:</hi> The grounds and attractives of this are Spiritual. And this kind of love the Text ſpeaks of. Chriſtians Hearts ſhould be filled with it: And the more this is expreſſed, the more the Church muſt needs be edified. The Nature of this Love I ſhall explain in theſe Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love is a <hi>Grace wrought by the God of all grace,</hi> 1 John 4. 7. <hi>Let us love one another; for love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God.</hi> That Spirit which brings a man to the knowledge of God, and regenerates him, and makes him a New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, works in him this Grace of Love; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re we read. That the <hi>fruit of the Spirit is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Gal. 5. 22. Though Good Nature be an
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56801:42"/> cellent thing, and the diſpoſitions of many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them to be full of loving-kindneſs; yet this natural ſweetneſs of temper does greatly differ from Chriſtian Charity. The beſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is regardleſs of the Soul; neither is it concerned for it ſelf or others, beyond the things of ſenſe, and of this preſent World. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle thus deſcribes a ſtate of Nature, in which he ſometimes was as well as others, <hi>Tit. 3. 3. We our ſelves were ſometimes fooliſh, diſobedient, deceived, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures, living in malice and envy, hateful and hating one another.</hi> So that true love to others is of an Heavenly Original.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love is in <hi>Obedience to the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> Chriſtians love one another, becauſe their Lord and Saviour has commanded them, Joh. 15. 12. <hi>This is my Commandment, that ye love one another as I have loved you:</hi> Both Law and Goſpel inſiſt upon this. The Summ of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table of the Law, is this, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> And by the Goſpel this Law is eſtabliſhed. Faith in Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and Love are joyned. <hi>1 Joh. 3. 23. And this is his Commandment, that we ſhould believe on the Name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he gave us Commandment.</hi> Obedience to the Command ſanctifies our love to our Neighbour, and renders it not only more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to him, but acceptable to God himſelf. When we love others, that Gods will may be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56801:43"/> fulfilled, and he may be pleaſed, and becauſe of the Image of God and Chriſt which we ſee in them; then we love truly: And this is the meaning of that, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>By this we know that we love the Children of God, when we love God, and keep his Commandments.</hi> When love to God, and a care to keep his Laws, induce us to love his Children, becauſe he bids us, and for his ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love implies a <hi>Mortification of contrary Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi> The Poet ſayes, <hi>Virtus eſt vitium fugere.</hi> Vertue is, to fly from Vice: So may I ſay, Love is, to fly from Anger, Wrath, Malice, Bitterneſs, Envy, Revenge, which are ſins of ſuch a nature, that they carry their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their bowels, and <hi>make</hi> an <hi>Hell</hi> as well as <hi>deſerve</hi> one. The darkneſs of the night is chaſed away when the day returns, and the Sun riſes; ſickneſs is removed, when health is reſtored; and in like manner thoſe ſinful and corrupt paſſions, which benight the Soul, and are the diſeaſes of it, are purged out, where this Grace of Love is indeed infuſed. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle plainly ſhews this, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 31. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. 2. In the former place he ſayes, <hi>Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour be put away, with all kind of malice.</hi> In the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſayes, <hi>Walk in love, as Chriſt alſo hath loved us, and gave himſelf for us.</hi> Compare alſo <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 8. with <hi>v.</hi> 14. and you may perceive, that <hi>we muſt put off anger, wrath, malice,</hi> when we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56801:43"/> 
               <hi>put on charity, which is the bond of perfectneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Love implies an <hi>Inclination to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> The nature of it is to unite and knit things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thus by the love of <hi>Friendſhip, the Soul of</hi> Jonathan <hi>was knit with the Soul of</hi> David, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 1. and the Hearts of Chriſtians are <hi>knit together</hi> by this excellent Grace of <hi>Love,</hi> Col. 2. 2. Union is of God, and is indeed the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſtrength. The bundle of rods in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, while they remain'd bound together, could not be broken; whereas every ſingle one might be ſnapt aſunder with eaſe. So far as the Church is divided, ſo far 'tis certainly and dangerouſly weakned. There is an admirable Union in the Godhead: Three diſtinct Perſons are in one incomprehenſibly glorious Nature. A wonderful Union alſo in Chriſt himſelf; two diſtinct Natures in one Perſon and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator; and theſe two Natures infinitely more differing than Earth and Heaven, than the Sun and a Mole-hill; and yet behold them inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly united. The Churches Union is Myſtical; they are Many Members, but love makes them <hi>one Body;</hi> for it makes them of <hi>one heart,</hi> and of <hi>one Soul.</hi> Love alters the contentious and cruel nature, and inclines to Union and Peace. So that, to uſe the Prophets Phraſe, <hi>The Wolf dwells</hi> peaceably <hi>with the Lamb, the Leopard lyes down with the Kid; the Calf and the young Lion and the Fatling together; and a little Child may lead them: the Cow and the Bear feed, their young
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56801:44"/> ones lye down together; and the Lyon eats ſtraw like the Oxe: the ſucking Child plays on the hole of the Aſp; and the weaned Child puts his hand on the Adders den;</hi> ſo far as love prevails, <hi>there is no hurting nor deſtroying one another in all Gods holy Mountain,</hi> Iſa. 11. 6, 7, 8, 9. Chriſt prayed for this Union, as that which would be for the Churches benefit, and for the <hi>Worids Conviction,</hi> that he came forth from God. <hi>John</hi> 17. 21. <hi>That they all may be one, as thou Father art in Me; and I in Thee; that they alſo may be one in us, that the World may believe that thou haſt ſent me.</hi> How needful is Love to unite Chriſtians, and to make them one; ſince divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſtrike at Chriſt himſelf, and harden the World in its infidelity!</p>
            <p n="5">5. Love <hi>enlarges the Heart, and frees it from the bonds of ſelfiſhneſs; and makes its deſire others welfare as well as our own.</hi> Love to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour breaths forth in ſervent wiſhes, that it may be well with him both in Time, and to Eternity. We are in every reſpect to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Brethren; and true love will make us long that every way they may be benefited; that they may not want any needful fecular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and encouragement; eſpecially that they may be bleſſed with all Spiritual bleſſings: And above all that they may attain Eternal Happineſs and Salvation. The Apoſtles love vents it ſelf in a Prayer for the <hi>Corinthians</hi> temporal proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and increaſe. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 10. <hi>Now he that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtereth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56801:44"/> ſeed to the Sower, both Miniſter brend for your food and multiply your ſeed ſown, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the fruits of your Righteouſneſs.</hi> So St. <hi>John</hi> writing to his beloved <hi>Gaius,</hi> wiſhes him health and proſperity, 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. <hi>Beloved, I wiſh above all things that thou mayſt proſper and be in health, even as thy Soul proſpereth.</hi> But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles wiſhes that Souls might be ſanctified and ſaved, were moſt vehement, and moſt pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically expreſſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Brethren my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael, is that they might be ſaved.</hi> Phil. 1. 8. <hi>God is my record how greatly I long after you all in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Gal. 4. 19. <hi>My little Children of whom I travel in birth again until Chriſt be formed in you.</hi> Behold how the Apoſtle loved Souls! I don't wonder that he wiſhes his <hi>love</hi> as a bleſſing to the Church; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 24. <hi>My love be with you all in Chriſt Jeſus. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Love is the <hi>fulfilling of the Law,</hi> the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which is ſo much for our Neighbours benefit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>He that loveth another, hath fulfilled the Law.</hi> As love to God includes the whole firſt table of the Law, ſo love to our Neighbour includes the ſecond: with reaſon 'tis called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>fulfilling of the Law,</hi> for it cauſes an affectionate and obediential reſpect unto every Commandment of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table, and there is not one of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts but 'tis hugely for the good of Mankind.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love has a regard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the <hi>Honour and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56801:45"/> of Others.</hi> That honour which is due to Natural Parents, love is ready to yield. They that were inſtrumental in giving us our very Being, and that nouriſhed us with ſuch tenderneſs and care when we were not abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſhift for our ſelves, may rightfully challenge obedience from us. Upon a ſuppoſition that Parents are fallen into decay, that piety that Children ſhew them in relieving them is called a <hi>Requiting</hi> them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 4. ſo that Childrens diſobedience as 'tis unnatural, ſo it has a great deal of ingratitude in it.</p>
            <p>Love aſcends higher than our Natural Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and reaches the very Thrones where Kings and Princes are placed. Kings are <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae Patres,</hi> Fathers of their Countrey; all the inhabitants of a Kingdom are the Children of the King, and as a Common Father their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hearts ſhould love and reverence him. It was not a Court complement, or a ſtrain of Rhetorick, but an expreſſion of religious Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, when the Prophet call'd <hi>the Anointed of the Lord</hi> the <hi>breath</hi> of the peoples <hi>noſtrils,</hi> Lam. 4. 20. and ſignifies how dear his life ſhould be unto them all. Love will cauſe <hi>tribute and cuſtom</hi> to be willingly paid, <hi>fear and honour</hi> to be rendred, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 7.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Princes, according as it was prophetically promiſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> are <hi>Eccleſiae Nutritij,</hi> the Churches <hi>Nurſing Fathers.</hi> The
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56801:45"/> Church of Chriſt in this world is not arrived to ſuch <hi>mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uity,</hi> but it ſtands in need of <hi>nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;</hi> the Magiſtrates care is needful, and his Authority is a good fence unto the Chriſtian faith. And if the Doctrine of the Goſpel has a legal eſtabliſhment, how ſhould this endear the Supream Magiſtrate unto all inferiours. Where Chriſtian love reigns in the hearts of Subjects, there Chriſtian Kings will reign with greater ſecurity. <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>rightly informed Conſcience</hi> wherever found, will do more than <hi>Rods and Axes</hi> (though theſe are alſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) to ſupport and defend the Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love has a regard to the <hi>Lives of Others.</hi> The guilt of blood is great, the cry of blood is loud. Murther! how does it wound the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers Conſcience, and <hi>defile the very land</hi> which receives the blood of him that is mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered! Love utterly abhorrs cruelty and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It conſiders the meekneſs and gentleneſs of Chriſt. When <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> would by miraculous fire have conſumed a <hi>Samaritan</hi> vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage that would not receive their Lord, He rebukes them, and ſayes <hi>ye know not what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spirit ye are of; for the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave them,</hi> Luk. 9. 55, 56. Love is ſo far from thirſting after blood, that it will not allow of malice in the heart; nay raſh and <hi>cauſelefſ anger</hi> it diſlikes, for that will make <hi>a man in danger of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56801:46"/> the judgment,</hi> Mat. 5. 22. Were but love every where revived, it would put an end to the <hi>Iron</hi> one, and cauſe the <hi>Golden age</hi> to return, <hi>Swords</hi> would be beaten into <hi>Plough-ſhares,</hi> and <hi>Spears</hi> into <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning-Hooks,</hi> and <hi>Nations would not learn Warr any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Love will not <hi>violate others chaſtity.</hi> Luſt is ſtrongly inclined to ſuch a violation; but the grace of love is of an holy and clean na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and abhorrs all obſceneneſs. It is ſo far from conſenting to defile anothers body, that it will not allow the heart where 'tis, by a filthy thought or deſire to be defiled: for our Lord ſayes, <hi>Whoſoever looketh on a Woman to luſt after her, hath committed adultery with her already in his heart,</hi> Mat. 5. 28. Love looks upon the bodies of Chriſtians as <hi>Members of Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>temples of the Spirit;</hi> now the Members of Chriſt are not to be polluted, the temples of the Spirit are not to be profaned. How little of true love is there in this luſtful Age, in this adulterous generation! An affection that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Chriſtian, is rarely to be found; but a reprobate and brutiſh concupiſcence is very riſe both in City and Countrey, though hereby both are ripening apace for vengeance; <hi>Jer. 5. 7, 8, 9. They aſſembled themſelves by troops in the harlots houſes, they were as fed Horſes in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, every one neighed after his Neighbours Wife; Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord, and ſhall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a nature as this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:56801:46"/>4. Love will not <hi>ſteal away the ſubſtance of another.</hi> It abhors to be injurious to any; it is for following that which is <hi>altogether juſt.</hi> It is <hi>ready to distribute, willing to communicate</hi> to the poor; according to that <hi>charge,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 18. and the poorer any are, it is ſo much the more communicative. Love is liberal; <hi>for he that ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reap ſparingly, he which ſoweth bountifully ſhall reap bountifully,</hi> 2 Cor. 9. 6. But though it will give away pounds to them that are needy, it dares not unjuſtly take away a penny or a farthing from another though never ſo wealthy. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us that <hi>a falſe balance is not good, and divers weights are an abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 20. 23. and they are alſo an abomination unto Love. No duty more clearly diſcovered by the light of nature, than to <hi>do juſtly;</hi> and what does God in his written word more expreſly require? the <hi>unrighteous</hi> being plainly threaten'd with the <hi>loſs of the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> and what poor and petty things are their unjuſt gains compared with ſuch a Kingdom! Wronging another, though it be in ſo ſlie a manner, that humane eyes obſerve it not, humane laws cannot puniſh it; yet will be overtaken with divine Vengeance; 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>That no man go beyond and deſraud his brother in any matter; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord is the avenger of all ſuch, as we alſo have forewarned you and teſtified.</hi> Love to our Neighbour implies a Love of <hi>Juſtice,</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:56801:47"/> is to <hi>give our Neighbour his due.</hi> Love can as ſoon ceaſe to be Love, as begin to be Injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Nay, if a man has heretofore been guilty of Injuſtice, it will incline and conſtrain him to make reſtitution; for, <hi>The wicked muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Pledge, and give again what he hath robbed, and walk in the Statutes of Life; then he ſhall live, he ſhall not dye,</hi> Ezek. 33. 15.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Love is <hi>very tender of others Names and Reputation.</hi> It deteſts <hi>all manner</hi> of <hi>Lying,</hi> as that which is an <hi>abomination to God,</hi> Prov. 6. 17. and expoſes the <hi>Lyar himſelf to the burning lake:</hi> Rev. 21. 8. But a <hi>ſlanderous or malicious lye,</hi> that <hi>wounds the Name,</hi> and <hi>murthers the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> of another, it hates exceedingly; for this is an abomination moſt abominable, and more againſt the very letter of the Law, <hi>Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy Neighbour.</hi> The <hi>Name</hi> of a man ought to be very dear to him, eſpecially if he be a Chriſtian; becauſe God, and Chriſt, and the Goſpel are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it: A Chriſtian cannot be aſperſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome aſperſion on Chriſtianity it ſelf. Love is very wary, and that with great reaſon, and will not caſt into the <hi>precious Oyntment a dead Fly,</hi> to make it <hi>ſend forth an evil ſavour.</hi> Love hinders the Tongue from evil ſpeaking, and makes it ſubject to the Law of kindneſs. Love is ſo far from <hi>raiſing</hi> a falſe report of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it dares not <hi>take it up,</hi> much leſs <hi>ſpread it all abroad.</hi> The Citizen of <hi>Sion</hi> who
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:56801:47"/> ſhall dwell with God both here and for ever, this is part of his Character; <hi>He ſpeaketh the truth in his heart, he back-biteth not with his tongue, nor doth evil to his neighbour, nor taketh up a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach againſt his neighbour,</hi> Pſal. 15. 2, 3.</p>
            <p>Light may as well become darkneſs, as Love be guilty of Lying and malicious Defamations. Profeſſors ears are ready to tingle when they hear the ſound of helliſh Oaths, and horrid Execrations, wretched men making bold with <hi>the Life of God,</hi> the <hi>blood and wounds of Chriſt,</hi> and hardly a ſentence is pronounced without an Imprecation that <hi>God may damn them:</hi> But theſe Profeſſors would do well to conſider, that the <hi>ſame Mouth of Truth</hi> which has forbid and threatned <hi>Curſing and Swearing,</hi> has forbid and threatned <hi>Lying</hi> and <hi>Slandering;</hi> and if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how much injury may be done by a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous tongue, we ſhall not wonder that the throats of ſuch Slanderers are compared to <hi>open Sepulchers,</hi> and their Tongues to <hi>whetted Swords</hi> and <hi>ſharpned Arrows,</hi> and the <hi>Poyſon of Aſps is ſaid to be under them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Love is <hi>contented with its own, and hinders us from coveting what belongs to another.</hi> Sinful luſtings and deſires after that which is our neighbours, precipitate unto thoſe acts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is injured; thus <hi>Ahabs</hi> inordinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after <hi>Naboths Vineyard,</hi> makes him a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of <hi>Naboth,</hi> and that with many aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, that he might enjoy it. Love breeds
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:56801:48"/> contentation, and inſtead of coveting what is anothers, it wiſhes him both a quiet poſſeſſion, and an holy improvement; and Love expell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe inordinate luſtings, it plucks up the very root of bitterneſs from whence do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly grow all thoſe injuries that the Sons of men do one to another. Thus Love is Eagle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyed to obſerve whatever God in his Law has commanded for our neighbours good, and ſince the wiſe and gracious Law-giver has mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his care of our neighbour, in fencing his Life and all that is dear to him with ſo many Commandments, Love rationally inferrs, it ought to be our care not to break this fence, but to keep all theſe Commandments without exception.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Love <hi>breeds ſympathy when our fellow Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are in miſery:</hi> It makes us fear leaſt harm befall the Church of God, and when the Church is actually under Affliction, it cauſes us in that affliction to be afflicted. Love is the great Law of Chriſt, and Chiſtian Sympathy is a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling it, <hi>Gal. 6. 2. Bear ye one anothers burthens, and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt.</hi> The Captive <hi>Jews</hi> their Harps were out of Tune, and their Hearts had little liſt to Mirth and Muſick; nay, <hi>By the rivers of Babylon they wept when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred Sion,</hi> Pſal. 137. 1, 2. Love eaſily melts the heart of a Saint into ſorrow, when other Saints are in ſadneſs and calamity; nay, 'tis re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy to put on bowels when it ſees any in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:56801:48"/> miſery. This Sympathy of Love is a real thing, and ſhews it ſelf in a forwardneſs to relieve and help. Love enlarges the Heart in Prayer for the diſtreſſed Church of Chriſt, and all his Members; it makes us in the Churches languors ready to faint and dye away our ſelves; Love draws forth our Compaſſion towards the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and diſtreſſed Land of our Nativity: and in ſome it ariſes to ſo high a degree, that they are ready (ſuch are their holy Agonies) to wiſh <hi>Their Names blotted out of the Book of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife,</hi> and themſelves <hi>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſed from Chriſt,</hi> rather than <hi>England ſhould become deſolate,</hi> rather than <hi>God ſhould depart,</hi> and the <hi>glorious Goſpel</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt be <hi>removed!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Love makes us <hi>to delight in the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints.</hi> Sin has brought a great defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and unlovelineſs upon Mankind; the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks thus of Men, conſidered in their natural State, <hi>They are all gone aſide, they are altogether become filthy, there is none that doth good, no not one,</hi> Pſal. 14. 3. But the Grace of God lias made a difference between the Saints and other men, they have <hi>put off the old man which is corrupt according to deceitful luſts, and they put on the new man which after God is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs,</hi> Eph. 4. 22. 24. Now this Holineſs makes them truly amiable. Love makes us <hi>pity</hi> the World that lies in wickedneſs, but to <hi>delight</hi> in thoſe who by Regeneration are called out of the World,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:56801:49"/> and made New Creatures. <hi>David,</hi> though a King, lookt upon Saints as <hi>the excellent ones,</hi> and <hi>his delight</hi> was <hi>all</hi> in them, as the moſt eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible and ſuitable Society, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 3. Love is exceedingly pleaſed with the holy and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and exemplary Lives of others, it finds a Melody and Sweetneſs in their gracious and edifying Diſcourſes, when their Hearts are warm, and their Graces are in vigorous exerciſe; the delight is greateſt when Saints are moſt like themſelves, diſcovering moſt of real Sanctity, and leaſt of ſinful Infirmity. Love is for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with all Saints, though of different perſwaſions: He that likes Saints of his <hi>own</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>onely,</hi> 'tis a ſign he is <hi>fond</hi> of his <hi>own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> and that his Complacency is not <hi>ſo tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Image of God,</hi> wherever it ſhines. 'Tis want of light that makes Saints of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſentiments in Religion, and 'tis want of Love that makes them ſo ſhye, to look ſo ſtrangely, to ſpeak ſo ſtrangely, and to act ſo ſtrangely one towards another.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Love cauſes <hi>a joy in the good of others.</hi> In the natural Body <hi>if one Member be honoured, all the Members rejoyce with it,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 26. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in like manner are <hi>to rejoyce with them that do rejoyce,</hi> Rom. 12. 15. It was an excellent Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and it argued the Truth of his Love to the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> of whom he was the forerunner, that he rejoyced to ſee <hi>Chriſt increaſe,</hi> though <hi>he himſelf decreaſed,</hi> Joh. 3. 29, 30.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:56801:49"/> The Apoſtle was perſwaded of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> affection to him, when he ſaid, <hi>I have confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in you all, that my joy is the joy of you all,</hi> 2 Cor. 2. 3. The more Love abounds, the more the joy of <hi>one</hi> Chriſtian will be the joy of <hi>every one.</hi> Love rejoyces to ſee the Spirit of God poured out in the moſt plentiful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to ſee uſeful and excellent gifts diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to others. It is really glad of their high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt attainments, their enlargements, their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, their honour and eſteem following up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all this. We are all Members one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and why ſhould we not rejoyce in one anothers honour, ſince we are really honoured one in another; and the honour of all redounds at length to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Head of all?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Love <hi>covers a multitude of ſins and Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 8. Not that there is any merit in this Grace of Charity, to deſerve the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin in our ſelves; but inſtead of ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faults of others, it ſpreads a veil over them. Love makes us tender-hearted and kind, ready to forgive others, as we our ſelves for Chriſts ſake have been forgiven. And indeed the offences and injuries done to us by others are but like the debt of a <hi>few pence,</hi> compared with our offences againſt God, which amount to many <hi>Millions of Talents.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> asked Chriſt, <hi>Lord, how often ſhall my Brother ſin againſt me, and I forgive him? till ſeven times?
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:56801:50"/> Jeſus ſaith unto him, I ſay unto thee, not till ſeven times, but untill ſeventy times ſeven,</hi> Mat. 18. 21, 22. Some think that there is alluſion to the cuſtom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to ſhew favour every ſeventh year, but eſpecially in the year of <hi>Jubilee.</hi> As there is a greater meaſure of <hi>light</hi> in the Chriſtian Church than there was in the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> ſo ought there to be a greater meaſure of <hi>love.</hi> We muſt not only forgive to ſeven times, or ſeven times ſeven, but <hi>ſeventy times ſeven;</hi> a certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umber for an uncertain; intimatin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we muſt pardon our treſpaſſing Brother without any ſtint or limitation. Our Lord calls the time of the Goſpel <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>acceptable year,</hi> Luk. 4. 19. Chriſtians ſhould abhorr all manner of revenge, and be as charitably inclined to paſs by their Brethrens faults, as if their life were a perpetual <hi>Jubilee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where is the love of thoſe, who not only harbour in their hearts a grudge againſt their Brethren, but their mouths are like Trumpets to ſound forth their failings. Nay, they tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not to examine whether failings or no; but boldly and blindly conclude them to be ſuch, and proclaim and exclaim againſt them: Nay, their eager tongues tarry not for a certain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; but whether reports to the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of others be true or falſe, they make them run like wild-fire. What's become of Love the mean while? Love hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es a <hi>multitude</hi> of ſins, but theſe perſons won't conceal <hi>one:</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:56801:50"/> Love covers real Crimes, but theſe forbear not ſpreading falſe reports. The Tongue by <hi>Drex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elius</hi> is called <hi>Orbis Phaethon,</hi> the <hi>Phaethon</hi> of the World, that ſets it in a flame. If as the Apoſtle ſayes, an <hi>unruly tongue defiles the whole body,</hi> and <hi>he that ſeems religious, and bridles not his tongue, does but deceive his own heart, and his Religion is in vain,</hi> Jam. 1. 26. Let a multitude of Profeſſors at this day, tremble, and be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and cry out, <hi>Who among us ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Love is <hi>projecting and deſigning the good of others.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle <hi>abaſed himſelf that others might be exalted;</hi> and ſought not <hi>his own profit, but the profit of many, that they might be ſaved,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 33. Love <hi>worketh no ill to his neighbour;</hi> but is very fruitful in contriving, and operative in promoting his Neighbours welfare. Love is not in not in <hi>word and in tongue only, but in deed and in truth,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 18. It will not only ſay, <hi>depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled,</hi> but 'tis ready to cloath the naked, and to feed the hungry: nay, it deviſeth <hi>liberal</hi> and charitable things; and conſiders the wants of Souls as well as Bodies, cordially, according to its capacity; endeavouring that both may be ſupplyed. The Apoſtles love to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> was very active, notwithſtanding a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful failing on their ſide. 2 <hi>Cor. 12. 14, 15. I ſeek not yours, but you; and I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you;</hi> (in the Greek 'tis
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:56801:51"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for your ſouls) <hi>though the more abundantly I love you, the leſs I be loved.</hi> Thus have I explained the <hi>Nature of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Second place I am to ſpeak of the <hi>Properties</hi> which the Scripture attributes to it, and requires ſhould be in <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Love muſt proceed from a <hi>pure heart,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 5. A heart muſt of neceſſity be made a new one, before this Grace of Love can dwell there. If Satan cannot make us <hi>hate</hi> our Brother, he will endeavour to <hi>defile</hi> our Love. There is need of the greater care, that our Love be not defiled by ſelfiſhneſs, or luſt and filthineſs. Our affections ſhould be pure and clean; as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels may be conceived to love one another. All impure motions muſt be deteſted utterly; and our hearts being firſt circumciſed to love a God of Holineſs, muſt love Saints for their holineſs ſake. Our love ſhould alwayes have an holy aim, and never degenerate, ſo as to deſign the polluting of others, or our ſelves with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love muſt be joyn'd with a <hi>good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 5. A Chriſtian ſhould not be conſcious to himſelf of any ſinful or by-ends that he has in his love to others. He muſt not have perſons in admiration becauſe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; nor allow of any Hypocriſy, which Conſcience cannot chuſe, if tender, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn. Therefore ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>Let love
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:56801:51"/> be without diſſimulation,</hi> Rom. 12. 9. Conſcience obſerves whether our inward affection anſwers our ſpeeches, our ſhews, and our pretences; and ſhould be able to bear witneſs of our integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Our love to our neighbours ſhould be for <hi>Chriſts ſake,</hi> and ſhould make us to purſue the ends for which Chriſt died on their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love muſt flow from <hi>faith unfeigned.</hi> In that fore-cited place, 1 <hi>Tim. 1. 5. Now the end of the Commandment is Charity out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience, and of faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned.</hi> There muſt be a firm belief of Gods <hi>good-will towards men,</hi> of Chriſts <hi>love to his Church,</hi> ſo as to give <hi>himſelf</hi> for its Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Salvation, and that he much inſiſts upon this <hi>Command,</hi> that Chriſtians ſhould <hi>love one another;</hi> and when love is the product of this belief, then 'tis right, then 'tis accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Apoſtle <hi>gave thanks without ceaſing</hi> in the behalf of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> when <hi>he heard of their faith in the Lord Jeſus, and love to all the Saints,</hi> Eph. 1. 15, 16. How can he refuſe to love any one <hi>Saint,</hi> who unfeignedly believes that Chriſt died for <hi>all;</hi> eſpecially if withall he be upon good grounds perſwaded, that Chriſt <hi>loved him, und gave himſelf for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Love <hi>muſt be fervent,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 22. <hi>Seeing ye have purified your Souls in obeying the truth through the Spirit, unto the unfeigned love of the Brethren, ſee that ye love one another with a pure
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:56801:52"/> heart fervently.</hi> 'Tis ill with the Body if the <hi>natural heat</hi> abates; it argues a dangerous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in the new Creature, if <hi>Love wax cold.</hi> If Chriſtians Love one towards another lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, proportionably there will be alſo a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing of their <hi>love to Chriſt himſelf;</hi> and this is very perillous. When there was not a <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency,</hi> but <hi>lukewarmneſs</hi> in <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Chriſt threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens <hi>to ſpue her out of his mouth,</hi> Rev. 3. 16. When <hi>Epheſus</hi> had <hi>left her firſt love,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>I will come unto thee quickly, and remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent,</hi> Rev. 2. 4, 5. The great love of God in Chriſt, his frequent injunctions that love may continue, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, ſweetneſs, uſefulneſs, and even abſolute neceſſity of love for the Churches conſervation; all this ſhould be as <hi>perpetual fewel</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this <hi>holy fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſtians Love muſt be <hi>Brotherly:</hi> Chriſt ſayes to his Diſciples, <hi>All ye are Brethren,</hi> Mat. 23. 8. The whole Body of Believers is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Brotherhood,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 17. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are all Children of the ſame heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who by one Spirit, according <hi>to his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercy has begotten them again to a lively hope;</hi> all of them have Chriſt to be their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother, and are born again of the <hi>ſame ſeed which is incorruptible;</hi> how reaſonable then are thoſe injunctions, <hi>Love as Brethren,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 8. And let <hi>Brotherly love continue,</hi> Heb. 13. 1. Alas for woe! that the ſinful Defects and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:56801:52"/> of Brethren are to be found among Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, but not the Affection. Multitudes at this day reſemble the Brother, ſpoken of by <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 18. 19. <hi>A Brother offended is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to be won than a ſtrong City, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are like the bars of a Caſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Love ſhould be <hi>extended ſo as to become Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick;</hi> and the more extenſive 'tis, the more it makes a Man reſemble God himſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love is to be extended to <hi>the whole Church,</hi> to <hi>all Saints.</hi> When Love is limited to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 'tis Impriſoned as it were, which ought to enjoy the greateſt Liberty. 'Tis common and needful to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Converſion to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Converſion to God:</hi> There is a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on likewiſe to be made between <hi>Love to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Love to the Church of God.</hi> 'Tis but too apparent that men place too much in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch a party and Perſwaſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all <hi>Receeding,</hi> though done with a clear Conſcience, and for the Churches Peace, is nick-named <hi>Apoſtacy:</hi> And though a man walks as cloſely with God, lives as well as ever, loves more Saints, and Saints more than ever, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not <hi>rigidly of ſuch a way,</hi> he is cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, belyed, reproacht and ſhunn'd, as if he were an <hi>Heathen man or Publican.</hi> Oh Love! why ſleepeſt thou? awake, awake! wherever thou art planted, revive and flouriſh, and bring forth the fruits of kindneſs, peaceableneſs, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and moderation! All true Saints of all
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:56801:53"/> Perſwaſions, are beloved of God, and purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his blood, and nothing ſhall be able to <hi>ſeparate them from the Love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus their Lord,</hi> Rom. 8. <hi>ult.</hi> Diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therefore and diſtances one from another, are very unſeemly, very ſinful. Though God does love all his Children <hi>freely,</hi> yet they are all <hi>worthy</hi> of one anothers love, and this love is a <hi>juſt Debt</hi> which they <hi>owe</hi> one to another. If Saints are loved as Saints, all Saints will be loved, <hi>à quatenùs ad omne valet conſequentia:</hi> And if we love not <hi>all,</hi> 'tis but too plain that we love <hi>none at all</hi> truly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love is to be extended to the <hi>Jews,</hi> if they are <hi>beloved for their Fathers ſakes,</hi> Rom. 11. 28. Chriſtians ſhould love them, and expreſs that love by Prayer, that they may not ſtill abide in their Unbelief, but look unto Jeſus whom they have pierced, and obtain Mercy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love is to reach unto the <hi>uncalled Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> The worlds blindneſs and wickedneſs ſhould move our Compaſſion; and ſince the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of our God is ſo unconceivably large, we ſhould deſire that more may partake of it, and ſince Chriſt is <hi>a Propitiation</hi> ſufficient <hi>for the ſins of the whole World,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 22. We ſhould pity the millions of Souls that never heard of him, and beg that the ſound of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel may come to their ears, and that through this Jeſus they may be reconciled and ſaved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Love is to be extended even <hi>to enemies and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56801:53"/> Perſecutors.</hi> Chriſtians muſt not <hi>render evil for evil,</hi> reproach for reproach, curſing for curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but if they are <hi>reviled,</hi> they are to <hi>bleſs,</hi> if they are <hi>defamed,</hi> they are to <hi>intreat;</hi> and they muſt endeavour the Worlds benefit, though they are made <hi>the filth of the World, and the off-ſcouring of all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 12, 13. A Saints Patience ſhould alwayes be greater than the Paſſion of a Perſecutor, a Saints love than a Perſecutors hatred. 'Tis an excellent Spirit, and the right Spirit of Chriſtian charity, to be meek and kind to thoſe that are moſt bitter againſt us; to ſpeak the beſt of thoſe, who ſpeak the worſt of us; to Pray that our moſt ſpightful Enemies may be forgiven; and that the injuries which are done us, being Pardon'd, may not do an eternal harm unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers.</p>
            <p>7. Love ſhould <hi>never fail, but more and more increaſe.</hi> It muſt be a conſtant fire never to be extinguiſhed, nay, it ſhould become ſtronger and purer continually, <hi>Phil. 1. 9. And this I pray, that your love may abound yet more and more in Knowledge and in all Judgment.</hi> The true reaſons of Love muſt be better and better underſtood, and the expreſſions of Love muſt be ſtill with more and more judgment and diſcretion, that the end aimed at may be attained. After the Apoſtle had acknowledged the <hi>Theſſalonians taught of God to love one another;</hi> yet adds, <hi>We beſeech you Brethren, that you increaſe more and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:56801:54"/> more,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4. 9. 10. And if where Love did ſo much abound, there was reaſon to preſs an increaſe, Oh, how much need is there in ſuch an angry and contentious Age as this, to blow up this fire which is ſo near to going out: I have done with the <hi>Properties</hi> of Love.</p>
            <p>In the third place I am to demonſtrate how <hi>Love is for the Churches Edification.</hi> 'Tis for the Edification of <hi>Him</hi> that loves, and for the Edification of <hi>thoſe</hi> whom he loves. A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Edifies both <hi>himſelf</hi> and <hi>others</hi> by Love. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall demonſtrate that he Edifies <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The more he Loves, there is the <hi>greater light</hi> in him. The underſtanding is darken'd by thoſe ſins which are contrary to Love, as Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, Paſſion, Envy, Hatred, ſo that what is Truth, is not eaſily diſcerned; what is Duty, is not readily apprehended in many caſes. The fore-mention'd evil Affections do biaſs the Judgment wrong. Though the eye be good, and the object not far off; yet the eye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo plainly ſee the object, if there be a miſt between them: Anger and Malice raiſe ſuch a miſt before the eye of the Judgment, that 'tis very prone to be miſtaken; but this <hi>miſt</hi> is <hi>ſcattered</hi> by <hi>Love,</hi> ſo that a Chriſtian ſees his way plain, and is leſs ſubject to <hi>ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 9, 10, 11. <hi>He that ſaith he is in the light, and hateth his Brother, is in darkneſs even until now: He that loveth his Brother abideth
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:56801:54"/> in the light, and there is none occaſion of ſtumbling in him; but he that hateth his Brother, is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and walketh in darkneſs, and knoweth not whither he goeth, becauſe that darkneſs hath blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The more a Chriſtian Loves, there is the <hi>more of Gods Image in him;</hi> he is the more tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the Divine Nature, 1 <hi>Joh. 4. 7, 8. God is Love, and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God.</hi> In Scripture God is ſaid to <hi>delight in Merccy,</hi> to <hi>reſt in his love,</hi> to be <hi>good to all,</hi> to be <hi>kind to the unthankful and evil.</hi> How does Love Edifie a Child of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him reſemble his Heavenly Father in theſe excellent perfections; and how <hi>unlike to Satan</hi> does love make us! Have we Knowledge? how great an underſtanding has the evil one! have we Faith? <hi>The Devils alſo believe and tremble;</hi> but if we have <hi>Love,</hi> Satan has <hi>nothing</hi> of this in him, he hates and tortures his own ſelf, he hates Gods Children, and all his own Children; he <hi>would</hi> deſtroy the former, he <hi>will,</hi> unleſs they ceaſe to be his Children, deſtroy the latter.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The more a Chriſtian loves, he <hi>has the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er evidence that he is indeed a Chriſtian.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us, that the <hi>fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace.</hi> The more love, the more peace and joy, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22. We read <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1, 2. of <hi>Conſolation in Chriſt and Comfort in love.</hi> Love builds us up in ſolid Comfort; for we have the mark of Chriſts Sheep upon us, if we love
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:56801:55"/> the whole flock. That <hi>Religion</hi> has not <hi>truth</hi> that has not <hi>love</hi> in it: pretences to light and purity, without love, are all vain. But he that is full of love, in this world; ſhall not be ſent to Hell in the other World, where there is no love at all, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall demonſtrate that Chriſtians edifie not only themſelves but <hi>others</hi> by their love, and that 'tis exceedingly for the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Edification.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love makes us <hi>concerned for the whole Church of Chriſt, and enlarged in our ſupplications and interceſſions for it.</hi> This publick Spirit which is the effect of Catholick love, is very pleaſing unto God, and mightily prevails with him. God encourages us to an importunity for <hi>Zion.</hi> He does not ſay as he did to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Let me alone</hi> that I may deſtroy: but <hi>give me no reſt</hi> until I ſave, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62. 6, 7. <hi>I have ſet watchmen upon thy Walls, O Jeruſalem, which ſhall never hold their peace day nor night: ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence, and give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh, and make Jeruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi> Love takes this encouragement, and makes the Chriſtian thus to reſolve: <hi>For Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſake I will not hold my peace, and for Jeruſalems ſake I will not reſt, until the Righteouſneſs thereof goes forth as brightneſs, and the Salvation thereof as
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:56801:55"/> a lamp that burneth.</hi> The Churches Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Righteouſneſs is to be prayed for, as well as it's Deliverance and Salvation. The Apoſtle tells us, if we will pray to purpoſe, we muſt <hi>lift up holy hands without wrath and doubting,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 8. Wrath defiles him that prayes, and <hi>fills the cenſer with ſtrange fire,</hi> mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſinful fervency and heat with prayer; and ſo hinders its prevalency and acceptation. But Love empties the heart of wrath, and fills it with an holy fervour; and how much does <hi>the effectual fervent prayer</hi> of a righteous man prevail! <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 16. One <hi>Moſes</hi> full of love to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for Gods Honour, deſirous of <hi>Iſraels</hi> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; he ſtands in the gap, and by prayer turns away that Wrath that was breaking in and ready to deſtroy all the people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. 23. <hi>Therefore he ſaid that he would deſtroy them, had not Moſes his choſen ſtood in the breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, to turn away his wrath leſt he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Love <hi>ſtrongly inclines us unto peaceableneſs,</hi> and what is for the Churches peace is for her edification, <hi>Rom. 14. 19. Let us follow after the things that make for peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another.</hi> I grant when we are purſuing peace, we muſt have a ſpecial regard to <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>holineſs,</hi> Zach. 8. 19. <hi>Love the truth and peace,</hi> Heb. 12. 14. <hi>Follow after Peace with all Men, and Holineſs.</hi> But the Scripture
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:56801:56"/> muſt determine what is Truth, and we muſt diſtinguiſh between the great Truths of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and thoſe that are leſs important. It was a truth which the Apoſtle was <hi>perſwaded of by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that there was <hi>no meat unclean of it ſelf;</hi> and yet thoſe who were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perſwaded, he look'd upon as tolerable, and not to be <hi>deſpiſed:</hi> Nay, he expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids thoſe of different Sentiments in this matter to <hi>judge one another,</hi> Rom. 14. The Scripture likewiſe muſt inform us wherein purity and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs lies; for a miſtake here may quickly draw forth ſuch a furious zeal, as may ſet the Church in a flame. <hi>Some</hi> place Purity and all Religion in being <hi>for the Liturgy eſtabliſhed,</hi> as if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers of it had been <hi>tantum non</hi> divinely inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and all other Prayer were but meer En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm and contemptible babbling. On the other hand, ſome place purity and all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in declaiming againſt the Liturgy, as <hi>Maſs-engliſh,</hi> the <hi>mark of the Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry voice of the Whore of</hi> Babylon. But neither the one nor the other place purity and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion right. The Scripture no where commands that we ſhould only pray by a form, neither does it forbid a form to be uſed. But it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that our very Hearts and Souls ſhould be in our prayers, and faith and holy deſires and other graces exerciſed in our duties; and <hi>here</hi> lies the <hi>purity</hi> of them. Love therefore refuſes to be <hi>quarrelſome</hi> about ſmaller matters:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:56801:56"/> for it knows that peaceableneſs cements the Church, and cloſes her breaches; and it juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fears leſt while men are ſo <hi>contentious</hi> about <hi>ceremonies,</hi> the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of Religion be loſt in the quarrel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love makes Chriſtians <hi>condeſcending and yielding one to another,</hi> that hereby edification may be promoted. To be Magiſterial and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willed is not to be the Servants of Chriſt, who are employed in building of his Church. We are not to be <hi>Dictators;</hi> but all alike to hearken to the voice and command of Chriſt our Lord, and to be mild and gentle one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> charges <hi>the Younger to ſubmit themſelves to the Elder,</hi> but withal adds, <hi>yea all of you be ſubject one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 5. and hereby intimates, that to be Lordly and impoſing is contrary to the Spirit of Chriſtianity. It was love that made the Apoſtle <hi>Paul a Servant to all, that he might gain the more,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 19. <hi>To the Jewes he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as a Jew, that he might gain the Jewes, to the weak he became as weak that he might gain the weak:</hi> he did not hereby manifeſt a carnal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance through fear, but a condeſcenſion of love. He was not to be charged with <hi>Levity</hi> or <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy,</hi> he was not to be cenſured as a <hi>Turn-coat,</hi> as an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> as a <hi>Mungrel minister;</hi> or a <hi>Linſey Wolſey Brother,</hi> nor to be called <hi>Dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baked; a Cake not turned.</hi> No, no, the Apoſtle loved the Goſpel, and had a mind to ſpread
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:56801:57"/> it, he loved Souls and was deſirous to ſave them, and underſtood how far he might yield in indifferent things for the Churches peace and edification. Love makes us patient and ſelf-denying, hinders us from purſuing petty deſigns, or private revenges; The pleaſing of God and profiting his Church, ſwallow up ſuch things as theſe. Love will hinder us from <hi>minding high things,</hi> and move us <hi>to condeſcend to men of low estate,</hi> Rom. 12. 16. Indeed to apply our ſelves to all the beſt and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ways for their benefit; we ſhall endeavour to <hi>help the weak,</hi> we ſhall <hi>pity the fallen,</hi> we ſhall labour to <hi>reduce the straying,</hi> we ſhall <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the diligent,</hi> and <hi>honour the ſtronger Saints,</hi> and all this is hugely for Edification.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Love makes Chriſtians <hi>highly to eſteem the Paſtours and Builders of the Church for their works ſake,</hi> and hereby Edification is promoted. The Miniſtry of the Goſpel is a ſpecial gift which Chriſt beſtowed upon his Church, for her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable advantage; <hi>Eph. 4. 8, 11, 12, 13. Wherefore he ſaith, when he aſcended up on high he led captivity captive and gave gifts unto men. And he gave ſome Prophets, and ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtours and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt; till we all come in the unity of the Faith and of the Knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man.</hi> And ſince the Miniſtry is ſuch a gift and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:56801:57"/> token of the Royal bounty of Chriſt who is aſcended far above all Heavens, certainly the flock of Chriſt are to love and encourage their Paſtours; and the more they do this, the more likely 'tis, that the end of the Miniſtry's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſhould be attained, namely the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and perfecting of the Church of Chriſt. The Apoſtle, though he might have command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yet uſes intreaties for Miniſters ſake, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 12, 13. He had bid them juſt before, <hi>v.</hi> 11. to <hi>edifie one another,</hi> but knowing the work of Edification would go on but lamely without a Goſpel-miniſtry, he therefore adds; <hi>And we beſeech you Brethren to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh you, and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at peace among your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Love will conſtrain <hi>the Paſtours and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church to mind their work to purpoſe.</hi> A Miniſter that is full of love to Chriſt and Souls, cannot be a Loyterer. If indeed he does deſign preferment, and to fill his baggs with wealth be his great aim, then he will grudge Souls his pains: He will not be concerned though Hell fill never ſo faſt, and though him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be going apace thither. But if holy love to the Church of Chriſt does rule in his heart, it will conſtrain him to be a Labourer, and to do his work diligently; he will watch and pray, he will ſearch and ſtudy, and abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:56801:58"/> all books the Bible: He will take heed to himſelf, and to all his flock, that he may ſave himſelf and them that hear him. Nay love will make a Miniſter labour, and <hi>ſuffer</hi> alſo for the Churches Edification. Abundant love to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> made the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you,</hi> 2 Cor. 12, 15. And 'tis very plain that he did not think much of ſuffering, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Yea, and if I be offered upon the Sacrifice and Service of your faith, I joy and rejoyce with you all.</hi> Theſe reaſons plainly demonſtrate how much Love tends to edifie.</p>
            <p>But a great many reaſons more I find <hi>all together;</hi> even a whole cluſter of them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4, 5, 6, 7. which I ſhall enlarge upon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are both a trial of our love, and a demonſtration moſt evident that love is for Edification. The Apoſtles words are very ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, very piercing; he reads a kind of Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my-Lecture upon this grace of Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and lays the inſide of it open to the view of others: He ſeems to ſpeak a ſtrange word, <hi>Though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing,</hi> v. 3. What is Charity and Love, may ſome ſay, if feeding the poor be not? Theſe outward acts a Phariſee may do meerly out of oftentation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. a Papiſt may do, ignorantly hoping hereby to ſatisfy for his ſins, and merit Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:56801:58"/> I grant that love without theſe outward acts of mercy, is vain and uſeleſs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Love in <hi>deed,</hi> is love in <hi>truth,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 18. But though love produce ſuch deeds, many outward acts of mercy may be where love is not. The Apoſtle in a great many particulars diſcovers true love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and I ſhall make it evident how in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular 'tis much for edification.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Love <hi>ſuffers long, and is kind.</hi> God is long ſuffering, and ſo is Love: It enables us to rule our own ſpirits, which argues true greatneſs and ſtrength of Soul. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 32. <hi>He that is ſlow to anger, is better than the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and he that ruleth his ſpirit, than he that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a City.</hi> Love is ſo far from revenging injuries already done, that it will bear new ones: and that's the meaning of our Lords Injunction, <hi>Mat. 5. 39. I ſay unto you, that ye reſiſt not evil, but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn to him the other alſo.</hi> Nay, Love though it ſuffers long, is <hi>kind</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. 'Tis much to put up an injury, but much more to be kind to the Injurer. This love in Churches, how would it unite them? and the more they are united, the more they are ſtrengthened. <hi>Provocations to wrath</hi> would be turned into <hi>provocations to love;</hi> and evil would be overcome by goodneſs; and the World hereby is likely to be convinced and converted. The Proto-Martyr <hi>Stephen</hi> was kind
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56801:59"/> to thoſe that ſtoned him: How does he pray that their <hi>ſin might not be laid to their charge,</hi> but that their Souls might be ſaved, though they thirſted after his blood, and took away his life from him! This Prayer was heard, and <hi>Saul</hi> at length is converted, and proves a <hi>Maſter-builder</hi> of the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Love <hi>envies not:</hi> It is not grieved and troubled at anothers excellency; neither does it grudge at the comfort or proſperity of another. How much of <hi>Hell</hi> is there in the temper of an envious man! The happineſs of another is <hi>his</hi> miſery, the good of another is his affliction: He looks upon the vertue of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother with an evil eye, and is as ſorry at the praiſe of another, as if that praiſe were taken away from himſelf. Envy makes him an hater of his Neighbour, and his own Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter. Love flies from Envy as extreamly diabolical; for the root of it is pride, and ill will is its Concomitant. What ſad work has Envy made in <hi>Churches!</hi> (not to ſpeak of the miſchief it has done all the World over.) When Chriſtians have been deſirous of <hi>vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, provoking one another, envying one another,</hi> which the Apoſtle ſo much dehorts from, <hi>Gal. 5. ult.</hi> When Paſtors have been envious at one anothers Parts, Gifts, Preferments, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Eſtimation, the poor Church has ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and its Edification has gone on like <hi>Pauls work,</hi> but very ſlowly. Envy makes the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56801:59"/> to fall out, to weaken one anothers hands; to hinder one another in the work of God. <hi>Where envying and ſtrife is,</hi> is there Edification? No ſuch matter, but there is <hi>confuſion, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evil work,</hi> Jam. 3. 16. Love inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing troubled at the grace, or uſefulneſs, or eſteem of another, rejoyces therein; and the more there are that honour God, and adorn the Goſpel, and benefit the Church, it rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the more.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love <hi>vaunteth not it ſelf, neither is it puffed up.</hi> The word which the Holy Ghoſt uſes for vaunting, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Greek word of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine derivation, coming from <hi>perperan,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>amiſs.</hi> An ancient Greek Father, St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> propounds this queſtion, What is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? and returns this anſwer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Love is againſt doing things for <hi>ſhew</hi> and <hi>oſtentation,</hi> and excludes vain-glorious boaſting. <hi>Puffing up</hi> relates to the <hi>Heart, vaunting</hi> to the <hi>words and actions:</hi> Love refuſes to do either. It makes a man not <hi>to think more highly of himſelf than he ought to think, but to think ſoberly,</hi> Rom. 12. 3. thoſe Precepts are much minded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>Be kindly affectioned one to another, with brotherly love, in honour preferring one another.</hi> and <hi>Phil. 2. 3. Let each eſteem other better than themſelves.</hi> And as Love hinders the heart from being puff'd up, ſo the tongue from vaunting it ſelf, or debaſing another: It will not defame or diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:56801:60"/> others, as if its own reputation were to be built upon the ruine of theirs. Now this kind of temper is very ſubſervient to the Churches intereſt. For while Chriſtians are thus low in their own eyes, and are ready both in word and deed to honour and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage one another, great grace, a ſhining luſtre is upon them all; and God himſelf delights in them to make them flouriſh and encreaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Love <hi>does not behave it ſelf unſeemly.</hi> What more unſeemly than a lofty look, than an haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty carriage! as if others were not good enough to unlooſe the latchet of our ſhoes? but Love does baniſh pride and ſcornfulneſs, and makes us humble in our converſe, which is the moſt ſeemly behaviour in the world. The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifies any unſeemly behaviour. So that Love ſtudies exactneſs of carriage, that Religion may be the more commended unto all. When Profeſſors do that which is unſeemly, the Church and Religion ſuffer by it; but a converſation without rebuke, which manifeſts a love both to God and Man, is the way to win many a man to God, that before was eſtranged from him. An un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly behaviour opens many a mouth againſt the Goſpel, creates new prejudices, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the World in their natural enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: But a ſeemly converſation makes Religion amiable; well-doing puts ill tongues to ſilence, and forces them to give glory to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:56801:60"/> God. 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 12. Having your converſation ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt among the Gentiles, that whereas they ſpeak againſt you as evil doers, they may by your good works which they ſhall behold, glorify God in the day of viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Love <hi>ſeeketh not her own,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclines us to edify and to ſeek the good of others. The Apoſtles meaning is not, that Love cauſes us to caſt off all care and regard of our ſelves, but only that which is immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and which proceeding from a blind ſelf-love, makes us diſregard what becomes of others. Chriſt himſelf is a pattern to Love in this reſpect, and Love follows him: He was humbled, that we might be exalted; He was condemned, that we might be juſtified; He became poor, that we through his pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty might be rich; He was made a curſe, that we might receive the bleſſing, even life for evermore, Love will make a Chriſtian ſeek the wealth of another, the reputation, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Salvation of another. Nay, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will prevail with us to ſuffer reproach, loſs, impriſonment, nay death it ſelf, when God calls us to it for the Churches good. 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 16. Hereby perceive we the love of God, becauſe he layed down his life for us; and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren.</hi> And <hi>Col. 1. 24. Who now rejoyce in my ſufferings for you, and fill up that which is behind of the afflictions of Chriſt in my fleſh, for his bodies ſake which is the Church.</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:56801:61"/> Hence 'tis apparent, ſayes <hi>Calvin, Quam non ſit ingenita nobis à natura charieas;</hi> that true Charity is not in us by nature, but a grace from above, really of divine original.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Love is <hi>not eaſily provoked.</hi> Before it was ſaid, <hi>it ſuffers long;</hi> but here ſomething fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is intimated, <hi>charitatem etiam in graviſſimis cauſis non facile iram effundere;</hi> that though the cauſe and occaſion be very great, yet love is not ready to be incenſed. I grant, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding love, a Chriſtian may be angry at Sin; but love makes him flye from cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſinful anger. The Scripture prohibitions are very ſtrict and ſevere, <hi>Eccleſ. 7. 9. Be not haſty in thy Spirit to be angry; for anger reſteth in the boſom of fools.</hi> Pſal. 37. 8. <hi>Ceaſe from anger and forſake wrath; fret not thy ſelf in any wiſe to do evil.</hi> Anger and wrath, what harm has it done in the Chriſtian World! what rents, what diviſions has it made! bitter fruit has grown from this root of bitterneſs. <hi>The wrath of man worketh not the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> nor his Churches good: and therefore Love, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates anger, and mortifies what is ſinful and hurtful in it, muſt needs do the Church a kindneſs. Alas! poor <hi>England!</hi> and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Church in it! how many parties are there, and how high their exaſperations! but their <hi>fury</hi> one againſt another is a <hi>perfect fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy;</hi> which has a certain and ſpeedy tendency unto an <hi>univerſal</hi> deſtruction. <hi>Want of love</hi> is
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:56801:61"/> one of the cleareſt demonſtrations that there is <hi>want of Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Love <hi>thinketh no evil,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'tis not apt to impute evil to another; but to aconſtrue the words and actions of others in the beſt ſence which they can bear. 'Tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry far from imagining and contriving evil and miſchief againſt another. To ruine men in their Eſtates; to blaſt their Names; to wound their Conſciences; to rid the World of them; theſe are none of Loves contrivances. And as Love carries on no evil deſigns; ſo it is not <hi>ſuſpicious that others do.</hi> Theſe ſuſpicions are very bad; for if the mind be full of them, it will be apt to meditate revenge, upon <hi>bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fancyed and ſuppoſed</hi> injuries; though the Chriſtian Religion forbids revenging <hi>reel</hi> ones. Want of love makes us imagine that others have contrivances againſt us, to undermine our intereſt and repute, and to do us ſome great harm; when indeed the juſt contrary may be true: and when we think ſo ill of them, our carriage towards them may be as ill as our thoughts. But love is too full of candour to give way to groundleſs jealouſies. And if this candour did but more prevail; how would Edification be promoted! Suſpicions keep the ſeveral parties that are among us at a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſtance. Difference in opinions makes the diſtance; ſuſpicions widen it. Several <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> are apt to ſuſpect <hi>Epiſcop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Men</hi> inclined
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:56801:62"/> to <hi>Popery.</hi> Divers Epiſcopal Men, are apt to think that if ever <hi>Popery come in,</hi> 'twil be brought in upon the <hi>back of the Puritans.</hi> Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent parties are all full of jealouſies: as if they were all falſe unto, and deſigned to ruine utterly one another, and only to ſet up eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one themſelves. Now theſe ſuſpicions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there be moſt apparent ground for them, ſhould be abandon'd, and Love will not che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them, for they weaken the Proteſtant Religion, and divide the Church againſt it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Love rejoyceth not in Iniquity, but rejoyceth in the Truth.</hi> Though our Neighbour is to be loved, yet we are not to love his iniquity, but endeavour by Prayer to God, by Reproofs and Intreaties, and other wayes to reclaim him from his evil and deſtructive way: <hi>Lev. 19. 17. Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, but ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour, and not ſuffer ſin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye upon him.</hi> And though our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour has ſhewed himſelf an Enemy to us; and after fall into ſome ſcandalous iniquity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is endammaged, and diſgraced; love will hinder us from being ſecretly glad of it; nay 'twill make us really to pity him, and to mourn for him. What <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes is much to our preſent purpoſe, <hi>Prov. 24. 17. Rejoice not when thine Enemy falleth, neither let thy heart be glad when he ſtumbleth.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in the ſins of others, how helliſh is it!
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:56801:62"/> this is ſo far from edifying, that it makes a man exactly to reſemble the evil one who is the Churches great Deſtroyer. This very bad temper, how does it prevail at this day among many perſons of different perſwaſions! When they hear of the ſcandalous falls of others who are not <hi>of their Way,</hi> they are <hi>pufft up,</hi> as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were, and but too much pleaſed. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2. They hope that the repute of their party will be advanced, by the exclamation that is made againſt thoſe of another Party. And hereby they ſhew, that they value their own Reputation above the Salvation of a Soul, the Honour of God himſelf, and the general Credit of Chriſtianity. But where Perſons are thus glad at the ſcandalous ſins of others, there is certainly a moſt <hi>ſcandalous want</hi> of Charity, which ſhews it ſelf in proclaiming on the houſe-tops, what love ſhould make them to cover. Love rejoiceth not in iniquity, but it <hi>rejoyceth in the truth,</hi> and theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e is <hi>truly</hi> for Edification. Truth may be put by an <hi>Hebraiſm</hi> for <hi>true goodneſs,</hi> for ſincere Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, as the <hi>Antitheſis</hi> in the words mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts; or <hi>truth</hi> may reſpect the reality of love it ſelf. Love rejoiceth in the truth, becauſe 'tis an enemy to ſhews and diſſimulation. I might alſo adde another gloſs; We muſt not love any man, or any party, ſo as to reject <hi>Truth,</hi> but <hi>that</hi> muſt be own'd with gladneſs, on which ſide, or where ſoever found. The
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:56801:63"/> Philoſopher did ſay, <hi>Amicus Socrates, amicus Plato; ſed magis amica Veritas. Socrates</hi> is my Friend, and ſo is <hi>Plato,</hi> but Truth is more my Friend than either.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Love is for the Churches Edification, <hi>for it hopes and believes all things.</hi> It believes the <hi>beſt</hi> of others, untill that which is <hi>bad</hi> is ſo <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> and apparent, that if it does not believe, it muſt be <hi>blind.</hi> Though one that is truly charitable, is unwilling to be impoſed upon, yet of the two he rather chuſes to be deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through his candour and facility, than to wrong his Brother by a ſiniſter ſuſpicion. And where love for the preſent <hi>cannot</hi> believe, yet twill <hi>hope.</hi> If it ſees others to be never ſo bad, yet it hopes they may come to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mind, and how earneſtly does it pray for their amendment! The Greek Tragedian <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides</hi> tells us, He is the beſt man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>who hopes alwaies.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Dictator <hi>Fabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Maximus,</hi> did a great kindneſs to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth almoſt ruin'd by <hi>Hannibal, quia nihil deſperavit,</hi> he did not quite deſpair in <hi>Romes</hi> extremity. Love to the Church will hinder us from giving over all as loſt; and <hi>hope</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>kept alive,</hi> that the Church in time may become more pure and more united, will put vigour into our endeavours, to promote the Churches Union and Holineſs.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Love Edifies, <hi>for it beareth and endureth all things.</hi> It bears the greateſt injuries from
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:56801:63"/> the World, and yet wiſhes the World well; and it endures unkindneſs from Brethren, ſtill remaining kind to them; it is not tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the fancied intolerableneſs of any inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſo as to render evil for evil; it minds that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ. 5. 15. See that nonè render evil for evil unto any man, but ever follow that which is good both among your ſelves and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Love! <hi>How much want is there of thee in the Church of Chriſt! and how much does this Church feel for this want! it groans, it languiſhes, it dies daily, becauſe of thy abſence.</hi> Return O Love, return! <hi>Repair breaches, reſtore paths to dwell in, edifie the old waſte places, and raiſe up the Foundations of many Generations, for after all the moſt politick contrivances,</hi> Thou wilt be found the Maſter-builder.</p>
            <p>Having done with the <hi>reaſons</hi> which demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that Love is for the Churches Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I am in the fourth place to ſhew <hi>the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of thoſe excuſes</hi> that are made <hi>for the want of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Some ſay, they are bound to <hi>contend ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for the Faith,</hi> and therefore Mildneſs and Love in this caſe are but urged unſeaſonably; <hi>ſtrive</hi> they <hi>ought,</hi> and ſtrive they <hi>will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That <hi>ſincere Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>all</hi> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, agree in the <hi>ſame Faith,</hi> and their diſagreeing among themſelves, is the way not to <hi>uphold</hi> that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:56801:64"/> Faith but to <hi>deſtroy it.</hi> The Controverſies between them is about <hi>Circumſtantials,</hi> and <hi>external modes of Worſhip;</hi> they <hi>all</hi> own the ſame Doctrine of the Goſpel, in oppoſition to the Corruptions and Hereſies of <hi>Rome.</hi> That's a <hi>bad</hi> Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that does exclude Love. He that believes the Goſpel of Chriſt to be the <hi>Goſpel of Peace,</hi> cannot but follow after Peace; <hi>Fides &amp; Amor, quam benè conveniunt?</hi> How well do Faith and Love agree? both together make the <hi>Breast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate</hi> of a Chriſtian, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 8. Whereby his <hi>Heart</hi> is armed and ſecured.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others ſay, they will <hi>not halt between two Opinions,</hi> they will follow <hi>God</hi> and not <hi>Baal,</hi> they are for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and not for <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and are reſolved to have <hi>no Charity</hi> for the <hi>Beaſts Worſhippers,</hi> nor any Communion with them.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Do not call that <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſm,</hi> which Chriſt calls not by <hi>ſuch a Name.</hi> To charge all Conformiſts with Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, is an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavy Charge, as bold as heavy, and as unreaſonable and uncharitable as either. I am ſure the Martyrs in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, though Conformiſts, were enabled to ſuffer the rage of <hi>Rome,</hi> and loved not their Lives unto the Death, that they might bear their. Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the Idolatry of Antichriſt. Thoſe that affirm a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer to be a <hi>Spiritual Image,</hi> and conſequently a breach of the ſecond Commandment, ſeem to me to diſcover a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtrength of <hi>Phancy</hi> than of <hi>Judgment.</hi> I grant,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:56801:64"/> the Second Commandment forbiddeth the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God by a falſe <hi>medium</hi> or means, and ſuch a falſe means is an <hi>Image,</hi> for by this means the <hi>Glory of the incorruptible God is changed</hi> into the <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of a corruptible Creature, which we are forbidden to fall down to and Worſhip; ſo that the <hi>medium</hi> or means forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in this Law, is an <hi>object</hi> as well as <hi>means:</hi> Now thoſe who are moſt for Forms of Prayer, will deny them to be the <hi>objects</hi> of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; their Worſhip is directed to God alone, and only in the Name of Chriſt the Mediator. That Reverend Author who aſſerts a Form of Prayer to be an Image forbidden in the Second Commandment, yet does grant, <hi>That a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Man, whether Miniſter or of private place, may by the Gift of Prayer which he hath received, compile to himſelf a ſet Form of Prayer, and may uſe the ſame for his Prayer whether in publick or in private according to his place:</hi> But if a Form were indeed forbidden, by no means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a man make ſuch a Form of Prayer for himſelf.</p>
            <p>Further, Let me add, that all who cry out againſt <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> ſhould beware of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs,</hi> which is a great <hi>part</hi> of it. <hi>Rome</hi> is full of Cruelty, cenſures and condemns all that are not of <hi>her way,</hi> and affirms 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that they ſhould be Saved. Thoſe in whom Chriſtian love does moſt abound, I am ſure are come furtheſt out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and are likelieſt to hinder a return thither; what ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56801:65"/> and diviſions will do, I wiſh that time may not too ſoon manifeſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Others plead, that they are for a <hi>thorough Reformation,</hi> and the purging of all impuritie out of the Church of Chriſt; and they <hi>cannot endure</hi> ſuch as do things by halves only.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That 'tis the <hi>Glory</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches that they are <hi>Reformed ones;</hi> and none of them are ſo pure, but Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be advanced to an higher degree. The Compilers of the Common Prayer in the <hi>Commination,</hi> acknowledge that in the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church there was a godly Diſcipline,</hi> which is wanting among us, and <hi>they wiſh</hi> that it may be reſtored. So that a need of Reformation in Diſcipline is here plainly confeſſed, and the thing deſired: But a Reformation is regularly to be endeavoured, no man uſing unwarrantable means, nor tranſgreſſing the bounds of his vocation. And while we are talking againſt Impurity in adminiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ions, (which the more exactly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, the purer, and the purer the better and more effectual) let us not overlook ſome of the <hi>worſt impurities</hi> of all; Pride, and Envy, and Hatred, and Wrath are the Impurities of the Devil himſelf; other ſins may have more of the <hi>Bruit</hi> or of the <hi>Child;</hi> but theſe have more of <hi>Beelzebub;</hi> 'till thou art <hi>reconciled</hi> to thy Brother, 'think not that thy <hi>Offering</hi> will be accepted, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 24. while thy Heart is full of bitterneſs, and Self-conceit,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:56801:65"/> and Strife, do not imagine thou canſt be a <hi>pure</hi> Worſhipper.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Others ſay, What, ſhall we Love a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> that are for returning to the <hi>Onions</hi> and <hi>Garlick</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and will receive the mark of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> it ſelf?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That the Scripture ſhould be Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died and underſtood, or elſe it may eaſily be miſapplyed. 'Twould better become men ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly to prove a thing to be Antichriſtian, than loudly and boldly to call it ſo. Shall he be branded as an Apoſtate, who manifeſts in his whole Converſation a fear of God, that loves the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity, that owns the great fundamental truths of the Goſpel, and is willing, if called to it, to ſeal them with his blood; ſhall he, I ſay, be branded as an Apoſtate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to give a <hi>legal ſatisfaction</hi> and ſhew he is no Papiſt, he ſometimes hears the Prayers of the Church, and Scriptures read in a known Tongue? Certainly the Cenſurer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> greater Apoſtate from <hi>Love,</hi> than this man is from <hi>Truth.</hi> Though the well-meaning of Perſons is to be well taken, and whatever of God is in them is to be loved and encouraged; yet this is to be diſliked, that differences between Proteſtants are made to ſeem greater than they are. It does not argue an healing Spirit to call every thing we diſlike, <hi>Egyptian</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh.</hi> This <hi>uncharitable Cenſuring,</hi> if it be not the <hi>mark of the Beaſt,</hi> 'tis the mark of <hi>one</hi> as
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:56801:66"/> 
               <hi>bad;</hi> you know who is ſtyled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Others ſay, That many who pretend to Religion and Conſcience, are <hi>Schiſmatical and Rebellious,</hi> and Love and Countenance does but harden and encourage them in their pernicious wayes, to the Prejudice both of Church and State.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Particular perſons who are culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let them hear the blame; but why ſhould all Diſſenters be judged <hi>Rebels?</hi> how peaceably have they carried themſelves for theſe many Years? how fervently do they Pray for the Kings Life and Proſperity? To Aſſaſſinate his Majeſty or the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> they look upon as an action moſt abominable, and are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that every one that names the Name of Chriſt, ſhould utterly abhor <hi>ſuch a Villanous Iniquity.</hi> They look upon <hi>Solomon</hi> not as ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like a <hi>politick Prince,</hi> but as declaring the <hi>mind of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Holy Ghoſt,</hi> when he ſayes, <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change,</hi> Prov. 24. 21. They are ſenſible that the <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> in the latter dayes have this Character, that they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Government,</hi> that <hi>They are preſumptuous and ſelf-willed, and are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 10. Let thoſe who are full of bitter Invectives againſt Diſſenters, as if they were Enemies to Government, conſider what the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> at <hi>Weſiminſter</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:56801:66"/> and the <hi>Congregational Divines</hi> at the <hi>Savoy</hi> ſay the ſame; <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> Chap. <hi>of the Civil Magiſtrate: It is the Duty of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to Pray for Magiſtrates, to honour their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to pay them Tribute and other Dues, to obey their lawful Commands, and to be ſubject to their Authority for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Infidelity or Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Religion, <hi>does not make void the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates juſt and legal Authority, nor free the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their due Obedience to him, from which Eccleſiaſtical perſons are not exempted; much leſs hath the Pope any power or juriſdiction over them in their Dominions, or over any of their People, and leaſt of all to deprive them of their Dominions or Lives, if he ſhall judge them to be Hereticks, or upon any other pretence whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the Charge of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wiſh there were no ſuch thing in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Chriſt; that Terms of Communion might be only Scriptural, and that all occaſions of Diviſion might be taken away. They <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> and that ſhe may have more True Lovers, and <hi>That all may proſper who Love her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come in the laſt place to the Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>USE I. Of <hi>Information:</hi> If Love be for the Churches Edification, then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence we may be informed, that <hi>Hatred, Variance, Emulations, Wraths, Strifes,</hi> and ſuch
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:56801:67"/> works of the Fleſh, <hi>tend to the Churches Ruine:</hi> they that harbour ſuch ſins as theſe, and are not concerned about the mortification of them, they are frantick Chriſtians, who caſt <hi>Fire-brands, and Arrows, and Death,</hi> doing much miſchief to others, but moſt to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. No wonder <hi>that Satan who labours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Churches,</hi> endeavours to <hi>kill Love.</hi> He is the envious one that ſows ill Weeds, he is the Father of Lies and Errors, he knows <hi>Errour</hi> tends to <hi>Diviſion,</hi> he ſets an Edge on the Paſſions of men, and makes them more ſharp and keen, he is the grand <hi>incendia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> in Churches, ſetting all in a flame, and he hopes this flame will conſume all before it, nay, burn at laſt to the loweſt Hell.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe <hi>Principles are trueſt and beſt,</hi> that tend to the <hi>begetting and increaſing of Love.</hi> The Church of Chriſt is little beholding to thoſe who are of <hi>narrow Principles,</hi> that mind only a <hi>part,</hi> but not the <hi>whole.</hi> The Apoſtle blamed the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for being of ſuch a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Spirit, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 12. Now this I ſay, that every one of you ſaith, I am of Paul, and I of Apollo, and I of Cephas;</hi> whereas all true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſhould reckon themſelves <hi>one</hi> in God and Chriſt, and conſequently ſhould be for one another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence we may be informed, that <hi>Love is the more excellent way.</hi> Rigour and Fury may force men to a diſſembled Compliance, but
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:56801:67"/> Love is the way indeed to win them. I don't think it a Credit to the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> that it muſt be ſeconded with the knocking argument of an <hi>iron Mace;</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition</hi> ſhews the <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of that Religion, which cannot ſtand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it has the help of ſuch Cruelty to ſupport it. Certainly that Church which is <hi>fulleſt of Love</hi> is the <hi>trueſt</hi> and wiſeſt, and moſt likely to be enlarged. The Apoſtle preferrs Charity before the <hi>Faith of Miracles,</hi> though theſe Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles mightily confirmed the Authority and Verity of the Goſpel; nay, he preferrs it before the <hi>Gift of Propheſie,</hi> though Propheſie was the moſt <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of all</hi> the Gifts of the Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1. He was indeed a Prince among Preachers, and ſuppoſes himſelf better than he was, and to ſpeak with the <hi>Tongue of an Angel;</hi> yet ſayes he, <hi>Without Charity, I am become as ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal;</hi> nay, <hi>If I have not Charity, I am nothing,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>USE II. Of <hi>Caution,</hi> in ſeveral particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take heed of what is <hi>contrary to Love,</hi> as that which is <hi>contrary to Edification.</hi> Unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Cruelty, Rage, Revenge, Bitterneſs, are ſo far from becoming Chriſtianity, that they are againſt Humanity it ſelf. When firſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſſion begins to ſtir in thy Heart, <hi>obſta principiis,</hi> quench the ſpark; <hi>for behold how great a matter a little fire kindles!</hi> Jam. 3. 5. What is contrary to Love, is contrary to thy <hi>own</hi> Peace,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:56801:68"/> and may make thee a Diſturber of the <hi>Churches</hi> Peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed of <hi>ſinful Self-love.</hi> This cauſes perilous times to overtake the Church of Chriſt, <hi>2 Tim. 3. 182. This know alſo, that in the laſt dayes perilous times ſhall come, for men ſhall be lovers of their own ſelves.</hi> Self-love turns Godlineſs into a <hi>Form,</hi> argues a <hi>want</hi> of the <hi>Power,</hi> it makes Religion to be ſubſervient unto baſe and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh deſigns; and hereby the Goſpel comes to be ſuſpected, Atheiſm grows rampant, and the Church muſt needs languiſh. Self-love will make you unconcerned for the Honour of God, for the good of man; it will produce a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs in you of others welfare, and hinder you from truly minding your own. He that loves no body but himſelf, and matters not what harms befall others, ſo himſelf can but ſcape, is a peſt of the World, unfit for Chriſtian, nay, for humane Society. Antiquity has cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that Speech as infamous, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>If I were dead, no matter though the World were all a fire.</hi> The Self-lover is of the ſame temper, if he can but keep what he has, and ſleep in a whole Skin, he is not at all affected with others Calamities and Afflictions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take heed of <hi>ſcandalizing any.</hi> 'Tis the great work of Satan to cauſe Scandals and Offences; and he ſhews the depth of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and malice in the management of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Engine. He repreſents God as too
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:56801:68"/> 
               <hi>rigorous</hi> in his Commands, Chriſt as too much <hi>thwarting</hi> the <hi>glorying</hi> of the fleſh: He repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents <hi>Self-denial,</hi> and the <hi>Croſs,</hi> as unreaſonable and intolerable; and all this is, that man may be offended, and his Converſion to God, and Faith in Jeſus may be hindred. Our Lord and Saviour who is the great lover of Souls, ſaw the miſchief of Scandal, and ſpeaks much to prevent it; He pronounces the woful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of the <hi>World,</hi> becauſe <hi>of offences;</hi> but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially binds and <hi>fixes the Woe</hi> upon <hi>that man by whom the offence cometh,</hi> Mat. 18. 7. At the reading of this, methinks every mans heart ſhould ake, and he ſhould cry out, as the Diſciples every one of them did in another eaſe, <hi>Lord, Is it</hi> I? Am <hi>I the man</hi> that thou ſayeſt <hi>wo unto?</hi> does the offence come by <hi>Me?</hi> 'Tis our duty to <hi>love</hi> others, but to <hi>ſcandalize</hi> them, is to be <hi>greatly injurious</hi> to them; and that's not an act, a ſign of love. Much talk there is of Scandal, and there is much more of Scandal than is talkt of: 'Tis a ſore evil that ſpits its venom every way: It ſtrikes at <hi>Jew,</hi> at <hi>Gentile,</hi> and at the <hi>Church of God.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle cautions us againſt giving <hi>offence</hi> to any of theſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 32. True Love to our Neighbour will make us avoid Scandal as carefully as a Mariner would a dangerous Rock that may cauſe a ſhipwrack. Here I ſhall lay down ſome <hi>Poſitions</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Scandal,</hi> that you may have the truer <hi>noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:56801:69"/> of it, and may flee from it, and the woe denounced upon it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Every <hi>diſpleaſing of another is not Scandal.</hi> 'Tis one thing to <hi>offend</hi> a man, and another thing to <hi>make him offend.</hi> Barely to diſpleaſe and grieve another, is not to ſcandalize him; for if it were, then thoſe Profeſſors that are moſt ignorant and peeviſh, muſt be perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humoured; they muſt have their wills, elſe they will be angry and grieved; and the weakeſt (as one obſerves) muſt bear ſway in the Church, which they are very unfit to do; and the ſtrongeſt, even Paſtors themſelves, muſt be ſubject to them; for they are hugely troubled if they are in the leaſt croſs'd. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Profeſſors are of different minds; ſome may be angry and grieved at my <hi>doing</hi> of a thing, others as much diſpleaſed and troubled at my <hi>not</hi> doing it: Now, if <hi>barely to offend</hi> another, were Scandal, in this caſe both Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal and the Woe belonging to it, might be impoſſible to be avoided. A man may be offended becauſe I am not of <hi>his mind;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of <hi>my peaceable temper,</hi> becauſe I think not that <hi>ſtiffneſs</hi> and <hi>ſtrangeneſs</hi> is the way to unity, but mutual yielding and condeſcenſion; <hi>forbearing one another in love,</hi> Eph. 4, 3. 4. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving one another,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt has received both the</hi> one <hi>and the</hi> other. Here indeed I may be ſaid to <hi>diſpleaſe,</hi> but <hi>Scandal</hi> cannot be laid to my charge.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:56801:69"/>2. Scandal is <hi>a putting a ſtumbling-block, or an occaſion of falling into ſin in anothers way.</hi> This is the Apoſtles definition of Scandal: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he cautions againſt Chriſtians judging and cenſuring one another, <hi>Rom. 14. 13. Let us not therefore</hi> (though of different ſentiments and practiſes in ſome things) <hi>judge one another any more; but judge this rather, that no men put a ſtumbling block, or an occaſion to fall in his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers way.</hi> When Profeſſors of Religion are looſe in their lives, and hereby not only confirm the World in their reſolution to be unjuſt, and proud, and covetous, and prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of time, and filthy ſtill; but alſo convey into the Hearts of other Profeſſors, that ſuch ſtrictneſs as the Scripture requires is needleſs; and that men may be ſaved without ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect walking; here is Scandal with a witneſs, and 'twill be with a vengeance. And as the blinding and ſtupifying the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of another is Scandal; ſo the <hi>wounding of the weak conſcience of another</hi> by drawing him to that which he doubts whether lawful to be done, is Scandal likewiſe. Love here ſhould make us very tender. Thoſe who are for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous impoſing upon others, ſhould conſider that of the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Cor. 8. 12. But when ye ſin ſo againſt the Brethren, and wound their weak Conſcience, ye ſin againſt Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Examples of the beſt are <hi>not to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a doubting Conſcience.</hi> Every man muſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:56801:70"/> be <hi>fully perſwaded in his own mind</hi> concerning the lawfulneſs of a thing, before he does it; for <hi>whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin;</hi> and he <hi>that doubts is damned, if he eat,</hi> Rom. 14. 5. 23. I grant the word for <hi>doubts,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may be tranſlated, He that <hi>puts a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween meats,</hi> and ſo eats <hi>againſt his</hi> Conſcience, is damned; but if you conſider what follows, <hi>becauſe he eateth not of faith,</hi> it is truly rendred <hi>doubts;</hi> for <hi>doubting</hi> is oppoſed to <hi>faith,</hi> as well as doing that which undoubtedly is judged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful. Thus we find our Lord making an oppoſition between <hi>Doubting</hi> and <hi>Faith:</hi> And the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed to expreſs this doubting, <hi>Mar. 11. 23. Whoſoever ſhall ſay unto this Mountain, be thou removed, and caſt into the Sea,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and ſhall not</hi> doubt <hi>in his heart, but ſhall</hi> believe <hi>that which he ſaith ſhall come to paſs, he ſhall have whatſoever he ſaith.</hi> Certainly as nothing is to be done againſt <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſo nothing with a <hi>doubting</hi> Conſcience; for he that does a thing doubting, cannot do that thing of Faith. We ſhould not urge others to follow our example, nor to <hi>do</hi> as <hi>we</hi> do, till they are <hi>fully ſatisfyed</hi> as <hi>we are;</hi> nay we ſhould preſs the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, leſt we wound their weak Conſciences, <hi>Rom. 14. 15. If thy Brother be</hi> grieved <hi>with thy meat, now walkeſt thou not Charitably; deſtroy not him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt died.</hi> By <hi>grieved,</hi> cannot be underſtood, <hi>ſorrow,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:56801:70"/> 
               <hi>another</hi> does that which the Brother thinks ſinful; for this will not <hi>deſtroy</hi> the Brother: but being <hi>grieved,</hi> implies having <hi>ones Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wounded,</hi> and ones <hi>Peace broken,</hi> by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the example of another with a doubting mind. The Apoſtle exhorts all to have faith concerning the lawfulneſs of a thing before they do it; cautions againſt judging and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing one another, though ſome could do what others could not. And this is the way to prevent Scandal, which is ſo great a piece of uncharitableneſs. But here I muſt add, that groundleſs doubts are ſigns of weakneſs, and he is an happy man that is got above them; and information in order to this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is very deſirable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Pleaſing another ſo as to occaſion his <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, is Scandal.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> was a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Chriſt, when he thought to pleaſe him, and prevent his ſuffereings; but Chriſt repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the temptation preſently, and rebuked <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſharply; <hi>Get thee behind me Satan;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>thou art my Scandal,</hi> thou <hi>ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but thoſe things which be of men,</hi> Mat. 16. 22, 23. The ſame Apoſtle (as one obſerves) ſcandaliz'd the <hi>Jews</hi> by pleaſing them: For fear of <hi>offending</hi> the weak <hi>Judaizing Chriſtians,</hi> he ſeparated from familiar communion with the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> by which he laid a ſtumbling block before them, to harden them in the ſinful opinion of <hi>Separation.</hi> A dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:56801:71"/> Scandal it was, whereby <hi>Barnabas</hi> himſelf was carried away. Love will make us <hi>pleaſe our Neighbour for his good to Edification,</hi> Rom. 15. 2. But to pleaſe him by doing as he does, ſaying as he ſays, and ſo to harden him in his too high thoughts of himſelf, in his errour and uncharitableneſs, in his dividing Principles, which have a tendency to hinder the laſting ſettlement and peace of any Church in the World; I ſay, <hi>thus</hi> to <hi>pleaſe</hi> him, is to <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize</hi> him by <hi>not</hi> croſſing and offending him. A meek and faithful inſtructing him, though it does anger him, would be a true expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of love to him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In ſhunning ſcandal, <hi>ſpecial regard muſt be had to the weak</hi> who are in <hi>greateſt</hi> danger. He that is weak falls more eaſily; and therefore ſtumbling blocks ſhould not be laid, but remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his way. Thoſe that ſuppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>higher</hi> than others in <hi>light</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> ſhould be the more condeſcending to them whom they think much below themſelves, and hear with their infirmities. <hi>We then that are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak, and not to pleaſe our ſelves,</hi> Rom. 15. 1. Thoſe that differ from us in judgement have precious Souls, as well as thoſe of our own way; therefore we muſt take heed of ſcandalizing them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaily if they are very numerous; We ſhould be wary how we utterly diſown a <hi>vaſt Body</hi> of Chriſtians, as if they were a company of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:56801:71"/> 
               <hi>Heathen men and Publicans,</hi> this will <hi>confirm</hi> them in their <hi>exaſperations and ſeverities</hi> againſt us, as <hi>highly reaſonable,</hi> and they will ſo fix their eyes upon <hi>that</hi> in us, which we <hi>cannot juſtifie:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that they will the <hi>leſs regard</hi> what we ſpeak againſt <hi>thoſe</hi> things which may <hi>ſtrongly be proved</hi> to <hi>need</hi> a Reformation. The more <hi>general</hi> a ſcandal is; the more <hi>fatal</hi> are the effects of it, and the more it proves <hi>detrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> to the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. All ſhould pray againſt <hi>proneneſs to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended.</hi> Others actions ſhould not make us forward to ſtumble and fall. As the <hi>providence</hi> of God towards us, though at preſent never ſo dark and intricate and unaccountable, ſhould not make us weary of him, or of his ſervice; becauſe he is a Lord the moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and his ſervice is really the beſt beyond all compariſon: So neither ſhould the carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of men though never ſo ſtrange and odd, and unexpected, occaſion our ſinning nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us in weldoing. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> men may be <hi>aſtoniſhed</hi> at the diſpenſations of divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, they may be amazed to ſee the world ſo full of wickedneſs, and to behold <hi>faith</hi> failing, <hi>love</hi> dying, and <hi>practical Religion</hi> ſo much ceaſing in the Church of Chriſt; yet they <hi>ſtir up themſelves againſt the hypocrites,</hi> they get over the ſtumbling blocks that are laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, <hi>they hold on their way and wax ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſtronger,</hi> Job 17. 8, 9. Fooliſn men! that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:56801:72"/> are glad of ſcandal! that run eagerly up and down, inquiring <hi>who will ſhew us any thing that may offend us?</hi> They rejoyce at any plea for a ſinful courſe, and greedily catch at any thing that may prejudice them againſt others that are not of <hi>their way;</hi> nay they are forward to ſuck in prejudices againſt Miniſtry, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt. A man that is ſwift to hear what may ſcandalize him; that is joyful upon occaſions, that make him angry and uncharitable, or any other way to ſin; he is like unto one that in a time of war does voluntarily run upon the <hi>Swords point,</hi> or up to the <hi>Canons mouth;</hi> or like one that in a time of Peſtilence, does not ſtrive to avoid, but to catch the contagion. A man that ſhould thus be fond of Plague or Sword, you will judge frantick, and he is in a worſe ſenſe <hi>frantick</hi> that is <hi>fond</hi> of <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</hi> That's the third Caution, <hi>Take heed of ſcandalizing any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Take heed of <hi>an unbridled Tongue.</hi> How mighty an hinderance of love has this little member been! Both Church and State have felt the Smarting and dangerous wounds, which a lawleſs tongue has given. The tongue of a <hi>Serpent,</hi> of a <hi>Viper;</hi> the tongue that is <hi>all ſting,</hi> and carries Poyſon and Death in it, is nothing <hi>neer ſo hurtful,</hi> as the Tongue of a <hi>Liar,</hi> of a <hi>Slanderer.</hi> The Apoſtle plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates, and the Prophet had done it long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:56801:72"/> that the <hi>Sins of the Tongue</hi> are the great cauſe of the <hi>badneſs of the times,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 10, 11. <hi>He that will love life and ſee good dayes, let him refrain his Tongue from evil, and his Lips that they ſpeak no guile, let him eſchew evil and do good, let him ſeek peace and purſue it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Four things are obſervable in theſe words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That an <hi>evil Tongue is the diſturber of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That 'tis a great <hi>indication of guile and hypocriſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That it <hi>very often ſhortens the Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That it is <hi>a grand Impediment unto our ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a vain thing to expect that times ſhould grow better, when tongues grow daily worſe and worſe; and neither Scripture, Reaſon, nor Conſcience can keep them to <hi>the words of truth and ſoberneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When there is ſo much <hi>evil</hi> in the <hi>tongue,</hi> how little of <hi>love,</hi> how little of <hi>good</hi> can there be in the <hi>heart?</hi> Would you have the Church of Chriſt edified? let not your tongues wound any of her members, though of a different perſwaſion from you. Do you love your Neighbours as your ſelves? be as backward to ſpeak evil of your Neighbours as of your ſelves. What our Lord ſpeaks concerning <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> may be applied to <hi>ſaying;</hi> whatſoever ye would that men ſhould <hi>ſay</hi> concerning <hi>you, ſay</hi> you even <hi>ſo</hi> of them. He that <hi>knew what was
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:56801:73"/> in man,</hi> tells us, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaks.</hi> Bitterneſs in the language ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a <hi>root of bitterneſs within,</hi> which the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er 'tis pluckt up the better.</p>
            <p>Take heed of ſpeaking lies to the prejudice of others. <hi>Satan the Accuſer has hardly a more exact picture in this world, than a Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lyer. Invent</hi> not lyes, <hi>believe</hi> not lyes, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> not lies. He that ſpreads a lye to his Brothers harm, is an hater of his Brother; he may talk of love, but is he a ſtranger to it, <hi>Prov. 26. 28. A lying tongue hateth thoſe that are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted by it, and a flattering mouth worketh ruine.</hi> Spreading of ſlanders is a ſign of hatred. Nay, you are not to ſpeak truth with an evil deſign; Clamour and railing at the faults of others, makes you faulty as well as they. 'Twere well if inſtead of publick defamations, there were more friendly, brotherly and <hi>private</hi> admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. That injunction of Chriſt, <hi>Tell thy Brother his fault between thee and him alone, if he hear thee, thou haſt gained thy Brother,</hi> Mat. 18. 15. is neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at this day, as if it were not in the Bible.</p>
            <p>Be not forward to pronounce judgment raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning others. Chriſt the <hi>Judge</hi> ſayes to Chriſtians, <hi>Judge not,</hi> Mat. 7. 1. You that ſpeak ſo much of <hi>ſtanding up</hi> for the <hi>Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of</hi> Chriſt, do not <hi>uſurp his place and office</hi> by becoming <hi>Judges</hi> of your Brethren; do not caſt that great command of this King of Kings behind your backs, <hi>Love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:56801:73"/>
            <p>Avoid <hi>partiality</hi> in ſpeaking of others; if you extenuate greater crimes in thoſe of your <hi>own</hi> party, and endeavour to conceal them, and aggravate leſſer things in thoſe of <hi>another</hi> party, and blaze them abroad; you <hi>reſpect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and <hi>are convinced of the law as tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> Jam. 2. 9. and ſo far as there is <hi>partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſo far there is <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> Jam. 3. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Tongues of Profeſſors! How long will it be e're you be quiet? How long ſhall your breath be li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Eaſt-wind, blaſting all about you? When ſhall all your words be agreeable to the Word of God? when ſhall your lips feed many, and hurt none? your reproachful, backbiting, railing language, your lies and falſhoods have been your ſin and ſhame, and the ſhame of Religion; repentance and amendment is abſolutely neceſſary, elſe Salvation ſtill will ſtand at a diſtance.</hi> Iſa. 63. 8. <hi>For he ſaid, Surely they are my people, Children that will not lye, ſo he was their Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE III. Of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> to <hi>abound in Love,</hi> which is ſo much for the Churches Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. My Exhortation I ſecond with theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is <hi>Love;</hi> his love is unconceivably great towards his whole Church, and every true member of it. There is not the <hi>meanest</hi> or <hi>most mistaking</hi> Chriſtian in the World, but
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:56801:74"/> if ſincere, God ſets his love and an high pric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon. Ungodly men are but like common ſtones; but Believers are Gods <hi>Jewels,</hi> and <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar treaſure above all people,</hi> Exod. 19. 5. And if God thus loves them all, ſurely <hi>they ought to love one another,</hi> 1 Joh. 4. 11. And they that <hi>dwell in love, dwell in God;</hi> now to dwell in God is to dwell ſafely, for he is the Rock of Ages; and in Him Mercy and Grace, and light and peace and joy are to be found.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt the <hi>Head is full of love to all the Members,</hi> among theſe therefore there ſhould be a moſt ardent affection one to another, and a great and ſweet agreement. <hi>Comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height; and know the love of Chriſt which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth knowledge,</hi> Eph. 3. 18, 19. And how will you be able to ſlander or injure, or be bitter againſt any whom Chriſt loves with a love that paſſes all underſtanding?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love is <hi>preferr'd before Faith and Hope,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. <hi>ult. And now abideth Faith, Hope, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but the</hi> greateſt <hi>of theſe is Charity.</hi> Faith and Hope ceaſe when we come to <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy;</hi> but Love never falls or ends. Faith <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives,</hi> and Hope <hi>expects,</hi> but Love <hi>gives</hi> the Heart to God, and for his ſake it gives libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to its Neighbour. Love is <hi>the bond of perfectneſs,</hi> Col. 3. 14. <hi>Charitas multos, &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:56801:74"/> unit;</hi> Love ties all other vertues together, and makes them more perfect and acceptable, and it unites the members of the Church to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which Church is the Worlds perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pſal. 50. 2. Out of Sion the perfection of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God hath ſhined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Love is a <hi>debt,</hi> Rom. 13. 8. <hi>Owe no man any thing, but to love one another.</hi> You are not juſt to your Neighbour unleſs you love him, and love to ſhew mercy to him. He that loves not another, defrauds him of what is due to him; nay, he is not only a Thief but a Murtherer, <hi>1 Joh. 3. 15. Whoſoever hateth his Brother is a Murtherer, and ye know that no Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi> And if he that wants love, is a Murtherer, 'tis leſs to ſay that he is a <hi>Schiſmatick;</hi> but he may truly be called the <hi>greateſt Schiſmatick</hi> that is <hi>moſt void of love. Haereſis fidei opponitur, Schiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati;</hi> Hereſie is oppoſed to Faith, and Schiſm to Charity: and if ſo, then they are furtheſt from Schiſm that are fulleſt of love; and they are moſt Schiſmatical, who are fulleſt of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and rancour againſt their Brethren.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>greater</hi> your love is, and the more <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> 'tis, it makes every one of you the more <hi>common good,</hi> the more <hi>Catholick bleſſing.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> is beholding to you, and ſo is the <hi>world:</hi> God himſelf is pleaſed to ſee your Charity ſo
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:56801:75"/> diffuſive and active; and your <hi>labour of love ſhall not be forgotten,</hi> ſhall not miſs of a reward.</p>
            <p>USE IV. Of <hi>Direction,</hi> How love may be <hi>revived, and increaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Obſerve the great <hi>defects of love</hi> in you, and be very much <hi>aſhamed</hi> and <hi>abaſed before God.</hi> How few of your actions and ſpeeches have favoured of Love! what workings have there been in your hearts contrary to it! Judge not <hi>want of love a ſmall</hi> offence, ſince 'tis ſo much call'd for both in Law and Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Seriouſly lay to heart how much <hi>Chriſt himſelf is concerned</hi> in and for <hi>all</hi> his Members, though their <hi>opinions</hi> may be different from <hi>yours.</hi> This good Shepherd loves all his flock, and he <hi>gave his life a ranſom</hi> for <hi>every one</hi> of them. Backbite not, diſcourage not, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute not, and eſpecially <hi>deſtroy not</hi> any one <hi>for whom Chriſt died,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 11. Every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar believer ſhould love the Univerſal Church; and ſhould have an intereſt in the Univerſal Churches love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Search the <hi>Scriptures</hi> that <hi>light</hi> may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. The more true <hi>knowledge,</hi> the more <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Eph. 4. 13. All ſincere hearts have a ſtrong diſpoſition to agree together in the truths of God, when once they are revealed to them. Pray againſt <hi>Errours;</hi> for as Errours are <hi>contrary</hi> to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:56801:75"/> 
               <hi>truth</hi> (which in all the parts of it agrees with it ſelf) ſo they often contradict one another, and naturally tend to make diviſions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be very <hi>bumble and ſelf-denying.</hi> There muſt be great yielding on all ſides, putting up many things, or love will not be revived. <hi>Humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind and meekneſs</hi> are the Companions of <hi>Charity,</hi> and cheriſh it exceedingly, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Put on as the elect of God bowels of mercyes, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, if any man have a quarrel againſt any. Even as Chriſt forgave you ſo alſo do ye, and above all theſe things put on Charity.</hi> Abhor <hi>pride</hi> which is the <hi>cauſe of contention.</hi> That is good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which I find in thoſe <hi>Rabbinical Rhythins,</hi> which if followed would increaſe love.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Thus in Engliſh:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let Wiſdom above all poſſeſſions be;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before Preferment chuſe Humility.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Every ill property be ſure depreſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But principally ſtiff tenaciouſneſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:56801:76"/>5. Mark them which <hi>cauſe Diviſions and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and avoid them.</hi> They that agree in Doctrine, and in the main things of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſhould not eaſily be divided: They ſhould think more of thoſe things wherein they agree, than of thoſe wherein they differ: And be ſure to deafen your ears to <hi>Tale-bearers,</hi> whoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to deſtroy Love, and ſow Diſcord. <hi>The words of a Tale-bearer are as Wounds;</hi> and how deep do they go? <hi>Where no Wood is, the Fire goeth out; and where there is no Tale-bearer, the Strife ceaſeth,</hi> Prov. 26. 20.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let this be your <hi>frequent Petition,</hi> That you may <hi>be taught of God to love one another.</hi> Pray that the Word, which commands Love, may be more deeply engraven in your Hearts, and rule there at all times; and that all <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperating thoughts</hi> and ſurmiſes, all <hi>unruly paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> which are contrary to Love, as enemies to <hi>you,</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> to <hi>God himſelf,</hi> may be brought into Captivity unto Chriſt the <hi>Prince of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>USE. V. Of <hi>Conſolation</hi> to the <hi>diſtracted, drooping, deſponding Church</hi> of Chriſt, and all the ſincere Members of it. The grounds of Comfort are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Church of Chriſt ſhall be upheld, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>withſtanding all <hi>her Diviſions.</hi> What heats,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:56801:76"/> what Hereſies in the Primitive times! If one reads the Catalogue of Errours in <hi>Epiphantus,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which men profeſſing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity embraced, and what rents theſe Errours made; it will be juſt matter of wonder that the Church was not torn to pieces by her own Members. Satan has been ſtriking at Faith and Charity; and yet ſtill there is a Church, and when he has done his worſt, there will be one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Love of Chriſt towards his Church is unchangeable.</hi> The Members may fail in their duty one towards another; but the <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> of the Head never fails. His care is conſtant: he is the <hi>ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever,</hi> Heb. 13. 8. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 1. That Jeſus <hi>having loved his own that were in the World, he loved them to the end.</hi> And this love ſecured them to the end.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There <hi>will be no want of love in Heaven.</hi> Though Chriſtians may not fancy to travel in one anothers company, yet they are all going towards the ſame Countrey, and place of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal reſt; and when they are once come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſhall reſt from <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>contention,</hi> as well as from <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>affliction.</hi> In that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious place and ſtate, there will be no errour, no culpable ignorance remaining; both light and love will be in their perfection; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:56801:77"/> perfect love is there, perfect peace and joy will be there alſo. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above is a City indeed that is compact together, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founded, for <hi>its builder and maker is God; Heb.</hi> 11. 10. and 'tis to laſt for ever, and is built accordingly. The triumphant Saints that inhabit there, how near are they brought unto God who is <hi>all in all!</hi> How cloſely and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably are they knit together in love! St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> will no more fall out, being both in Heaven; and <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> are perfectly agreed.</p>
            <p>When St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as he tells us in his <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> had been diſcourſing with his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning Heaven, the Crown, the Joys, the Peace, the Pleaſures there, his Mothers heart grew warm with Sacred Fire; and that warmth at length was heightned into an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Rapture;</hi> making her cry out, <hi>Quid hic faciam?</hi> What ſhall I do here below! How ſhall I with patience ſtay in a vale of fears, who have had ſuch a ſight of the glory, ſuch a taſte of the joyes of the <hi>New Jeruſalem!</hi> Certainly it ſhould make ſincere Chriſtians <hi>long to be above;</hi> and it ſhould comfort them that it <hi>will</hi> not be <hi>long</hi> ere they are above; when they behold the Church on Earth ſo <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>torn</hi> by <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and <hi>unruly Luſts and Paſſions;</hi> and when withall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that among the <hi>innumerable Company of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:56801:77"/> Angels,</hi> and <hi>all the glorifyed Saints,</hi> there is not the leaſt diſcord, but a compleat and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Harmony.</p>
            <p>I have finiſhed my Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Love,</hi> and the <hi>Churches Edification.</hi> I ſhall add a few <hi>Verſes</hi> which I made when <hi>Priſoner</hi> in the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalſed.</hi> I find that <hi>Muſick</hi> relieved <hi>Saul</hi> when the <hi>Evil Spirit</hi> came upon him, and <hi>compoſed</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of a <hi>Prophet</hi> when it was ruffled and out of order; and perhaps <hi>Poetry</hi> may have an effect of the like nature. The Verſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are theſe.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now uſe thy liberty, my Mind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who art not in the leaſt confin'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The whole Earth over thou may'ſt go,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And view the All that it can ſhew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And that great All which thou can'ſt ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is not enough to ſatiate Thee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From</hi> Gades <hi>to</hi> Ganges <hi>thou may'ſt run,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Thy thought's much ſwiſter than the Sun)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And in thy travel nothing ſpy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But what is vexing Vanity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The greedy Worldling ſpares no pains;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he has, the leſs he gains:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To profit others does refuſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay, locks up all from his own uſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Senſual pleaſures mixed be</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With an inward Anxiety:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:56801:78"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>The brutiſh part they only pleaſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But are the Mind's ſnare and diſeaſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Ambitious Man ſtrives to climb high,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That he may ſtand more ſlippery.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The gliſt'ring Crowns which Monarchs wear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Have leſs of Honour than of Care.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vain World! produce even all thy ſtore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou art indeed a thing but poor.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay, Heavens Heirs have felt thy rage</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In this, as every former Age.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If not by an exceſſive love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An Idol made of, thou do'ſt prove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Hell, or Shambles unto them</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who dare thee with thy all contemn.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Church is too much like the World,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into a ſtrange confuſion hurl'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Envy, and Wrath, and Pride, and Strife,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imbittering this preſent life.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By all is plain enough expreſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ariſe, depart, here's not thy Reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Trample on Earth, then take thy flight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Immortal Soul! <hi>Things out of ſight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Above the Sun, or any Star,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are worthy'ſt of thy thoughts by far.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let not thy Senſes Jaylors be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor what ſuits them infatuate thee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Open thy eyes, behold thy God;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Riſe with thy Lord, that thy abode.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>May be with him that's Light and Love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay,</hi> All <hi>in</hi> all <hi>that are above.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:56801:78"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Perſecution moſt fierce</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Can no way hinder thy Converſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With Heaven: Though in a Dungeon deep</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As the Earth's</hi> Centre, <hi>Foes ſhould keep</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Body cloſe, yet thou art free;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thy</hi> beſt Friend <hi>to viſit Thee;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The joyful tokens of his Love,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Priſons <hi>are</hi> Palaces, <hi>do prove;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nay,</hi> Paradiſes <hi>of Delight,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Although they ſilly Nature fright.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sorrow <hi>is</hi> Joy, <hi>and</hi> Pain <hi>is</hi> Pleaſure;</l>
               <l>Diſgrace <hi>is</hi> Honour, Loſs <hi>a</hi> Treaſure.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The World when</hi> worſt, <hi>is</hi> beſt <hi>of all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To thoſe God does to ſuffer call.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> New Jeruſalem <hi>comes down,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is clearly'ſt ſeen when Men moſt frown;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And with the ſharpeſt Thorns thee Crown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Take up thy</hi> Croſs, <hi>which is thy Tryal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And taſte the</hi> Sweets <hi>of Self-denial.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God is thy Father, and thy Reſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abide with him, and thou art bleſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Following Poem was more lately Compoſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:56801:79"/>
            <head>A Welcome <hi>to</hi> Diſeſteem.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>THe World's a</hi> Syren, <hi>and its ſweeteſt Song The greateſt Wrong.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' Applauſe of Men the Prais'd endangereth Like poyſonous breath.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Wings of Fame like thoſe of</hi> Icarus, <hi>Pernicious.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He that Ambitious is of Eſtimation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shews himſelf fond of Peril and Temptation.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'th moſt of Men a change is ſeen as ſoon As him i'th' Moon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A word, a look can quench the hotteſt Love, And anger move.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The fondeſt Friend oft turns the worſt of Foes, And fury blows.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſo does think to make men alwayes kind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He may as well attempt to hold the Wind.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:56801:79"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>On Mountains high the Tempeſts fierceſt are, And nothing ſpare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The tops of loftieſt Buildings in a Town Are ſooneſt down.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He that's Above, is envied to Death By thoſe beneath.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ambition does prove a fatal Charm,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And makes a man expoſe himſelf to harm.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconſtant World! how low ſhould wiſe men deem Thy high eſteem!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To better bad men, Honour has no force, Makes good men worſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Honour is fitly styl'd the</hi> Fooliſh Fire <hi>That flies deſire;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But fondly follows ſuch as ſcorn and fly it,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That they may be miſled and ruin'd by it.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>What peace and ſafety is in being low, The Prudent know.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſts Head did fly the Circle of a Crown And great Renown;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The whole World offered He did refuſe, And Meanneſs chuſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:56801:80"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>To follow Wiſdoms Pattern can't be folly;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſhonour's no juſt ground of Melancholy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Falſe World! thy ill report I'le not deſerve, It ſhall me ſerve.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy frowns and ſlanders ſhall a kindneſs do, Not make me rue.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When Friends turn Foes, and Foes more Foes I ſee, It weaneth me</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From things below, and kills exceſſive Love,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where doating my deſtruction might prove.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I will the Rage of Froward Men, and Spight, With Love requite.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It troubles me to ſee Profeſſors Ire Burning like Fire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I wiſh I were all Tears to check the Flame, And quench the ſame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If Wrath ſhut ears againſt my Miniſtry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I will to God for all the louder cry.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. V.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56801:80"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
